<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Root xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/"><body><p>Chapter 2 : The Basics</p>
<p>Classes</p>
<p>Classes are used to describe your character’s natural talents. This may or may not have anything to do with your character’s profession. For example, not all rogues are thieves and not all scholars are spell casters.</p>
<p>Your own physical characteristics and abilities need not match those of your chosen character but it can help you in your adventuring career if your actual physical skills are congruent with your character’s fantasy skills. The NERO system allows players to play characters that are very different from themselves and still be able to prosper.</p>
<p>You must pick one of these classes:</p>
<p>Fighter</p>
<p>Fighters take naturally to the physical combat arts and rely mainly on strength and stamina to accomplish their goals. They can wear more armor than any other class.</p>
<p>Rogue</p>
<p>Rogues have a natural bent towards dexterity based skills, and the practice of alchemy. Rogues are limited in how much armor they can wear. Their lower Body Points, lighter armor and relatively high costs for combat skills does not make them well suited for front line combat roles.</p>
<p>Scholar</p>
<p>Scholars are adept at many mental skills and readily learn the magical arts. Scholars are even more limited in how many Armor Points they can use than Rogues. </p>
<p>Templar</p>
<p>Templars are spell casters who are somewhat more adept than scholars at physical combat skills. They are not religious in any way; NERO specifically prohibits religion in the game. Their combat training leaves them better able to fight but takes away from their studies. They cannot use as many Armor Points as Fighters, but can use more than Scholars.</p>
<p>Races</p>
<p>The human race is not the only race in the world of NERO. There are many mythical and unusual races, such as elves, dwarves, half-orcs, and other more exotic races. Some NERO chapters have sub-cultures of the listed races.</p>
<p>Only the races listed are available for play by PCs. Some NERO chapters have additional races or variations of the listed races but these additional races and variations are NPC only and are not available for use by Player Characters. In order to give the game a multiracial feel, each race has been developed individually to add to everyone’s enjoyment. To keep the balance of each particular race, there are certain fundamental requirements that each player of that race must observe. We do this so that you will be placing yourself into a real culture that provides the most interaction with other players.</p>
<p>Racial abilities help you to understand a race’s outlook on life. You must understand the necessities of role-playing your race based on the advantages and disadvantages of that race. You should purchase your particular racial abilities as soon as possible.</p>
<p>Playing your race means knowing and understanding your races’ culture and society. Some races have their culture based on certain societies in our own world, some races are purely fantastic like the elves or hoblings and some are based on popular mythology or folklore. Other races such as the Biata have been created from scratch, creating a unique aspect to our game.</p>
<p>It is important to understand that this rule book only gives you a brief description of your race’s society. More detailed information on your race’s culture can be found on the NERO International website www.nerolarp.com It is very important that you learn the culture and behavior of your race so that you seem like a part of that culture.</p>
<p>If you wish to play a non-human race, you must wear the appropriate makeup to distinguish yourself. All exposed skin must be covered with the appropriate makeup. Any props (such as elf ears) must be worn at all times. </p>
<p>You cannot wear makeup to disguise yourself to appear as a race you are not, nor can you act in such a way as to mislead others as to your race. If you are not playing a barbarian or a gypsy, you cannot dress, talk and act like one. </p>
<p>NERO expects you to play your character’s race properly. Half-orcs should be slow witted, barbarians should act uncouth, and drae should shun the sunlight. Even though we strongly encourage everyone to avoid clichés and stereotypes when creating their character histories, you MUST abide by your racial characteristics. You cannot write your history to make you the “outsider” of your race and be the one barbarian who is a genius celestial caster, the one gypsy who is quiet and shy, or the one drae who likes to go sunbathing.</p>
<p>A player not acting as described for his or her character’s race will not be allowed to continue playing that character as a member of that race and will be forced to choose another race for their character. There is no such thing as true half races for purpose of NERO rules. There is nothing wrong with having your parents be of different races, but you can only take the attributes of one of these races. In-game you can tell everyone you’re “half-elf/half-gypsy” but out-of-game, you are one race or the other. You must then take all the advantages, disadvantages and physical characteristics of that single race and none of the unique characteristics of the other.No character may have the powers, physical characteristics, or mannerism of more than one race. It should always be very clear to everyone what race you are.</p>
<p>These role-playing rules are put in place to allow players to make assumptions about the races. When you see someone wearing pointed ears, you know that they may have certain abilities such as Resist sleep and that may change your strategy with dealing with them. You can conclude that every biata you see will dislike celestial magic and every dwarf will appreciate and study well-made weapons. Every race must act like and be identifiable as that race by all other players. By adhering to racial characteristics, this fantasy world of ours becomes much more real.</p>
<p>The following lists the basic NERO races (other than human). This is a very short overview. you play one of these races, you can find find a more thorough explanation for your particular race that will provide more background for your character on the NeroLarp.com website.</p>
<p>The skills mentioned in the descriptions ahead are explained in greater detail in the “Skill Descriptions” on page 33. When reference is made to“Scholarly Skills” or “Stealth Skills,” it means only those skills listed under those categories in the Skill cost tables. (“Scholarly Skills” for example includes Read and WRite and Read Magic.) Note that if you are playing a nonhuman, you should buy your racial skills as soon as possible. After all, how can you possibly role-play your race properly if you don’t have the basic skills and abilities that help to define that race? If you reach 5th level or so and still haven’t purchased your skills, other members of your race should treat you as inferior or look at you with pity because you cannot resist sleep or break a charm. </p>
<p>The next section of this book lists the various races other than human. If playing a human, you are free to devise any sort of personality you wish without any benefits or disadvantages </p>
<p>Barbarian</p>
<p>Barbarians come from nomadic tribes and are unused to “civilized” society. They are a very superstitious lot and may often perform unusual small ceremonies to rid themselves of their “curse.” (“Oh-oh! Seven hoblings just crossed path! Bad luck! Now I must tie string around finger and walk backwards for an hour!”) This is not to imply that barbarians have to be stupid—merely uncultured and somewhat primitive. In order to be identifiable as barbarians, you should talk poorly, dress in furs and leathers, and otherwise look primitive. Barbarian tribes (usually named after animals) are often very competitive and not too friendly.</p>
<p>Barbarian tribes are very earth friendly and in fact, celestial magic was unheard of by barbarians until the more “civilized” beings began moving into their area. As such, barbarians distrust celestial magic and consider it “not natural.” Barbarians fear and distrust celestial magic and will dislike having celestial protective spells cast upon them. This distrust only applies to Celestial Defensive spells, and does not apply to Celestial Magic Items. It should be noted that there are some characters that refuse to use Celestial Magic Items for role-play reasons of their own. This “Celestial Abstinence” is not required by the rules in any way. All players are encouraged to role-play their characters in any way that they consider fun. </p>
<p>When a barbarian reaches the age of 18, he or she will ask the tribe leader for a Task of Adulthood. This task must require an extreme amount of bravery and challenge and may take many years to accomplish. Only when the task is completed will the barbarian be considered a true member of the tribe. Barbarians who switch tribes are likewise required to perform such a task.</p>
<p>Barbarians are strong and thus start off with two extra body points. They have to pay double for all Scholarly skills. They can also buy the skills Barb arian Slay, and Detect Celestial Magic which, once a day, will allow the barbarian to determine whether an item has any celestial magic present upon </p>
<p>Biata</p>
<p>According to legend, biata are descended from a barbarian tribe, but they do not act or look like barbarians. They have large upturned feathery eyebrows and often grow feathers in their hair and claws on their fingers as well. (The claws are decorative in nature and cannot be used as weapons.)</p>
<p>Biata tend to be very orderly in their philosophy of life—they always act with a purpose. They will not do things “on a whim” and are always working towards some goal. To other races, this tends to make them seem like extremists—either very good or very evil—but even the most evil biata will have his or her own code of ethics and will never act erratically or randomly. This also makes the biata seem very stubborn. </p>
<p>They are also very secretive about the origins of their race and will treat all other races as “outsiders” rarely worthy of complete trust. It is said that biata were formed through magical mating of a gryphon and a human (or perhaps a barbarian). The Gryphon barbarian tribe was made up entirely of biata and until the last Great Celestial Change in 590, all biata looked like humans. Having celestial protective spells cast upon biata causes great discomfort. Most will refuse to sleep behind Wards and will not use celestial magic items. All players are encouraged to role-play their characters in any way that they consider fun. </p>
<p>Mentalist: Biata, like stone elves, have spent years honing mental skills and as such can perform certain mental abilities. These abilities are all completely role-playing in nature. Generally speaking, a biata can remove role-playing insanity based on memories or otherwise “cure” mental damage on any willing subject. You cannot use this ability to tell if another player is telling the truth or to have that player remember events forgotten due to a Forget elixir or otherwise get around any NERO rule. A player always has the right to refuse to role-play any of these skills and can at any time decide to “break off” contact or be cured. In order to use this role-playing skill, you must touch the other person and concentrate completely by either staring into each other’s eyes or by both of you having your eyes closed. You cannot perform any other in game skill while role-playing this. Any biata who simply touches someone and says “There, you no longer have a fear of heights (or whatever)” is not playing the race properly. For more information about these skills, see “Mind Abilities” in the chapter on Special Abilities. </p>
<p>Biata can buy the skills Break Charm , Resist Charm , and Resist Sleep. Biata cannot learn Read Magic.</p>
<p>Drae</p>
<p>Drae are dark elves, a mysterious race that mostly lives underground, shunning sunlight. They have jet black skin, white or silver hair, and pointed ears. They rarely socialize with other races. They keep to themselves and generally feel themselves to be superior to all other races.</p>
<p>When playing a drae, the most important thing to remember is honor. The Drae culture emphasizes honor to such a degree that a Drae who has lost honor should commit suicide as punishment before honor can be regained. This does not mean that you cannot be an evil Drae; it merely means that you will keep your word once it is given. If you are disgraced in any way, you will publicly do what needs to be done for your honor to be restored.</p>
<p>Drae can have a sense of humor but must take their own actions very seriously. There are drae entertainers (though rare) but even these regard honor as the highest attribute.</p>
<p>Drae have -2 Body Points in the daytime (defined as 6 a.m. to 6 p.m.). At 6 a.m., the drae loses 2 points from their maximum Body Points (never below one Body Point), adjusting their current Body Points to match if necessary. This means that a drae will never fall unconscious due to this penalty. At 6 p.m., the drae’s maximum Body Points go up by exactly the same number of points that they went down the night before. This rule cannot be used to circumvent other effects where Body Points are lost.</p>
<p>Drae can buy Resist Sleep and Resist Charm . They can also buy the Archery skill at half cost (round up), but they cannot use Two Handed Blunt weapons or Two Handed Swords.</p>
<p>Elf</p>
<p>Elves are long-lived people with pointed ears. That may be the only thing all the elven races have in common!</p>
<p>All elves can buy the skills Resist Sleep and Resist Charm . They have one less Body Point than a human character of the same class and level. They can buy the Ar chery skill at half cost (round up), but they cannot use Tw o Handed Blunt weapons or Two Handed Swords. </p>
<p>There are many varieties of elves. The most common are:</p>
<p>Amani elf</p>
<p>Amani elves are descendants of Quentari elves. Many years ago, a political rift developed in Quentari and many of the elves movedto the Ash Forest (or the “Amani” forest in their language) in the Duchy of Ashbury in Evendarr to start anew. Since then, they have spread all over the continent. </p>
<p>Amani elves are friendlier and more down-to-earth than their Quentari cousins. They get along much better with other races but still do not socialize a great deal with them. Even though they socialize with other races, they rarely marry any other than their fellow Amani elves. An Amani who falls in love with another race is not shunned from the society, but is obviously not treated with the same degree of respect by his or her fellow Amani elves.</p>
<p>Quentari elf</p>
<p>Quentari elves come from the elven kingdom of Quentari. They consider themselves to be the most civilized race; all others are barbaric in comparison. To some degree this is true—they have the oldest culture, the greatest cities, and the most learned scholars. It is this attitude however that makes their living with other races a problem, as no one likes being seen as inferior. Quentari elves tend to be scholars, and it is rare to encounter a Quentari elf who does not know how to read and write. When fighting, they tend to prefer bows and short swords, but fighting is seen as a last resort when peaceful negotiations are unsuccessful.</p>
<p>Stone elf:</p>
<p>Stone elves have whitish skin, upturned eyebrows, and pointed ears. Stone elves do not show emotions and as such are viewed by other races as humorless and intense. This is part of their culture as well as being part of their race. This restriction makes the stone elves very hard to role-play—if you cannot keep a straight face when told a funny joke, you should not be playing a stone elf.</p>
<p>They have a natural affinity for celestial magic and make excellent celestial casters. Although there are of course healers in their society, most stone elf casters are celestial. </p>
<p>Mentalist: Stone elves, like biata, have spent years honing mental skills and as such can perform certain mental abilities. These abilities are all completely  role-playing in nature. Generally speaking, a stone elf can remove role-playing insanity based on emotions or otherwise “cure” mental damage on any willing subject. You cannot use this ability to tell if another player is telling the truth or to have that player remember memories lost to Forget elixirs or otherwise get around any NERO rule. A player always has the right to refuse to role-play any of these skills and can at any time decide to “break off” contact or be cured.</p>
<p>In order to use this role-playing skill, you must touch the other person and concentrate completely. Any Stone elf that simply touches someone and says “There, you no longer have a fear of heights (or whatever)” is not playing the race properly. For more information about these skills, see “Mind Abilities” on page 93.</p>
<p>Wild Elf</p>
<p>Wild elves live in nomadic tribes like barbarians and share many barbarian traits. Wild elves are distinguished in-game by their furs and other barbarian clothing, even though they have pointed ears like all other elves.</p>
<p>Wild elves are not treated as “real elves” by most of the rest of the elven race. There is no outright warring going on, but the wild elves often feel as if they are second-class citizens even though they generally have all the rights as any other citizen.</p>
<p>The wild elf society places an emphasis on hunting and tracking skills.</p>
<p>Dwarf</p>
<p>Dwarves are sturdy individuals who live in mountainous regions. Dwarves in NERO are not necessarily short (remember that all players and monsters are the same size as the person playing them), but taller players should think twice about playing a dwarf. In-game, the rumor is that dwarves are the small cousins of hill giants, and so to the giants, they were seen as short.</p>
<p>Dwarves tend to be friendly but secretive. They all have beards, although many females prefer a long goatee. Their race enjoys and appreciates good craftsmanship, especially in weapons, armor, and jewelry. Because they live so much longer than humans, they tend to dislike the humans’ faster paced lifestyles (but they generally like the food). </p>
<p>Dwarves have an extreme hatred of trolls who often attack and take the dwarven caves for themselves. Their history is very lengthy but is mostly comprised of stories and legends of great dwarven heroes. Some of these stories can take many hours or even days to tell completely, and no self-respecting dwarf would consider telling an abridged version.</p>
<p>Dwarves are generally peaceful and have no problem with other races—although they think elves are pompous, humans are impatient, hoblings are troublemakers, and half-orcs and-half ogres are incapable of understanding the finer things in life (like a well made weapon and a fine wine).</p>
<p>They start with one extra body point, can buy Resist Poison, and can buy the Sm ithing skill for one point less. Dwarves cannot use Polearms, Staves, Two Handed Blunt weapons or Two Handed Swords. They must pay double for Read Magic.</p>
<p>Gypsy</p>
<p>Unlike other races that are distinguished by physical features, gypsies are defined by costume, behavior, and culture. To be a gypsy means to be boisterous, extroverted, and larger than life. Gypsies, a fiery and passionate race, love to dance and sing. The most important aspect of gypsy life is family. The gypsies have enormous loyalty to their people, treating each as a family member and referring to them as “brother” or “sister.”</p>
<p>Many gypsy tribes may coexist in the same area, each being ruled by its own Bandoleer or “Prince/Princess.” There is a Gypsy King but quite often this figure is far removed from normal gypsy life and has no great influence over the local tribes. Usually a gypsy tribe will have its own distinctive predominate color or marking, used to differentiate itself from other tribes in the area.</p>
<p>Gypsies can bestow or remove Gypsy Curse, the use of which is limited by the Gypsy Code of Honor. The Gypsy Code of Honor requires that a gypsy be always honest and trustworthy among members of his or her own tribe. The gypsy will support the other tribe members and will do whatever it takes to help (including lying</p>
<p>to, stealing from, and cursing or killing non-tribe members).</p>
<p>The Gypsy Code of Honor means respecting the actions of fellow gypsies as well. If a gypsy places a Gypsy Curse on someone, it had better be for a good reason (sometimes, the recipient might take action against the entire tribe). If there was a good reason, then the entire tribe will support that gypsy.</p>
<p>Half Ogre</p>
<p>Half ogres are not human/ogre hybrids, but rather are a race that closely resembles ogres in coloration and behavior and were dubbed half ogres by those that first  encountered them. They have yellow skin and protruding lower fangs. Half ogres are tougher than average and are almost always fighters. They tend to be less intelligent and should role-play difficulty in understanding complicated subjects. Note also that half ogres have a very short life expectancy compared to other races, and they mature faster, so that your starting character may only be four years old!</p>
<p>Half ogres are very tough fighters and they know it. It is very rare for a half ogre to show any fear. They are usually first to run into battle and will almost never run away. However, they have an innate fear of undead and will have to summon up a ton of courage to fight any zombie, skeleton or vampire that comes their way.</p>
<p>Half ogres tend to see the world in simple ways. What good is writing if you can’t fight with it? They think most of the other races are spoiled and live too fancily.  Half ogres would rather spend their money on new weapons and armor than on fancy homes, fancy food, or fancy clothes. Half ogres think that the concept of nobility is the most ridiculous idea “civilized” society has to offer. In the half ogre tribes, the tribal leaders are the best fighters. In fact, half ogres are constantly fighting among themselves for dominance. </p>
<p>If a half ogre sees another, it is likely that they will fight to establish who is dominant. The fight is never to the death but only until one of the half ogres acknowledges the other’s superiority. There is never any cheating nor are there sneak attacks in this sort of battle; there is great honor at stake in the half ogre community.</p>
<p>They start with two extra Body Points and must pay double for all Scholarly skills see Table 3-2 on page 30. Half Ogres may purchase the skill Strong-arm once.</p>
<p>Half Orc</p>
<p>Half orcs may have at one time been human/orc hybrids but have now evolved into a race of their own. They have green skin and protruding lower fangs or teeth. They are a strong people, but tend to be less intelligent and should role-play difficulty in understanding complicated subjects. Because of this Orcish Society is primitive and brutal. Orcish culture is based on the concepts of might makes right. They would rather die in combat than of old age, and would never be seen running from a battle unless the situation was completely overwhelming. Scholars are very respected among the Half Orcs as wise-ones and healers, and the harming of one can carry dire consequences.</p>
<p>The half orc society is clan-based, where families and blood relations are regarded as most important. Individual half orcs may leave the family to adventure with other races in order to gain in strength and earn a name for themselves. Half Orcs reach maturity quickly, and most are capable of using a weapon at age 4. </p>
<p>Half orcs start with two extra Body Points. They must pay double for all Scholarly skills see Table 3-2 on page 30. Half Orcs may purchase the skill Strong-arm once.</p>
<p>Hobling</p>
<p>Hoblings are peaceful people and generally are smaller than average. They have furry feet and hands, as well as bushy sideburns and eyebrows. </p>
<p>Hoblings love working with their hands and as such are often craftsmen. They are friendly and cheerful and have a great sense of humor, and quite often use their charisma to their advantage. Hoblings do not generally like adventure even though they love the treasure that can come from adventuring. Their treasure will be spent on fine food, good clothes, and a high standard of living. Their love of living well means that most Hoblings are business people first. The thought of doing something for free is appalling to them, and although to some this appears to be mere laziness, Hoblings consider this common sense. They are completely honest in their business deals however and always keep to their promises once made—however, you’d better read any contract with a hobling very carefully, as they know all the loopholes. They make excellent spies as long as the money keeps coming in.</p>
<p>Hoblings begin with one less Body Point. Hoblings cannot be fighters and cannot use Bows, Crossbows, Polearms, Staves, Two Handed Blunt weapons or Two Handed Sw ords. They can buy Pick Locks and Disarm /Arm Trap at half price (round up) and can buy the racial ability Resist Poison. Hoblings may purchase the skill Hobling Dodge once.</p>
<p>Mystic Wood Elf</p>
<p>Mystic Wood elves are an eccentric race originally from the Mystic Woods in Northern Evendarr. They are not really elves but were called that by the people who first encountered them. Mystic Wood elves have elven ears but also small horns on their foreheads. Popular theory holds that they are descended from elven-satyr/nymph hybrids, but this has never been proven. Mystic Wood elves hate (or at the very least find distasteful) all forms of enslavement, from slavery and kidnapping to magical charms and alchemical controls. For example, a Mystic Wood elf that finds a Charm elixir will probably destroy it. They may also attempt to break charms they find on others.</p>
<p>Mystic Wood elf society is organized into 3 major clans, and these clans are viewed as family by the Mystic Wood elf. Mystic Wood elves hold oaths to be extremely important. Mystic Wood elves have two names, their “road” name which they commonly use, and their “real” name which they usually only share with their most trusted friends outside the Mystic Wood elven community. Mystic Wood elves have a remarkably high tolerance for alcohol and love travel and adventure. For them, getting there is not half the fun, it’s all the fun. </p>
<p>Mystic Wood elves are natural born artisans and can buy the Craftsman (other) skill for 2 build points instead of the 3 build that it costs other races. For each level attained, a Mystic Wood elf must buy at least one skill from “Magic Skills,“ Table 3-2 or ”Trades and Crafts,” Table 3-3 on page 30 Mystic Wood elves can also buy Resist Charm for 3 build and Break Charm for 2 build. As they are not elves, Mystic Wood elves do not lose 1 body and can use Two Handed weapons.</p>
<p>Sarr</p>
<p>Sarr are a race of felinoids and many, but not all, come from a land known as Myrr. They live in a matriarchal society, with women outnumbering men several times over. There are multiple clans among the Sarr, each one representing a different type of large hunting cat. Each clan has different beliefs, leaders, history, and behaviors.</p>
<p>Sarr are curious, loyal, independent, and extremely proud.Tradition is highly valued among the Sarr. The Sarr race has an affinity for Earth Magic, but members of the Lion clan are known to be very proficient with Celestial Magic. This does not mean that you must play a Lion if you wish to use Celestial Magic, just that you may be looked down upon by the other clans if you break from tradition.</p>
<p>Sarr will form attachments with adventuring groups, but they will also strike out on their own in search of adventure when the urge hits them. Do not think that Sarr are cute little fluffy house cats; they are some of the fiercest warriors of all the races. They never forget an enemy and always seek revenge no matter how long it takes.</p>
<p>Sarr must wear makeup to appear as one of the large hunting cats. The bottom of the nose should be dark. Whiskers, stripes or spots may be added if appropriate. If you play a black panther Sarr, you must wear a prosthetic cat nose, cat ears, or other additions to make it clear to all that you are not a drae. </p>
<p>Scenting: Sarr have superior scenting abilities, and as such may detect an alchemical substance or disease on an item if they spend three seconds inspecting it. This racial skill does not allow them to tell what kind of alchemical substance or disease is present. </p>
<p>Sarr may buy the skill Resist Poison. Sarr cannot use Bows, Crossbows, One Handed Blunt weapons, Staves, Thrown Weapons, or Two Handed Blunt weapons. The only Small Weapon allowable is a dagger or hatchet. All weapons must be edged.</p>
</body></Root>