Chapter 2 : The Basics
Classes
Classes are used to describe your character’s natural talents. This may or may not have anything to do with your character’s profession. For example, not all rogues are thieves and not all scholars are spell casters.
Your own physical characteristics and abilities need not match those of your chosen character but it can help you in your adventuring career if your actual physical skills are congruent with your character’s fantasy skills. The NERO system allows players to play characters that are very different from themselves and still be able to prosper.
You must pick one of these classes:
Fighter
Fighters take naturally to the physical combat arts and rely mainly on strength and stamina to accomplish their goals. They can wear more armor than any other class.
Rogue
Rogues have a natural bent towards dexterity based skills, and the practice of alchemy. Rogues are limited in how much armor they can wear. Their lower Body Points, lighter armor and relatively high costs for combat skills does not make them well suited for front line combat roles.
Scholar
Scholars are adept at many mental skills and readily learn the magical arts. Scholars are even more limited in how many Armor Points they can use than Rogues. 
Templar
Templars are spell casters who are somewhat more adept than scholars at physical combat skills. They are not religious in any way; NERO specifically prohibits religion in the game. Their combat training leaves them better able to fight but takes away from their studies. They cannot use as many Armor Points as Fighters, but can use more than Scholars.
Races
The human race is not the only race in the world of NERO. There are many mythical and unusual races, such as elves, dwarves, half-orcs, and other more exotic races. Some NERO chapters have sub-cultures of the listed races.
Only the races listed are available for play by PCs. Some NERO chapters have additional races or variations of the listed races but these additional races and variations are NPC only and are not available for use by Player Characters. In order to give the game a multiracial feel, each race has been developed individually to add to everyone’s enjoyment. To keep the balance of each particular race, there are certain fundamental requirements that each player of that race must observe. We do this so that you will be placing yourself into a real culture that provides the most interaction with other players.
Racial abilities help you to understand a race’s outlook on life. You must understand the necessities of role-playing your race based on the advantages and disadvantages of that race. You should purchase your particular racial abilities as soon as possible.
Playing your race means knowing and understanding your races’ culture and society. Some races have their culture based on certain societies in our own world, some races are purely fantastic like the elves or hoblings and some are based on popular mythology or folklore. Other races such as the Biata have been created from scratch, creating a unique aspect to our game.
It is important to understand that this rule book only gives you a brief description of your race’s society. More detailed information on your race’s culture can be found on the NERO International website www.nerolarp.com It is very important that you learn the culture and behavior of your race so that you seem like a part of that culture.
If you wish to play a non-human race, you must wear the appropriate makeup to distinguish yourself. All exposed skin must be covered with the appropriate makeup. Any props (such as elf ears) must be worn at all times. 
You cannot wear makeup to disguise yourself to appear as a race you are not, nor can you act in such a way as to mislead others as to your race. If you are not playing a barbarian or a gypsy, you cannot dress, talk and act like one. 
NERO expects you to play your character’s race properly. Half-orcs should be slow witted, barbarians should act uncouth, and drae should shun the sunlight. Even though we strongly encourage everyone to avoid clichés and stereotypes when creating their character histories, you MUST abide by your racial characteristics. You cannot write your history to make you the “outsider” of your race and be the one barbarian who is a genius celestial caster, the one gypsy who is quiet and shy, or the one drae who likes to go sunbathing.
A player not acting as described for his or her character’s race will not be allowed to continue playing that character as a member of that race and will be forced to choose another race for their character. There is no such thing as true half races for purpose of NERO rules. There is nothing wrong with having your parents be of different races, but you can only take the attributes of one of these races. In-game you can tell everyone you’re “half-elf/half-gypsy” but out-of-game, you are one race or the other. You must then take all the advantages, disadvantages and physical characteristics of that single race and none of the unique characteristics of the other.No character may have the powers, physical characteristics, or mannerism of more than one race. It should always be very clear to everyone what race you are.
These role-playing rules are put in place to allow players to make assumptions about the races. When you see someone wearing pointed ears, you know that they may have certain abilities such as Resist sleep and that may change your strategy with dealing with them. You can conclude that every biata you see will dislike celestial magic and every dwarf will appreciate and study well-made weapons. Every race must act like and be identifiable as that race by all other players. By adhering to racial characteristics, this fantasy world of ours becomes much more real.
The following lists the basic NERO races (other than human). This is a very short overview. you play one of these races, you can find find a more thorough explanation for your particular race that will provide more background for your character on the NeroLarp.com website.
The skills mentioned in the descriptions ahead are explained in greater detail in the “Skill Descriptions” on page 33. When reference is made to“Scholarly Skills” or “Stealth Skills,” it means only those skills listed under those categories in the Skill cost tables. (“Scholarly Skills” for example includes Read and WRite and Read Magic.) Note that if you are playing a nonhuman, you should buy your racial skills as soon as possible. After all, how can you possibly role-play your race properly if you don’t have the basic skills and abilities that help to define that race? If you reach 5th level or so and still haven’t purchased your skills, other members of your race should treat you as inferior or look at you with pity because you cannot resist sleep or break a charm. 
The next section of this book lists the various races other than human. If playing a human, you are free to devise any sort of personality you wish without any benefits or disadvantages 
Barbarian
Barbarians come from nomadic tribes and are unused to “civilized” society. They are a very superstitious lot and may often perform unusual small ceremonies to rid themselves of their “curse.” (“Oh-oh! Seven hoblings just crossed path! Bad luck! Now I must tie string around finger and walk backwards for an hour!”) This is not to imply that barbarians have to be stupid—merely uncultured and somewhat primitive. In order to be identifiable as barbarians, you should talk poorly, dress in furs and leathers, and otherwise look primitive. Barbarian tribes (usually named after animals) are often very competitive and not too friendly.
Barbarian tribes are very earth friendly and in fact, celestial magic was unheard of by barbarians until the more “civilized” beings began moving into their area. As such, barbarians distrust celestial magic and consider it “not natural.” Barbarians fear and distrust celestial magic and will dislike having celestial protective spells cast upon them. This distrust only applies to Celestial Defensive spells, and does not apply to Celestial Magic Items. It should be noted that there are some characters that refuse to use Celestial Magic Items for role-play reasons of their own. This “Celestial Abstinence” is not required by the rules in any way. All players are encouraged to role-play their characters in any way that they consider fun. 
When a barbarian reaches the age of 18, he or she will ask the tribe leader for a Task of Adulthood. This task must require an extreme amount of bravery and challenge and may take many years to accomplish. Only when the task is completed will the barbarian be considered a true member of the tribe. Barbarians who switch tribes are likewise required to perform such a task.
Barbarians are strong and thus start off with two extra body points. They have to pay double for all Scholarly skills. They can also buy the skills Barb arian Slay, and Detect Celestial Magic which, once a day, will allow the barbarian to determine whether an item has any celestial magic present upon 
Biata
According to legend, biata are descended from a barbarian tribe, but they do not act or look like barbarians. They have large upturned feathery eyebrows and often grow feathers in their hair and claws on their fingers as well. (The claws are decorative in nature and cannot be used as weapons.)
Biata tend to be very orderly in their philosophy of life—they always act with a purpose. They will not do things “on a whim” and are always working towards some goal. To other races, this tends to make them seem like extremists—either very good or very evil—but even the most evil biata will have his or her own code of ethics and will never act erratically or randomly. This also makes the biata seem very stubborn. 
They are also very secretive about the origins of their race and will treat all other races as “outsiders” rarely worthy of complete trust. It is said that biata were formed through magical mating of a gryphon and a human (or perhaps a barbarian). The Gryphon barbarian tribe was made up entirely of biata and until the last Great Celestial Change in 590, all biata looked like humans. Having celestial protective spells cast upon biata causes great discomfort. Most will refuse to sleep behind Wards and will not use celestial magic items. All players are encouraged to role-play their characters in any way that they consider fun. 
Mentalist: Biata, like stone elves, have spent years honing mental skills and as such can perform certain mental abilities. These abilities are all completely role-playing in nature. Generally speaking, a biata can remove role-playing insanity based on memories or otherwise “cure” mental damage on any willing subject. You cannot use this ability to tell if another player is telling the truth or to have that player remember events forgotten due to a Forget elixir or otherwise get around any NERO rule. A player always has the right to refuse to role-play any of these skills and can at any time decide to “break off” contact or be cured. In order to use this role-playing skill, you must touch the other person and concentrate completely by either staring into each other’s eyes or by both of you having your eyes closed. You cannot perform any other in game skill while role-playing this. Any biata who simply touches someone and says “There, you no longer have a fear of heights (or whatever)” is not playing the race properly. For more information about these skills, see “Mind Abilities” in the chapter on Special Abilities. 
Biata can buy the skills Break Charm , Resist Charm , and Resist Sleep. Biata cannot learn Read Magic.
Drae
Drae are dark elves, a mysterious race that mostly lives underground, shunning sunlight. They have jet black skin, white or silver hair, and pointed ears. They rarely socialize with other races. They keep to themselves and generally feel themselves to be superior to all other races.
When playing a drae, the most important thing to remember is honor. The Drae culture emphasizes honor to such a degree that a Drae who has lost honor should commit suicide as punishment before honor can be regained. This does not mean that you cannot be an evil Drae; it merely means that you will keep your word once it is given. If you are disgraced in any way, you will publicly do what needs to be done for your honor to be restored.
Drae can have a sense of humor but must take their own actions very seriously. There are drae entertainers (though rare) but even these regard honor as the highest attribute.
Drae have -2 Body Points in the daytime (defined as 6 a.m. to 6 p.m.). At 6 a.m., the drae loses 2 points from their maximum Body Points (never below one Body Point), adjusting their current Body Points to match if necessary. This means that a drae will never fall unconscious due to this penalty. At 6 p.m., the drae’s maximum Body Points go up by exactly the same number of points that they went down the night before. This rule cannot be used to circumvent other effects where Body Points are lost.
Drae can buy Resist Sleep and Resist Charm . They can also buy the Archery skill at half cost (round up), but they cannot use Two Handed Blunt weapons or Two Handed Swords.
Elf
Elves are long-lived people with pointed ears. That may be the only thing all the elven races have in common!
All elves can buy the skills Resist Sleep and Resist Charm . They have one less Body Point than a human character of the same class and level. They can buy the Ar chery skill at half cost (round up), but they cannot use Tw o Handed Blunt weapons or Two Handed Swords. 
There are many varieties of elves. The most common are:
Amani elf
Amani elves are descendants of Quentari elves. Many years ago, a political rift developed in Quentari and many of the elves movedto the Ash Forest (or the “Amani” forest in their language) in the Duchy of Ashbury in Evendarr to start anew. Since then, they have spread all over the continent. 
Amani elves are friendlier and more down-to-earth than their Quentari cousins. They get along much better with other races but still do not socialize a great deal with them. Even though they socialize with other races, they rarely marry any other than their fellow Amani elves. An Amani who falls in love with another race is not shunned from the society, but is obviously not treated with the same degree of respect by his or her fellow Amani elves.
Quentari elf
Quentari elves come from the elven kingdom of Quentari. They consider themselves to be the most civilized race; all others are barbaric in comparison. To some degree this is true—they have the oldest culture, the greatest cities, and the most learned scholars. It is this attitude however that makes their living with other races a problem, as no one likes being seen as inferior. Quentari elves tend to be scholars, and it is rare to encounter a Quentari elf who does not know how to read and write. When fighting, they tend to prefer bows and short swords, but fighting is seen as a last resort when peaceful negotiations are unsuccessful.
Stone elf:
Stone elves have whitish skin, upturned eyebrows, and pointed ears. Stone elves do not show emotions and as such are viewed by other races as humorless and intense. This is part of their culture as well as being part of their race. This restriction makes the stone elves very hard to role-play—if you cannot keep a straight face when told a funny joke, you should not be playing a stone elf.
They have a natural affinity for celestial magic and make excellent celestial casters. Although there are of course healers in their society, most stone elf casters are celestial. 
Mentalist: Stone elves, like biata, have spent years honing mental skills and as such can perform certain mental abilities. These abilities are all completely  role-playing in nature. Generally speaking, a stone elf can remove role-playing insanity based on emotions or otherwise “cure” mental damage on any willing subject. You cannot use this ability to tell if another player is telling the truth or to have that player remember memories lost to Forget elixirs or otherwise get around any NERO rule. A player always has the right to refuse to role-play any of these skills and can at any time decide to “break off” contact or be cured.
In order to use this role-playing skill, you must touch the other person and concentrate completely. Any Stone elf that simply touches someone and says “There, you no longer have a fear of heights (or whatever)” is not playing the race properly. For more information about these skills, see “Mind Abilities” on page 93.
Wild Elf
Wild elves live in nomadic tribes like barbarians and share many barbarian traits. Wild elves are distinguished in-game by their furs and other barbarian clothing, even though they have pointed ears like all other elves.
Wild elves are not treated as “real elves” by most of the rest of the elven race. There is no outright warring going on, but the wild elves often feel as if they are second-class citizens even though they generally have all the rights as any other citizen.
The wild elf society places an emphasis on hunting and tracking skills.
Dwarf
Dwarves are sturdy individuals who live in mountainous regions. Dwarves in NERO are not necessarily short (remember that all players and monsters are the same size as the person playing them), but taller players should think twice about playing a dwarf. In-game, the rumor is that dwarves are the small cousins of hill giants, and so to the giants, they were seen as short.
Dwarves tend to be friendly but secretive. They all have beards, although many females prefer a long goatee. Their race enjoys and appreciates good craftsmanship, especially in weapons, armor, and jewelry. Because they live so much longer than humans, they tend to dislike the humans’ faster paced lifestyles (but they generally like the food). 
Dwarves have an extreme hatred of trolls who often attack and take the dwarven caves for themselves. Their history is very lengthy but is mostly comprised of stories and legends of great dwarven heroes. Some of these stories can take many hours or even days to tell completely, and no self-respecting dwarf would consider telling an abridged version.
Dwarves are generally peaceful and have no problem with other races—although they think elves are pompous, humans are impatient, hoblings are troublemakers, and half-orcs and-half ogres are incapable of understanding the finer things in life (like a well made weapon and a fine wine).
They start with one extra body point, can buy Resist Poison, and can buy the Sm ithing skill for one point less. Dwarves cannot use Polearms, Staves, Two Handed Blunt weapons or Two Handed Swords. They must pay double for Read Magic.
Gypsy
Unlike other races that are distinguished by physical features, gypsies are defined by costume, behavior, and culture. To be a gypsy means to be boisterous, extroverted, and larger than life. Gypsies, a fiery and passionate race, love to dance and sing. The most important aspect of gypsy life is family. The gypsies have enormous loyalty to their people, treating each as a family member and referring to them as “brother” or “sister.”
Many gypsy tribes may coexist in the same area, each being ruled by its own Bandoleer or “Prince/Princess.” There is a Gypsy King but quite often this figure is far removed from normal gypsy life and has no great influence over the local tribes. Usually a gypsy tribe will have its own distinctive predominate color or marking, used to differentiate itself from other tribes in the area.
Gypsies can bestow or remove Gypsy Curse, the use of which is limited by the Gypsy Code of Honor. The Gypsy Code of Honor requires that a gypsy be always honest and trustworthy among members of his or her own tribe. The gypsy will support the other tribe members and will do whatever it takes to help (including lying
to, stealing from, and cursing or killing non-tribe members).
The Gypsy Code of Honor means respecting the actions of fellow gypsies as well. If a gypsy places a Gypsy Curse on someone, it had better be for a good reason (sometimes, the recipient might take action against the entire tribe). If there was a good reason, then the entire tribe will support that gypsy.
Half Ogre
Half ogres are not human/ogre hybrids, but rather are a race that closely resembles ogres in coloration and behavior and were dubbed half ogres by those that first  encountered them. They have yellow skin and protruding lower fangs. Half ogres are tougher than average and are almost always fighters. They tend to be less intelligent and should role-play difficulty in understanding complicated subjects. Note also that half ogres have a very short life expectancy compared to other races, and they mature faster, so that your starting character may only be four years old!
Half ogres are very tough fighters and they know it. It is very rare for a half ogre to show any fear. They are usually first to run into battle and will almost never run away. However, they have an innate fear of undead and will have to summon up a ton of courage to fight any zombie, skeleton or vampire that comes their way.
Half ogres tend to see the world in simple ways. What good is writing if you can’t fight with it? They think most of the other races are spoiled and live too fancily.  Half ogres would rather spend their money on new weapons and armor than on fancy homes, fancy food, or fancy clothes. Half ogres think that the concept of nobility is the most ridiculous idea “civilized” society has to offer. In the half ogre tribes, the tribal leaders are the best fighters. In fact, half ogres are constantly fighting among themselves for dominance. 
If a half ogre sees another, it is likely that they will fight to establish who is dominant. The fight is never to the death but only until one of the half ogres acknowledges the other’s superiority. There is never any cheating nor are there sneak attacks in this sort of battle; there is great honor at stake in the half ogre community. 
They start with two extra Body Points and must pay double for all Scholarly skills see Table 3-2 on page 30. Half Ogres may purchase the skill Strong-arm once.
Half Orc
Half orcs may have at one time been human/orc hybrids but have now evolved into a race of their own. They have green skin and protruding lower fangs or teeth. They are a strong people, but tend to be less intelligent and should role-play difficulty in understanding complicated subjects. Because of this Orcish Society is primitive and brutal. Orcish culture is based on the concepts of might makes right. They would rather die in combat than of old age, and would never be seen running from a battle unless the situation was completely overwhelming. Scholars are very respected among the Half Orcs as wise-ones and healers, and the harming of one can carry dire consequences.
The half orc society is clan-based, where families and blood relations are regarded as most important. Individual half orcs may leave the family to adventure with other races in order to gain in strength and earn a name for themselves. Half Orcs reach maturity quickly, and most are capable of using a weapon at age 4. 
Half orcs start with two extra Body Points. They must pay double for all Scholarly skills see Table 3-2 on page 30. Half Orcs may purchase the skill Strong-arm once.
Hobling
Hoblings are peaceful people and generally are smaller than average. They have furry feet and hands, as well as bushy sideburns and eyebrows. 
Hoblings love working with their hands and as such are often craftsmen. They are friendly and cheerful and have a great sense of humor, and quite often use their charisma to their advantage. Hoblings do not generally like adventure even though they love the treasure that can come from adventuring. Their treasure will be spent on fine food, good clothes, and a high standard of living. Their love of living well means that most Hoblings are business people first. The thought of doing something for free is appalling to them, and although to some this appears to be mere laziness, Hoblings consider this common sense. They are completely honest in their business deals however and always keep to their promises once made—however, you’d better read any contract with a hobling very carefully, as they know all the loopholes. They make excellent spies as long as the money keeps coming in.
Hoblings begin with one less Body Point. Hoblings cannot be fighters and cannot use Bows, Crossbows, Polearms, Staves, Two Handed Blunt weapons or Two Handed Sw ords. They can buy Pick Locks and Disarm /Arm Trap at half price (round up) and can buy the racial ability Resist Poison. Hoblings may purchase the skill Hobling Dodge once.
Mystic Wood Elf
Mystic Wood elves are an eccentric race originally from the Mystic Woods in Northern Evendarr. They are not really elves but were called that by the people who first encountered them. Mystic Wood elves have elven ears but also small horns on their foreheads. Popular theory holds that they are descended from elven-satyr/nymph hybrids, but this has never been proven. Mystic Wood elves hate (or at the very least find distasteful) all forms of enslavement, from slavery and kidnapping to magical charms and alchemical controls. For example, a Mystic Wood elf that finds a Charm elixir will probably destroy it. They may also attempt to break charms they find on others.
Mystic Wood elf society is organized into 3 major clans, and these clans are viewed as family by the Mystic Wood elf. Mystic Wood elves hold oaths to be extremely important. Mystic Wood elves have two names, their “road” name which they commonly use, and their “real” name which they usually only share with their most trusted friends outside the Mystic Wood elven community. Mystic Wood elves have a remarkably high tolerance for alcohol and love travel and adventure. For them, getting there is not half the fun, it’s all the fun. 
Mystic Wood elves are natural born artisans and can buy the Craftsman (other) skill for 2 build points instead of the 3 build that it costs other races. For each level attained, a Mystic Wood elf must buy at least one skill from “Magic Skills,“ Table 3-2 or ”Trades and Crafts,” Table 3-3 on page 30 Mystic Wood elves can also buy Resist Charm for 3 build and Break Charm for 2 build. As they are not elves, Mystic Wood elves do not lose 1 body and can use Two Handed weapons.
Sarr
Sarr are a race of felinoids and many, but not all, come from a land known as Myrr. They live in a matriarchal society, with women outnumbering men several times over. There are multiple clans among the Sarr, each one representing a different type of large hunting cat. Each clan has different beliefs, leaders, history, and behaviors.
Sarr are curious, loyal, independent, and extremely proud.Tradition is highly valued among the Sarr. The Sarr race has an affinity for Earth Magic, but members of the Lion clan are known to be very proficient with Celestial Magic. This does not mean that you must play a Lion if you wish to use Celestial Magic, just that you may be looked down upon by the other clans if you break from tradition.
Sarr will form attachments with adventuring groups, but they will also strike out on their own in search of adventure when the urge hits them. Do not think that Sarr are cute little fluffy house cats; they are some of the fiercest warriors of all the races. They never forget an enemy and always seek revenge no matter how long it takes.
Sarr must wear makeup to appear as one of the large hunting cats. The bottom of the nose should be dark. Whiskers, stripes or spots may be added if appropriate. If you play a black panther Sarr, you must wear a prosthetic cat nose, cat ears, or other additions to make it clear to all that you are not a drae. 
Scenting: Sarr have superior scenting abilities, and as such may detect an alchemical substance or disease on an item if they spend three seconds inspecting it. This racial skill does not allow them to tell what kind of alchemical substance or disease is present. 
Sarr may buy the skill Resist Poison. Sarr cannot use Bows, Crossbows, One Handed Blunt weapons, Staves, Thrown Weapons, or Two Handed Blunt weapons. The only Small Weapon allowable is a dagger or hatchet. All weapons must be edged.
Scavenger
“Scavenger” is a generic term used for any type not covered by the other races. They are humanoids with the characteristics of a mundane animal (rat, badger, skunk, dog, etc.), but not magical animals such as Drakes, Gryphons, Unicorns or the like. Players are free to use their imagination in creating a scavenger as long as makeup is worn and it is obvious that the player is not playing a monster or another player race. (For example, you cannot be a “cat” scavenger because there would be no way out-of-game to differentiate you from a Sarr.)
Scavengers should role-play their particular animal’s characteristics to whatever extent they see fit, but animalistic traits must be evident in some way.
While some scavengers are closer to their animal half and do not understand the concept of possessions or the niceties of civilization as do the other races, others are truly civilized cultures with long histories. There is no commonality between different types of scavengers other than the fact that they appear to be humanoid animals. Some scavengers are very hardy survivors on the fringe of civilization and others are noble beings descended from generations of city dwellers.
There are a few traits that these animalistic humanoids share just from being animal-like.
Scenting: All scavengers have superior senses of smell, and can use Scenting Abilities that allow them to detect an alchemical substance or disease on an item if they spend three seconds inspecting the item. (This racial skill does not allow them to tell what kind of alchemical substance or disease is present.) Scavengers can buy the skill Resist Poison. In addition the animal part of them makes it harder for them to learn to read than it is for other humanoids and thus they must pay double cost for all Scholarly Skills see Table 3-2 on page 30. Note that this does not necessarily make them less intelligent than any other race, just less able to read.
Cultures
In addition to playing various races, it is fun to play a character from an unusual culture as well. The in-game guides to the various countries and duchies of the NERO world can give you some ideas. The more cultures we have in the game, the richer the role-playing experience.
You might also wish to create your own culture. However, understand that you should be very careful about what you say in-game about your culture; because you may end up having to take it all back if the Plot Committee says no. You must make sure that nothing in your concept of this culture violates NERO policies, rules, or the in-game history! 
You cannot be a traveler from another planet or from the future or from a modern democratic society; the basic concepts of medieval society should still exist. Use the current countries as described in your chapter’s Player’s Guide as a guideline.
You should write up your concept of your culture and submit it to your local Plot Committee for approval along with your character history. If you want to show up to an event playing that character before the history is approved, you should refuse to speak about your culture too much in game. Also note that any culture suggestions, once accepted, become the property of NERO.
This is a delicate balance we are creating; we want to encourage players to create more than a strictly European medieval feel to the game while at the same time we want to prevent the game from becoming impossible to manage. We can’t have six separate island nations at exactly the same spot on the globe. That is why it is imperative that if you want to talk about your culture in-game, you must get it approved by the Plot Committee. In addition, you should be careful if you wish to play a culture that is based on a real Earth culture. For example, if you wish to play a barbarian based on an American Indian culture, please make sure that you know something about that culture. If you walk around saying “ugh” and “how” and calling people “Kemosabe” you may be asked to stop. The best bet is to not play a character from a real culture with which you are not very familiar. We love having characters from societies based on medieval Japan or ancient Egypt or the Hawaiian Islands or Africa, but we  definitely do not want players with no knowledge of those cultures to play insulting stereotypes from those cultures— even if no insult was intended.
The most important thing is to prevent your character from being insulting to people whose heritage really is of that culture. At the risk of saying we want PCPCs (Politically Correct Player Characters), please be careful. Just think first.
Monsters and NPCs
NPCs (Non-Playing Characters) and Monsters are guided by a Monster Master who assigns them duties. The Monster Master, in turn, answers to the Plot Committee and their weekend director. If an NPC character dies or completes his or her assignment, the NPC player must return to the monster cabin (which is off-limits to everyone except NPCs and marshals). They can then be sent out again as another NPC.
Many NPCs are used in set encounters like guarding a tomb or capturing a character. Others simply wander around the woods looking for unsuspecting adventurers to fight. There may be specific monster areas in the woods where certain types of monsters appear from time to time and wait for the adventurers to find them.
All NPCs aren’t necessarily monsters nor are they placed out there just for PCs to fight. NPCs may be bards and entertainers, beggars, merchants, hired thugs, or anything else needed to advance the proper town atmosphere. NPCs that are not monsters should be indistinguishable from any player.
There may also be some full-time town NPCs such as the major Guild leaders and some of the highest nobility. They are NPCs because they also serve a logistics function or because they are controlled by the Plot Committee. These NPCs, like all NPCs, have a limited number of lives and in all aspects must follow all game rules.
Players who wish to be NPCs get compensation for the work they do. In exchange, we expect our NPCs to do what they are told and follow the rules.
Monster Size
All monsters are the size of the NPC or physical representation playing the part. There are not any 9 foot tall trolls unless there is a 9 foot tall NPC playing the part or a 9 foot tall apparatus built for that purpose.
Matters of Life and Death
States of Existence
There are three Standard States that someone at a NERO event can
be in. These are:
1) OOG: Out Of Game
2) IG: In game and completely visible to those around you (Yes, you can try to hide in bushes, etc... but you actually have to hide.)
3) Spirit: In game and a spirit 
Alternate States (such as flying, burrowing, invisible, etc.) are not possible.
Out-of-Game
When someone takes themselves out of the action for their own convenience, they are out-of-game. In order to go out-of-game, you must wear a white headband. This signifies to others that your character is not there. Please do not abuse this, and note that your game items must stay in-game.
Bathhouses or similar facilities are out-of-game. You may not however run into one if monsters are chasing you. Anyone traveling to and from the showers may be out-of-game if they so choose. If they are out-of-game, though, they should have no game items on them.
As a courtesy you can sleep in a cabin out-of-game. However if someone has a real reason to pull you back into game, you may be disturbed. For Example, if you have an important game item that half the players are looking for, then a marshal may come by looking for it. If you have done something to anger another group, or even a bunch of monsters, then you may not run off and put your cabin out-of-game to avoid the consequences. A marshal will likely be involved and you will be presented with several options, such as; you are at the mercy of the injured parties or you may opt to fight, at which point combat could commence. In such cases, you will be given only as much preparatory time as you would have actual warning, again decided by the marshal.
You cannot go out-of-game in the middle of a combat unless you have a medical reason.
Hit Points
Your character’s health and the quality of his or her armor are represented by the use of Hit Points.
There are two types of Hit Points: Armor Points and Body Points. Armor Points represent the additional protection that is gained from armor. These points are usually lost first.
Body Points represent how strong and healthy your body is at that moment. When in a battle, armor usually takes damage first and then Body Points. There are exceptions. Some spells and skills state that only body or armor is affected.
Body Points do not regenerate from day to day but you will receive your full amount of Body Points at the start of each new NERO event.
Please note that there is no mechanism to dismember bodies in NERO.
You must update your Armor Points and Body Points at the end of a battle to reflect those lost during combat. This is done by adjusting your tags or updating your character skill sheet. Armor tags do not need to match the physical representation worn. If you are wearing a phys-rep for 6 points of armor you can use a 15 point tag, but you can only gain the benefit of 6 points of armor from that tag. In order to get full benefit from the 15 point armor tag, you must be wearing a phys-rep for armor that gives at least 15 points.
Life and Death
Knowing the rules in this section can literally make the difference between life and death. Some of this will be confusing upon a first reading, as this section makes references to rules that have not yet been covered. If this is your first reading of the NERO© Rule Book©, get the general idea of this section and then come back after you’ve read more.
Unconscious:
If you are reduced to exactly zero Body Points, then you are unconscious. You will regain consciousness at one Body Point only after one minute.
You can make no sounds at all while unconscious or dying. If your party doesn’t notice you lying there, you can’t moan or say “Well, it looks like I’m unconscious.”
Carrying the Incapacitated:
To carry another character or creature that is incapacitated, you must place a hand near the torso and tell the other player “I am carrying you”. The recipient must
get up and stand in front of you. Then you hold both hands over their shoulders to indicate you are carrying them. Both hands must be free. You must walk at a normal pace. You may walk forward or drag them by walking with them backwards. Whether walking or running you must wait for the person playing the body to get up and follow you. You cannot “tag” them and sprint, claiming that you have the body. The person must move with you. If a packet, weapon, or other game effect strikes you or the body being carried, you must drop the body. You may pick it up again once it stops moving. The effect is applied to whomever it hit, following all normal NERO rules.
All of the same rules apply if you use a game effect upon yourself, including Im prison, healing spells, or gaseous form. If you cast Imprison upon yourself or go gaseous, the carried body must be dropped and hence cannot be included in the effect.
Dying:
Any time you are reduced below zero Body Points, you drop to -1 and no further, even if the last blow to you did 48 points of damage. Once you are reduced to -1, then your character is dying. You will die unless given First Aid or curing within one minute. This one minute is referred to as your “death countdown.” First Aid takes a complete uninterrupted minute to be successful.
Once First Aid has begun; with the call “First Aid“, the one minute death countdown freezes. If you receive another hit while in this condition, then the aid is considered to be interrupted and you will continue the death countdown from where it was frozen by the First Aid. If the First Aid is completed, then you will be at zero Body Points (unconscious) and will wake in 1 minute with 1 Body Point. First Aid is not required if you are at 0. Curing that brings you to at least 1 Body Point will immediately bring you to consciousness without the minute needed for First Aid. If you are at -1, then for all healing it only takes 1 point to reach zero. So, for example, if you received 5 points of healing you would have 4 Body Points.
Dead:
If you are still at -1 Body Points after completing your Death Countdown, then you are dead. Death may also come from Killing Blows (see below) and certain effects. All
of your active spells, alchemical substances, and other effects will immediately disappear. The only things that will remain are Gypsy Curse, Forget-it-Well, Forget-me-Not,
and Enslavement. Sometimes, a Curse of Transform ation or an Infection might disappear when a character dies. No other game effect is active after death, except for certain
Formal Magic Spells (this will be stated on the tag). The only thing that can save you now is a Life spell delivered within five minutes. Even if a Life spell is given to you, all your active spells, alchemical substances and other effects (except those listed above) are lost. If the five minutes pass without a Life spell then your body dissipates, all of your in game items drop to the ground, and you must immediately become a spirit and can only be brought back by a resurrection
Killing Blows
There are many ways in our game to render an opponent completely helpless. These include Web spells, Paralyze spells, tying them up physically (thus making them immobile from the neck down), or just hitting them until they drop unconscious.
Once a person has been incapacitated, it is not too difficult to kill them. This is represented by a Killing Blow.
If the character is being actively guarded by companions, however, it is another matter entirely! When you have leisure to do so, it is easy to find a chink in the armor or slip a dagger under the helmet and deliver a Killing Blow. It is considerably more difficult to do so if someone is trying to prevent you from accomplishing
that very feat. Therefore, there are a few restrictions as to its use. To administer a killing blow, you must place your weapon or touch a packet in your hand somewhere on the victim’s torso and remain in that position while you recite “Killing Blow One; Killing Blow Two; Killing Blow Three <damage type>.”
If anyone strikes you during the count or knocks your weapon away, then the Killing Blow is interrupted and fails to kill the person.
Please note that even though there is a three- count for Killing Blows, the Killing Blow only counts as one strike. 
A Killing Blow must be administered to the torso of the victim; an arm, leg, or shoulder is not sufficient. Likewise, the blow cannot be struck on a moving target. If you have Waylaid someone, you must wait for the body to come to rest before you can deliver the Killing Blow.
A Killing Blow can be delivered by anyone, whether they have a weapon or not. Some creatures are immune to normal weapons. To be effective, the Killing Blow must be applied with a weapon that can damage the creature. No skill in the weapon is necessary. For example, if a creature is affected by silvered or magical weapons but not normal weapons, the Killing Blow must be applied with a silvered or magical weapon. In such a case, using a hand to perform the Killing Blow would not work.
Once a Killing blow has been given to you, you are dead and should begin your death count.
Spirits
When your character dies and their body dissipates (after the point at which a Life spell will no longer work) you must become a spirit.
You must drop all in game items, put on a white headband and head immediately and directly to your chapter’s resurrection point (usually the Healers’ Guild) to register your death. The spirit is completely invisible to the world around it and may not interact in any manner with other characters (no noises, no charades . . . nothing!). Spirits travel only as fast as the player walks—no running to the Healers’ Guild. 
It is impossible to burn or otherwise completely destroy the body before the five minute Life spell requirement is used up. There can be no effects that can accelerate the destruction of the body of a PC except for the specific exceptions outlined in the Formal Magic System. We know this doesn’t make complete in-game sense but this rule is to prevent every single kill from turning into a “Let’s burn the body!” situation.
Resurrections
Spirits are resurrected in Extended Earth Circles created through Formal Magic. Very often a local Healers Guild safeguards such a Circle in order to perform  resurrections. Upon entering the Extended Earth Circle, the spirit remains unable to interact with characters, but anyone inside the Circle and Invested in the Circle will “sense” a presence and will know the identity of that presence if it is someone they know. They may then resurrect that spirit, and after five minutes the body will be restored to the spirit. The identity of the spirit does not have to be known in order to be resurrected. You must be invested in the Circle to be able to start the resurrection, but once it is begun anyone with the skill of Healing Arts can complete it. If no one is available with Healing Arts, then the spirit can resurrect on its own once the Invested member has begun the resurrection. However, in-game this is very painful emotionally to the resurrecting character.
A spirit can reject a specific healer but stay in the Circle waiting for another person to perform the resurrection. The rejected healer will be aware that the spirit is refusing to resurrect under his or her guidance but will not be able to tell which healer the spirit is “requesting” or waiting for.
The spirit is not aware of any character plans to resurrect in specific circles based on the means of death. Thus you cannot say to your friends “If I resurrect in Bristol, that means that Enemy X killed me; and if I resurrect in Wildwood, that means Enemy Y.” 
The spirit will normally go to the closest Extended Earth Circle of Power to resurrect. No in-game knowledge is necessary for your spirit to find the “closest” Earth Circle. This includes Circles that your character has never seen in game. A spirit can choose to go to a different Circle than the closest one if the closest Circle is hostile, but the character, once resurrected, will not be aware of this decision. The Player, not the character, determines “hostility”. This is a fine point at best, but it means that out-of-game knowledge is used when deciding whether to resurrect at a given circle. For example, let’s suppose your character dies and a Forget poison is used. When your body dissipates, you go to the Earth Circle. When you get there, you see your character’s killer hiding behind the cabin where the Earth Circle is located. You decide to resurrect elsewhere because the circle is “hostile” to you. This is allowed and is well within the rules. As a matter of fact, no one in the game, not even a marshal, can require another player to justify why they decided that a particular circle is “hostile”. It’s an out-of-game decision made by the player, and can be made for no reason at all. The decision to resurrect elsewhere can even be made after the resurrection has started. Of course, once the resurrection is finished it’s too late.
If your character decides to go to another Circle other than the designated in-game Circle during a weekend event, you must go to the resurrection point out of-game to record the death and let them know what you are planning. You may be required to stay out-of-game for a period of time to represent the amount of time it would take for your spirit to travel to the next closest Extended earth Circle and for your body to then travel back. It is impossible to tell how someone died from looking at their spirit so at this point determining the method of death is not possible.  
Many resurrections are performed by a character who tells a story about the events of what occurs during the five minutes and the person receiving the resurrection may choose to have their character believe that story, or any other as they prefer. Each and every story should abide by NERO rules and any problems should be reported to a Marshal. 
At the end of the resurrection, the player must say “I reform one, I reform two, I reform three”. There is nothing that will successfully affect a resurrecting body during this three count. The last three seconds are considered part of the time in which the spirit “cannot interact with the world around it” and hence nothing will affect the character. You cannot begin any three count, including a killing blow, upon a resurrecting body until after the resurrection count is over. 
A newly resurrected character has his or her maximum Body Points and will awake from resurrection without any game possessions at all but clothed. All remaining spells and elixirs that were present on the character will be gone, including Gypsy Curse and Enslavement.
Anyone who resurrects at a full earth circle will have their skills renewed. This does not include craftsman skills or production skills, but does reset Formal Magic casting ability and Formal Cantrips. Most of the time, a Curse of Transformation or an Infection will disappear when a character is resurrected. Note that the lost memories from Forget poisons are not restored by resurrection.
No other game effect is active after death, except for certain Formal Magic which will be stated on the magic item tag.
Each time your character dies, he or she adds another Death to their Death Total. Every character gets two guaranteed resurrections.
After that, there is a chance of dying permanently and not coming back.
When you show up at the earth Circle to resurrect, a Marshal will update your Death Total and then will ask you to choose from the Bag of Chance.
In the bag will be ten stones. There will be one Death Stone for each time you have died beyond the two free resurrections. In addition, there will be a number of Life Stones put into the bag so that the total number of stones is always ten. If you choose a Life Stone, then you can successfully be resurrected. 
If you pick a Death Stone, then your character has permanently died. At this point, your character’s body reforms exactly where it dissipated. The body will remain there until someone finds it and takes it.
However, lying out in the middle of the woods all night hoping someone finds your body is not fun for most players. Therefore it is completely acceptable to leave a note saying “You see Raymond’s body here.” Any spirit-linked items will remain there and will be spirit-linked to the next appropriate person who touches them.
First Event Deaths:
Any first-time NERO player will not have any of the deaths taken during his first event count toward his character. This policy is done as a service to new players so that they can get used to the game before being penalized for their deaths, not as a way to abuse the system and be immortal. This is out-of-game knowledge, so deaths taken by a new player should still be role-played appropriately. Any player that is deemed to be abusing this policy for intentional gain or detriment to the game or other players will be dealt with accordingly, at the discretion of the local chapter affected. This benefit is only given during a player’s first game, and experienced players that start a new character will not be allowed these unlimited deaths.
Character Advancement
Experience Points
Experience Points (XP) are used in NERO for the advancement of a player’s character. Whenever you attend a regular 2 day weekend event in NERO you receive a “blanket” of Experience Points equal to your current total Build Points.
Some events are shorter or longer and therefore worth different amounts of XP.
It is possible to, at maximum, double this experience through several means.
At the end of the event, you may pay to the game staff one silver per additional experience point you wish to gain . This is known as “Maxing Out.” You may also pay less than the maximum amount for correspondingly less gain.
Ex. Dave has 40 build points, he receives a Blanket of 40xp for attending a two day event and can pay 1-40 silver for an extra 1-40xp.
Some chapters will let you max out through helping NPC, or clean-up/setup duties and some will let you max out automatically. See your local chapter for their policies on max out.
Meditation
Any character may Meditate to regain use of “times per day” or “expendable” skills that were blocked by the Return <type> monster ability. To Meditate, the player must role-play deep concentration for 60 seconds, during which time they may perform no other actions including speaking, moving, or the use of any in-game skills, items or abilities. At the end of the meditation the character regains any skills or abilities lost to the effect “Return <type>.” Only character skills and abilities may be regained by Meditating. (not Magic Items, Scrolls, Alchemy, etc.)
A spell-casting character may also Meditate to regain spells that missed a legal target. At the end of the meditation, the character regains the use of any thrown spells that failed to hit a valid target, as well as all spells, skills and abilities lost to the Return <type> effect.
Spell casters should not use the Meditate ability to intentionally miss their targets in an attempt to cause confusion for the NPCs. “Decoy” spells that are intentionally thrown away from the target should not be regained by Meditate. In effect, you can only get your spells back from Meditate if you were actually attempting to hit your target and missed. Spells negated by defenses (ex. Dodge, Phase, and Resist) cannot be meditated back.
Build Points
Experience Points are automatically converted to Build Points (BP), which you then use to buy skills for your character. The amount of Experience Points needed to buy a Build Point is based on your level. Your level is determined by how many Build Points your character has. It takes 10 Build Points to gain a level. All characters start with 65 XP which equals 30 Build Points therefore all characters start at second level. These 30 Build Points are used to buy the character’s initial skills.
Levels
Your level determines how many Body Points you get and how many Experience Points you need to get a Build Point. Table 2-4 shows the character’s level based on the total Build Points. It also shows the number of XP needed for the next BP, and the Body Point value per class (fighter, rogue, scholar, and templar) for the level attained.
 
Chapter 3 The Skill System
NERO characters advance by purchasing skills.
Each skill you learn allows you to perform a particular task or group of tasks. Many can only be used a limited number of times per day. Some skills allow you to improve your abilities when the skill is bought multiple times. Be sure to carefully read the skill descriptions.
Standard Reset
In any case where a skill can be used only a certain number of times per day (such as Critical Slays or spells), the used skills will not return to you until the next day at 6 PM. This is known as a reset. On adventure days the reset happens before each module or adventure.
Limited Reset
Some chapters offer an additional reset of times-per-day skills at 6 AM. These are called “limited resets” and do not refresh craft/production skills, formal magic skills, Cantrips, or magic items. Information on whether or not your local NERO Chapter is using the Limited Reset rule will be available on their web site, at the event, and often announced at the Opening Ceremonies of the event.
The Skill System
NERO is a fantasy game. By that, we mean that it is a compilation of rules and customs by which we allow people to simulate doing things that they cannot really do. The most obvious of these things is magic.
You should not be fooled into thinking that your personal skill equates to the character skill it represents. For instance, we have weapon skills. You must have the
One Handed Edged weapon skill before you are allowed to use a long sword. Many people have asked if they can at least pick up a sword and block blows with it—after all, anyone could make the attempt, could they not? The answer is no, in our game they cannot.
The level of ability represented by the skill bought can be considerably different from that of your average player. It represents a skill that has required hours of practice a day for months to gain. When such an individual is faced with a person totally unskilled in weapon use, they would strike the person down with ease. The player’s skill may be somewhat less than that of the character, however, so the restrictions are used to simulate the skills.
Similarly, the proficiency system represents a level of skill that the player might never obtain. We use it as a way to artificially give a player’s character, no matter what his or her real world skill, an advantage over another whose character is not as skilled. It allows a player of indifferent skill to defeat or hold their own against a player of much greater skill. 
This is, after all, a fantasy. A person should be able to acquire skills that allow their character to do things that they themselves could not do in real life.
 