<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Root xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/"><body><p>Chapter 4 Magic</p>
<h1>Spell Aura</h1>
<p>There are two types of physical representations for spell aura; the manufactured spell orb and the traditional spell packets. Check with your local chapter so see which aura types you can use as some venues restrict one type or the other.</p>
<p>The spell orb is a manufactured product made of soft foam and can be no bigger than the size of a tennis ball. Soft foam balls can be purchased at most sporting good stores and toy stores. Foam balls are made by companies such as Wilson (called the Foam Flight Practice Ball) and Nerf makes a soft foam tennis ball.</p>
<p>Spell packets are constructed with bird seed and fabric. The bird seed should be the small variety, with no sunflower seeds or other heavy or sharp items that could hurt.</p>
<p>Do not use replacements! Rice can get wet and turn into a hardened ball. Rubber balls or tightly packed rubber bands will be too hard. If you are caught using something other than bird seed, you will have your packets and spell tags, if tags are used, confiscated and will lose your spells for the rest of the day.</p>
<p>To make a spell packet, the birdseed is placed in the center of the fabric, and the fabric is gathered around it and a small rubber band is used to bind the fabric or it can be sewn shut. Packets should be loosely packed, tight balls of birdseed can hurt!</p>
<p>The packet may be of any color except orange or yellow. Orange packets are used to represent alchemical gas globes, and yellow packets are used for arrows.</p>
<p>A good size for your fabric is 6" by 6", and a good amount of birdseed is 3/4 tbsps. You can use different amounts but, you should never use so much material that the resulting packet cannot fit into a 35mm film canister. Packets that are larger than that will be confiscated by a marshal. You may want to personalize your spell packets in some way by using a distinctive cloth or writing on the packets. This is a good way to make sure you can get your packets back after a battle without arguing with other spell casters about whose packets are whose.</p>
<p>Spell packets are visible as an opaque colored aura of energy only when held in the hand. In game they are visible but they do not produce any light. They are not in-game items and cannot be stolen, fumbled or removed.</p>
<p>You should not carry in your hand more spell packets than you can actually cast (although you can have plenty of extras in your pouches or pockets). If you only have 3 spells, you cannot have 42 spell packets between your fingers. You may also carry packets to represent scrolls or magic items that require a thrown packet to be thrown but those items must be readily available and not stashed away in a backpack.</p>
<h2>Casting Spells</h2>
<p>To cast a spell, the caster must have a spell packet in hand. The hand and arm with the spell packet in it must be "free" (Hands that are holding something else, or are tied or bound either physically or with a binding spell are not "free"). The caster must then correctly recite the verbal for the spell in a voice loud enough to be heard by a person standing next to you even if there is no one standing next to you. Within three seconds after finishing the verbal, the caster must then throw the packet at the target. The short phrase or "incantation" of the spell is spoken in plain English so the victim will know what spell has been cast. In game, these words are understood by anyone, but have a "magical effect" associated with them that makes them different from normal speech. Even though you can speak the language, you cannot "fake" a spell incantation or otherwise bluff the casting of a spell. You also cannot bluff the start of a spell incantation. If you start the incantation, the spell is used. Spellcasters expend the power to cast a spell as soon as the incantation has begun. You cannot start the incantation for a spell, change your mind, and then still have that spell. You must wait until the next reset to restudy and to cast the spell again.</p>
<h2>Touch-Casting</h2>
<p>Touch-casting is performed by holding a packet and placing it against the target you wish to affect. The obvious advantage to this is that there is no chance of missing and wasting the effect. In such a case, the effect recipient may choose to "accept" the effect, thus letting it past their Spell Defenses such as Shield Magic or Elemental Shield. The recipient must be conscious to "accept" an effect without triggering the Spell Defences. You may never "accept" a thrown effect. The decision to accept an effect through touch-casting is made immediately after the effect is cast. This is to prevent a caster from tricking an unsuspecting victim. </p>
<p>The recipient of a touch-cast effect can always refuse the effect by saying "refused." This will use up the effect, but have no effect whatsoever on the recipient. Whenever attempting to touch-cast, you must abide by all NERO safe conduct rules.</p>
<h2>Meditation</h2>
<p>Any character may Meditate to regain use of "times per day" or "expendable" skills that were blocked by the Return type monster ability. To Meditate, the player must role-play deep concentration for 60 seconds, during which time they may perform no other actions including speaking, moving, or the use of any in-game skills, items or abilities. At the end of the meditation the character regains any skills or abilities lost to the effect Return (type). Only character skills and abilities may be regained by Meditating. (not Magic Items, Scrolls, Alchemy, etc.) A spell-casting character may also Meditate to regain spells that missed a legal target. At the end of the meditation, the character regains the use of any thrown spells that failed to hit a valid target, as well as all spells, skills and abilities lost to the Return (type) effect. Spell casters should not use the Meditate ability to intentionally miss their targets in an attempt to cause confusion for the NPCs. "Decoy" spells that are intentionally thrown away from the target should not be regained by Meditate. In effect, you can only get your spells back from Meditate if you were actually attempting to hit your target and missed. Spells negated by defenses (ex. Dodge, Phase, and Resist) cannot be meditated back.</p>
<h2>Schools of Magic</h2>
<p>Whenever your character begins learning magic, either celestial or earth, you must select which of the two is your primary school of magic. The other will be the secondary, costing more build to buy. There is nothing preventing you from learning both earth and celestial magic but a separate spell pyramid must be built for each school.</p>
<h2>Stacked Effects</h2>
<p>Identical spells may not be stacked. No person may have a second copy of the same spell actively affecting him or her unless the spell description states otherwise. If</p>
<p>you are hit with a second effect that isn't stackable, the call is "got it". Calling "No effect" in this situation is incorrect. This definition is extended to include all identically named NERO game effects, not just spells. Identical effects are not stackable, unless noted in the effect's description.</p>
<p>The following spell types have special rules regarding spell stacking.</p>
<h2>Blade Effects</h2>
<p>These effects change the damage call of a weapon. You may have no more than three blade effects active on you at any time. The following spells are blade effects Endow, Delayed Endow, Elemental Blade, Enchanted Blade, and Silver Aura. While blade effects can affect the same target, they only work one at a time.</p>
<h2>Charm Effects</h2>
<p>You can only be affected by one charm effect at a time. If a creature is under a Charm effect and is hit with another, the most recent one will replace the previously administered effect as long as the new effect is of equal or higher value to the previous effect. See Table 5-6 on page 64.</p>
<p>Ex. Durk the adventurer is Charmed by a Siren his friend Sloan casts a charm spell at him, since Charm is of equal value to the Charm on Durk, the Siren's charm effect is negated and Durk is now only charmed to Sloan.</p>
<p>However, if the second effect is of lower value on the chart (1 being the lowest) the first charm effect remains.</p>
<p>Ex. Durk the Adventurer is Charmed by a Siren, the Siren's minion casts Shun on Durk. Since Shun is a lower value than Charm, Durk calls "Got it" and take no effect to the Shun. Durk would remain Charmed to the Siren.</p>
<h2>Target Specific</h2>
<p>Some effects like Wither Limb or Shatter have a sub-target as part of the call. This is required for spells and optional for other delivery methods such as carrier attacks or potions. If the sub-target is not specified then it is the target's choice as to which sub-target that is un-withered(Wither Limb ) or unrendered (Shatter, Destroy) will be affected. If no target matching the description exists, the call is "Got it". Calling "No effect" in this situation is incorrect.</p>
<h2>Spell defenses</h2>
<p>Spell defenses carry over from adventure to adventure. A fighter who still has a Shield spell on him at the end of a NERO adventure weekend will still have that spell at the beginning of the next weekend or module. This rule applies only to spells that are "indefinite" in duration. There can be no Wards when the game starts.</p>
<p>In-game, Spell Defenses are visible when they go off. It is obvious to anyone looking at you that you were protected from an attacking spell and what defense was used to negate it. You must state what the defense is at the time by saying "Reflect Magic" or "Shield Magic" for example, thus informing all observers that the spell was unsuccessful. Saying "flash" or "no effect" is not allowed. If you do not call a spell defense within three seconds of being hit, you take the effect and the defense is lost.</p>
<p>A spellcaster is not immune to his or her own spells, nor can they automatically dispel or deactivate their own spells, unless specifically noted in a spell's description. Spells such as Bless and Shield which merely add hit points do not have to be so announced.</p>
<h2>Visible Effects</h2>
<p>Berserk, Bind, Confine, Disease, Feeblemind, Hallucinoid, Imprison, Nausea, Paralyze, Pin, Silence, Sleep, Taint Blood, Vertigo, and Web, are all visible to any viewer while they are in effect, so long as they take the time to observe them (they must ask the affected player). The spells Ward and Circle of Power are also visible, provided that the physical representation (rope, building or otherwise) can be seen and the viewer takes the time to observe them. You cannot call a Hold to determine whether any visible effects are present. The amount of time it takes to ask if your character sees the effect is the amount of time it took your character to notice the effect, and you should only ask for visible effects from a short distance away at a conversational volume.</p>
<h2>Eldritch Power</h2>
<p>Many of the spells call upon an energy called eldritch power. This is a type of energy that only affects beings that are alive or animated. If you cast a Flame Bolt spell</p>
<p>at someone and miss and hit a tree, the tree will not catch on fire. Nor can you use an Ice Bolt spell to keep your ice cream cold. These spells can only affect creatures that are alive or animated.</p>
<h2>Reversible Spells</h2>
<p>Many earth magic spells are reversible (for example, Cure Disease and Cause Disease). These spells do not have to be learned or "memorized" separately. In fact, there is no way to separate the two spells. If you know the spell Cure Wounds, you automatically also know Cause Wounds. You cannot "forget" how to cast necromantic spells or otherwise claim to only know one side of a reversible spell. You can decide at the moment of casting which spell effect you will use (With proper incantation, of course). The reverse of many healing spells are necromantic, identifiable by the word "Chaos" in their incant. Beware however, that in- many in game places laws exist against necromantic spells such as Create Undead, so you'd better be ready to face the in-game consequences.</p>
<h2>Spell Disruption</h2>
<p>If a person takes body damage while casting a spell, the spell is disrupted. It does not work and is lost from memory. A spell can be disrupted by anything that deals body damage, including weapons, traps, or other spells. This is known as Disruption or Spell Disruption and is sometimes applicable to other types of attacks as noted in their descriptions.</p>
<h2>Necromancy</h2>
<p>Is necromancy evil? Not every person on Tyrra thinks so, in fact, it is accepted and even promoted by some races and cultures. However, necromancy is illegal in most parts of the world because many people believe it draws upon the decaying and dying aspects of the earth and thus prevents the earth from acting "naturally." The most accepted in-game explanation is this: Imagine the planet going through its seasons normally from year to year. Healing spells "go with the flow" of this cycle and do not disrupt the orderly process of living and dying that are part of this orderly system. Necromancy "goes against the flow" of this cycle by tapping into the chaotic forces that are not part of this system. Creating undead, for example, requires that a spirit behave in ways that are contrary to the orderly flow of the cycle. This in-game "theory" has been used in the past to explain large numbers of undead randomly appearing ("The chaos in this area is so strong that the cycle is being completely disrupted!") as well as aberrant weather ("This cold wave this time of year can only be explained by too much necromancy being cast in the area!"). Of course, there are many scholars who believe that this theory is a load of goblin dung and that bad weather and undead rising are all part of the normal cycle. It is up to you to decide as your character how you feel about the issue. Assume for game purposes that there are many learned treatises on both sides and that people have been arguing the point for many hundreds of years.</p>
<h2>Elemental Planes</h2>
<p>There are twelve main elemental planes which exist across powerful dimensional boundaries. The world of Tyrra is made up of the combination of these elements and their intersections. Please see the Tyrran Cosmology document at NeroLarp.com for more information, but it is important to note here that each of the twelve elemental planes has an associated damage type: a power it uses to harm opponents. These planes and their associated damage types are as follows:</p>
<p>Planes  Life, Death, Order, Chaos, Dream, Reason, Light, Darkness, Earth, Air, Fire, and Water. </p>
<p>Damage Types, in order  Essence, Destruction, Order, Chaos, Dream, Reason, Light, Darkness, Stone, Lightning, Fire, and Ice.</p>
<h2>Illegal Skills and Powers</h2>
<p>No character can ever use a plot given power to gain information about a PC's actions after the fact. This includes approved spells and skills such as Dreamvision as well as other abilities such as clairvoyance, clairaudience, tracking or scrying of any manner.</p>
<p>If a character wants to know what was said or done by a PC first hand, he must actually be present at the time of the action. Plot will never provide this information via one of the listed abilities, or through any similar means, and a PC can never claim to have known it due to ESP or other special abilities after the fact.</p>
</body></Root>