<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Root xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/"><body>
<p>NERO characters advance by purchasing skills.</p>
<p>Each skill you learn allows you to perform a particular task or group of tasks. Many can only be used a limited number of times per day. Some skills allow you to improve your abilities when the skill is bought multiple times. Be sure to carefully read the skill descriptions.</p>
<h3>Standard Reset</h3>
<p>In any case where a skill can be used only a certain number of times per day (such as Critical Slays or spells), the used skills will not return to you until the next day at 6 PM. This is known as a reset. On adventure days the reset happens before each module or adventure.</p>
<h3>Limited Reset</h3>
<p>Some chapters offer an additional reset of times-per-day skills at 6 AM. These are called limited resets and do not refresh craft and production skills, formal magic skills, Cantrips, or magic items. Information on whether or not your local NERO Chapter is using the Limited Reset rule will be available on their web site, at the event, and often announced at the Opening Ceremonies of the event.</p> 
<h2>The Skill System</h2>
<p>NERO is a fantasy game. By that, we mean that it is a compilation of rules and customs by which we allow people to simulate doing things that they cannot really do. The most obvious of these things is magic.</p>
<p>You should not be fooled into thinking that your personal skill equates to the character skill it represents. For instance, we have  Weapon skills. You must have the</p>
<p>One Handed Edged  Weapon skill before you are allowed to use a long sword. Many people have asked if they can at least pick up a sword and block blows with it, after all, anyone could make the attempt, could they not? The answer is no, in our game they cannot.</p>
<p>The level of ability represented by the skill bought can be considerably different from that of your average player. It represents a skill that has required hours of practice a day for months to gain. When such an individual is faced with a person totally unskilled in  Weapon use, they would strike the person down with ease. The player's skill may be somewhat less than that of the character, however, so the restrictions are used to simulate the skills.</p>
<p>Similarly, the proficiency system represents a level of skill that the player might never obtain. We use it as a way to artificially give a player's character, no matter what his or her real world skill, an advantage over another whose character is not as skilled. It allows a player of indifferent skill to defeat or hold their own against a player of much greater skill. </p>
<p>This is, after all, a fantasy. A person should be able to acquire skills that allow their character to do things that they themselves could not do in real life.</p>
<h2>Spell Slots</h2>
<p>There are special rules for spell acquisition that are unlike most other skills in the game. When you purchase a 1st level spell from the skill list, what you are actually buying is the ability to memorize and cast one 1st level spell. This is known as a Spell Slot. </p>
<p>You may memorize any 1st level spell and store it in this slot. Only one 1st level spell may be stored there at any time. Once that spell has been cast, the slot will become empty and will remain that way until the next limited, or standard reset, or until it is refilled by other means. If you have several spell slots of a given level, you can fill them with any combination of spells (of the appropriate level) that you know. </p>
<p>You must buy spell slots in a proportional pyramid fashion. If you wish to buy a spell slot of a particular level, then you must have two spell slots of the level below. </p>
<p>In other words, you must have a minimum of one spell slot difference between any adjoining levels and a maximum of two spell slots difference. If you wish to buy your first 2nd level spell slot, you must have at least two 1st level spell slots already, but you may not have three. Once you have purchased four spell slots of any particular level, then you need not buy any additional spell slots of that level to complete the pyramid. Imagine now the pyramid being an obelisk with a broad support and a pointed top (like the Washington Monument).</p>
<p>You may buy more than four spell slots per level but there must always be at least as many spell slots below that level in order to support the new amount. Further, the pyramid must be constantly building, which means that the level above must have only one less than the amount you are buying.</p>
<p>In other words, to buy a fifth 2nd level spell slot, you must have a fifth 1st level spell slot and a fourth 3rd level spell slot.</p>
<p>Example of Pyramid Rules: Enchanto the mage has a 3rd level spell slot, two 2nd level spell slots, and three 1st level spell slots. His pyramid is fine.</p>
<p>He wants to learn a 4th level slot eventually. He must build the foundation of the pyramid so it can support a 4th level spell. </p>
<p>First, he buys another 1st level slot and then another 2nd level slot. He must next purchase another 3rd level slot. </p>
<p>Now his pyramid is ready for the new spell level. Imagine the pyramid as needing the proper support for the 4th level spell has been made by making sure there are two 3rd level spell slots below. (The foundation for the two 3rd level slots was made when he had three 2nd level slots, and so on down the line.) He can buy his first 4th level spell slot If Enchanto wants to buy a 5th level slot, he can do so without having to buy any more 1st level slots because four is the maximum required. He must support the 5th level slot by buying a 2nd, 3rd, and a 4th in that order to make the pyramid.</p>
<p>Enchanto now has a perfect pyramid again. If he wants, he can stop buying 2nd level spells now, as four is the maximum required. His pyramid will then progress with the purchase of a 3rd level spell slot, and then a 4th, 5th, and then his first 6th level spell slot. </p>
<p>If Enchanto has all the slots listed in the pattern above (figure 3-4) and then decides that he wants a fifth 2nd level spell slot, he must first buy another 1st level slot and a fourth 3rd level spell slot to support the 2nd level spell slot. After he buys the 1st and 3rd level spell slots, he can get the 2nd level spell slot he wanted. </p>
<p>The pyramid must continue to be built and it must be built from the ground up! Note that the pattern is very set as to which spell slots have to be next purchased unless you wish to buy more than four spell slots of any one level. </p>
<p>There is potentially no limit to the number of spells per level as long as this progression is maintained. If Enchanto wanted to keep “bottoming out” his pyramid, he could end up with a pyramid that has nine 1st level spells, eight 2nd level spells, seven 3rd level spells, and so on up to one 9th level spell. Skill Costs O Below and on the following pages are the charts listing the Build Point costs of skills. Each skill has four cost columns associated with it: F (fighter), R (rogue), S (scholar) and T (templar). Note that all classes may buy any skill; they just might have to pay more Build Points. When buying skills, you should be aware of the prerequisites as well. For instance, to buy  Weapon proficiency,you must first have a  Weapon skill to be proficient in and four critical attack skills. To learn how to cast celestial spells, you must first know how to read and Write and read Magic. A good way to design your character is to imagine him or her at a higher level and work backwards. Figure out which skills you would like to have and how many Build Points you will have to spend for the skills. Try it with different classes to see which costs the least.</p>
<h2>Skill Costs</h2>
<p>Below and on the following pages are the charts listing the Build Point costs of skills. Each skill has four cost columns associated with it: F (fighter), R (rogue), S (scholar) and T (templar). Note that all classes may buy any skill; they just might have to pay more Build Points.</p>
<p>When buying skills, you should be aware of the prerequisites as well. For instance, to buy  Weapon proficiency,you must first have a  Weapon skill to be proficient in and four critical attack skills. To learn how to cast celestial spells, you must first know how to read and Write and read Magic.</p>
<p>A good way to design your character is to imagine him or her at a higher level and work backwards. Figure out which skills you would like to have and how many Build Points you will have to spend for the skills. Try it with different classes to see which costs the least. </p>
<h2>Production Skills</h2>
<p>To create game items such  as Weapons, Armor, Potions, Scrolls, Traps, Alchemical Elixirs, ContactPoisons, and Gas Globes, you must first buy the appropriate skill with  your Build Points.</p>
<p>The charts in Adventuring Gear on page 105 show what can be made with specific skills. To actually make an item on these lists, you will have to determine the item you wish to make and then make sure that you have the Production Levels.</p>
<p>Every item or special item property has an associated Production Level that is required to create it. Each Game Day, a character has one Production Level for each purchase of the associated Production Skill. This is referred to as the character’s Base Production Level. There are three ways to augment your production output; Trade Mastery, Materials, and Workshops, they do not change the Base Production Level.</p>
<h2>Trade Mastery</h2>
<p>A character with ten or more levels of a single Production Skill is considered a Master of her trade, and generates one “Master” Production Level per level of overall skill.</p>
<h3>Workshops</h3>
<p>A workshop generates one ”Workshop” Production Level per level of overall skill.</p>
<h3>Materials</h3>
<p>A character may also buy more refined materials at Logistics in order to increase their output at the rate of one silver per Production Level, to a maximum of their Base Production Level. Local chapters may issue Production Components to represent these refined materials as in-game treasure or for sale by merchants in addition to or instead of using silver. One Production Component is equal to one silver for the purposes of increasing production output,but the combined increased output of silver and Production Components cannot exceed the Base Production Level. Example: “Talon has 20 levels of create scroll so his base production level for one day is 20. Since Talon has over 10 levels of create scroll he is a mastercraftsman and gets 1 for 20 bonus production levels. Talon spends 10 silver and turns in 10 production components at check-in for another 20 bonus production levels. Finally Talon uses a scroll workshop which allows him to create 20 bonus production levels of scrolls. Talon then uses his 80 production levels to create scrolls, this is the maximum amount of production output Talon can get with his base production level. All production items have an expiration date. These items last 24 months after being created. The expiration date of a particular production item is known by anyone who looks at the item reads the associated item tag that goes with it. When an item expires, it is said to have broken, rusted, or otherwise lost potency. This damage can be repaired by using production skills to issue a new tag for the item. This explains how you can still own your father’s sword even though it rusts and expires every two years. </p>
<h3>Special Abilities</h3>
<p>If a production skill has Special Abilities, only Base Production Levels can be used for them. If a Base Production Level is used for a Special Ability then it cannot be used to make a game item, but the use of workshops, silver, production components, or Master Levels is undiminished.</p>
<p>It is possible to become more productive in making Production items if you have access to a workshop that specializes in making them. A character with a workshop can make additional Levels of items to a maximum of their Base Production Level.</p>
<p>There are specialized workshops for making </p>
<p>(a) alchemical elixirs, gases, and contact poisons,</p>
<p>(b) making weapons and armor,</p>
<p>(c) creating potions, </p>
<p>(d) creating scrolls, and </p>
<p>(e) making and arming traps.</p>
<p>Access to these workshops is found through in game means, often by way of a local guild or noble connection. Workshops are chapter specific.</p>
<h2>Goblin Production</h2>
<p>Goblin stamps can be used to purchase production items. They can not be used to add special abilities to items. The scale and rules governing their use are available on the NERO National Website. These rules have been known to change, so make sure you check the NERO National Website periodically</p>
</body></Root> 