<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Root xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/">
<p>The NERO Rule Book 9th Edition is dedicated to Fran Moore and Joe Cali,</p>
<p>Fran Moore passed away in October of 2010. Fran was one of the most prominent writers of the Tyrran Campaign she and several others shaping the Tyran World as we know it today. Fran was and continues to be, an inspiration to us all.</p>
<p>~ Joseph Valenti</p>
<p>Joe Cali, a veteran player and long time supporter of NERO, passed away on June 18th, 2011 Joe was a man with a warm heart who always had a smile on his face. His home, hearth, and kitchen were always open to anyone in need. His presence in our world will be sourly missed</p>
<p>~ Matthew Taylor</p>
<p></p>
<p>The NERO Rule Book is Copyright 1990, 1991, 1992, 1993, 1994, 1997, 1999, 2011 by NERO Live Adventure Games LLC.</p>
<p>The NERO name and logo is a registered trademark of NERO Live Adventure Games LLC.</p>
<p>This book is for use in official NERO games only.</p>
<p>Use of these rules by purchaser in any unsanctioned game where admission is charged is prohibited.</p>
<p>No part of this book may be reproduced, stored in or introduced into a retrieval system or transmitted in whole or in part, by any means (electronic, mechanical, photocopying, recording, or otherwise) without expressed written permission of NERO.</p>
<p>Purchase of this book implies acceptance of the above terms.</p>
<p></p>
<p>Joseph Valenti DBA NERO </p>
<p>653 country Kitchen Rd.</p>
<p>Banesville GA 30204</p>
<p>(914) 309-7718</p>
<p>jvalenti@nerolarp.com</p>
<p>www.nerolarp.com</p>
<h1>Edited and Compiled by</h1>
<p>Melissa Brannon, Dan Comstock, Tim Delong, Nicholas Denny, Mike Ennis, David Epstein, Michael Golosvker, Tiny Hughes, Rebecca King, Noah Mason, Ryan Massey Mitchell Meconi, Robert Poulin, Matthew Sims, Charles Smith, Kevin Sterbakow, Joseph Valenti, Fred Watson, John Zeigler, Sarah Clark, and many many others</p>
<h1>Designers</h1>
<p>Adam Taylor, Heidi Morris-Taylor</p>
<h1>Lead Photographer</h1>
<p>Joanna Becker</p>
<h1>Contributing Photographers</h1>
<p>Scott Erb Photography, George Short, Damien Turi, Erin Nicholson, Sarah Clark, Ivey Hardy, Brian Wamsher, Denise Beculer, Rebecca Kindergan, Angel Williamson, Tony Lopes, NorthCoastNero, Sheena Osborne, David Acosta</p>
<p></p>
<p>Special Thanks to Sonya Maizell for writing the introductory story</p>
<p></p>
<p>The NERO Game System is intended to allow players and staff hours of live-action fun without any amount of play stoppage. It is the responsibility of the players and staff to remember this when reading and interpreting the rules. We have done our best to clear up vagaries and make there rules sound, and we will continue to do so in the future. still, players and staff should avoid constantly trying to find loopholes or language that allows them to do things that are against the spirit of the rules. the NERO international office will determine the spirit of the rules in all cases where interpenetration is disputed.</p>
</Root>