Chapter 4 Magic</p>
<p>Spell Aura</p>
<p>There are two types of physical representations for spell aura; the manufactured spell orb and the traditional spell packets. Check with your local chapter so see which aura types you can use as some venues restrict one type or the other.</p>
<p>The spell orb is a manufactured product made of soft foam and can be no bigger than the size of a tennis ball. Soft foam balls can be purchased at most sporting good stores and toy stores. Foam balls are made by companies such as Wilson (called the Foam Flight Practice Ball) and Nerf makes a soft foam tennis ball.</p>
<p>Spell packets are constructed with bird seed and fabric. The bird seed should be the small variety, with no sunflower seeds or other heavy or sharp items that could hurt.</p>
<p>Do not use replacements! Rice can get wet and turn into a hardened ball. Rubber balls or tightly packed rubber bands will be too hard. If you are caught using something other than bird seed, you will have your packets and spell tags, if tags are used, confiscated and will lose your spells for the rest of the day.</p>
<p>To make a spell packet, the birdseed is placed in the center of the fabric, and the fabric is gathered around it and a small rubber band is used to bind the fabric or it can be sewn shut. Packets should be loosely packed—tight balls of birdseed can hurt!</p>
<p>The packet may be of any color except orange or yellow. Orange packets are used to represent alchemical gas globes, and yellow packets are used for arrows.</p>
<p>A good size for your fabric is 6”x 6”, and a good amount of birdseed is 3/4 tbsps. You can use different amounts but, you should never use so much material that the resulting packet cannot fit into a 35mm film canister. Packets that are larger than that will be confiscated by a marshal. You may want to personalize your spell packets in some way by using a distinctive cloth or writing on the packets. This is a good way to make sure you can get your packets back after a battle without arguing with other spell casters about whose packets are whose.</p>
<p>Spell packets are visible as an opaque colored aura of energy only when held in the hand. In game they are visible but they do not produce any light. They are not in-game items and cannot be stolen, fumbled or removed.</p>
<p>You should not carry in your hand more spell packets than you can actually cast (although you can have plenty of extras in your pouches or pockets). If you only have 3 spells, you cannot have 42 spell packets between your fingers. You may also carry packets to represent scrolls or magic items that require a thrown packet to be thrown but those items must be readily available and not stashed away in a backpack.</p>
<p>Casting Spells</p>
<p>To cast a spell, the caster must have a spell packet in hand. The hand and arm with the spell packet in it must be “free” (Hands that are holding something else, or are tied or bound either physically or with a binding spell are not “free”). The caster must then correctly recite the verbal for the spell in a voice loud enough to be heard by a person standing next to you even if there is no one standing next to you. Within three seconds after finishing the verbal, the caster must then throw the packet at the target. The short phrase or “incantation” of the spell is spoken in plain English so the victim will know what spell has been cast. In game, these words are understood by anyone, but have a “magical effect” associated with them that makes them different from normal speech. Even though you can speak the language, you cannot “fake” a spell incantation or otherwise bluff the casting of a spell. You also cannot bluff the start of a spell incantation. If you start the incantation, the spell is used. Spellcasters expend the power to cast a spell as soon as the incantation has begun. You cannot start the incantation for a spell, change your mind, and then still have that spell. You must wait until the next reset to restudy and to cast the spell again.</p>
<p>Touch-Casting</p>
<p>Touch-casting is performed by holding a packet and placing it against the target you wish to affect. The obvious advantage to this is that there is no chance of missing and wasting the effect. In such a case, the effect recipient may choose to “accept” the effect, thus letting it past their Spell Defenses such as Shield Magic or Elemental Shield. The recipient must be conscious to “accept” an effect without triggering the Spell Defences. You may never “accept” a thrown effect. The decision to accept an effect through touch-casting is made immediately after the effect is cast. This is to prevent a caster from tricking an unsuspecting victim. </p>
<p>The recipient of a touch-cast effect can always refuse the effect by saying “refused.” This will use up the effect, but have no effect whatsoever on the recipient. Whenever attempting to touch-cast, you must abide by all NERO safe conduct rules.</p>
<p>Meditation</p>
<p>Any character may Meditate to regain use of “times per day” or “expendable” skills that were blocked by the Return <type> monster ability. To Meditate, the player must role-play deep concentration for 60 seconds, during which time they may perform no other actions including speaking, moving, or the use of any in-game skills, items or abilities. At the end of the meditation the character regains any skills or abilities lost to the effect “Return <type>.” Only character skills and abilities may be regained by Meditating. (not Magic Items, Scrolls, Alchemy, etc.) A spell-casting character may also Meditate to regain spells that missed a legal target. At the end of the meditation, the character regains the use of any thrown spells that failed to hit a valid target, as well as all spells, skills and abilities lost to the Return <type> effect. Spell casters should not use the Meditate ability to intentionally miss their targets in an attempt to cause confusion for the NPCs. “Decoy” spells that are intentionally thrown away from the target should not be regained by Meditate. In effect, you can only get your spells back from Meditate if you were actually attempting to hit your target and missed. Spells negated by defenses (ex. Dodge, Phase, and Resist) cannot be meditated back.</p>
<p>Schools of Magic</p>
<p>Whenever your character begins learning magic, either celestial or earth, you must select which of the two is your primary school of magic. The other will be the secondary, costing more build to buy. There is nothing preventing you from learning both earth and celestial magic but a separate spell pyramid must be built for each school.</p>
<p>Stacked Effects</p>
<p>Identical spells may not be stacked. No person may have a second copy of the same spell actively affecting him or her unless the spell description states otherwise. If</p>
<p>you are hit with a second effect that isn’t stackable, the call is “got it”. Calling “No effect” in this situation is incorrect. This definition is extended to include all identically named NERO game effects, not just spells. Identical effects are not stackable, unless noted in the effect’s description.</p>
<p>The following spell types have special rules regarding spell stacking.</p>
<p>Blade Effects</p>
<p>These effects change the damage call of a weapon. You may have no more than three blade effects active on you at any time. The following spells are blade effects Endow, Delayed Endow, Elemental Blade, Enchanted Blade, and Silver Aura. While blade effects can affect the same target, they only work one at a time.</p>
<p>Charm Effects</p>
<p>You can only be affected by one charm effect at a time. If a creature is under a Charm effect and is hit with another, the most recent one will replace the previously administered effect as long as the new effect is of equal or higher value to the previous effect. See Table 5-6 on page 64.</p>
<p>Ex. Durk the adventurer is Charmed by a Siren his friend Sloan casts a charm spell at him, since Charm is of equal value to the Charm on Durk, the Siren’s charm effect is negated and Durk is now only charmed to Sloan.</p>
<p>However, if the second effect is of lower value on the chart (1 being the lowest) the first charm effect remains.</p>
<p>Ex. Durk the Adventurer is Charmed by a Siren, the Siren’s minion casts Shun on Durk. Since Shun is a lower value than Charm, Durk calls “Got it” and take no effect to the Shun. Durk would remain Charmed to the Siren.</p>
<p>Target Specific</p>
<p>Some effects like Wither Limb or Shatter have a sub-target as part of the call. This is required for spells and optional for other delivery methods such as carrier attacks or potions. If the sub-target is not specified then it is the target’s choice as to which sub-target that is un-withered(Wither Limb ) or unrendered (Shatter, Destroy) will be affected. If no target matching the description exists, the call is “Got it”. Calling “No effect” in this situation is incorrect.</p>
<p>Spell defenses</p>
<p>Spell defenses carry over from adventure to adventure. A fighter who still has a Shield spell on him at the end of a NERO adventure weekend will still have that spell at the beginning of the next weekend or module. This rule applies only to spells that are “indefinite” in duration. There can be no Wards when the game starts.</p>
<p>In-game, Spell Defenses are visible when they go off. It is obvious to anyone looking at you that you were protected from an attacking spell and what defense was used to negate it. You must state what the defense is at the time by saying “Reflect Magic” or “Shield Magic” for example, thus informing all observers that the spell was unsuccessful. Saying “flash” or “no effect” is not allowed. If you do not call a spell defense within three seconds of being hit, you take the effect and the defense is lost.</p>
<p>A spellcaster is not immune to his or her own spells, nor can they automatically dispel or deactivate their own spells, unless specifically noted in a spell’s description. Spells such as Bless and Shield which merely add hit points do not have to be so announced.</p>
<p>Visible Effects</p>
<p>Berserk, Bind, Confine, Disease, Feeblemind, Hallucinoid, Imprison, Nausea, Paralyze, Pin, Silence, Sleep, Taint Blood, Vertigo, and Web, are all visible to any viewer while they are in effect, so long as they take the time to observe them (they must ask the affected player). The spells Ward and Circle of Power are also visible, provided that the physical representation (rope, building or otherwise) can be seen and the viewer takes the time to observe them. You cannot call a Hold to determine whether any visible effects are present. The amount of time it takes to ask if your character sees the effect is the amount of time it took your character to notice the effect, and you should only ask for visible effects from a short distance away at a conversational volume.</p>
<p>Eldritch Power</p>
<p>Many of the spells call upon an energy called eldritch power. This is a type of energy that only affects beings that are alive or animated. If you cast a Flame Bolt spell</p>
<p>at someone and miss and hit a tree, the tree will not catch on fire. Nor can you use an Ice Bolt spell to keep your ice cream cold. These spells can only affect creatures that are alive or animated.</p>
<p>Reversible Spells</p>
<p>Many earth magic spells are reversible (for example, Cure Disease and Cause Disease). These spells do not have to be learned or “memorized” separately. In fact, there is no way to separate the two spells. If you know the spell Cure Wounds, you automatically also know Cause Wounds. You cannot “forget” how to cast necromantic spells or otherwise claim to only know one side of a reversible spell. You can decide at the moment of casting which spell effect you will use (With proper incantation, of course). The reverse of many healing spells are necromantic, identifiable by the word “Chaos” in their incant. Beware however, that in- many in game places laws exist against necromantic spells such as Create Undead, so you’d better be ready to face the in-game consequences.</p>
<p>Spell Disruption</p>
<p>If a person takes body damage while casting a spell, the spell is disrupted. It does not work and is lost from memory. A spell can be disrupted by anything that deals body damage, including weapons, traps, or other spells. This is known as Disruption or Spell Disruption and is sometimes applicable to other types of attacks as noted in their descriptions.</p>
<p>Necromancy</p>
<p>Is necromancy evil? Not every person on Tyrra thinks so—in fact, it is accepted and even promoted by some races and cultures. However, necromancy is illegal in most parts of the world because many people believe it draws upon the decaying and dying aspects of the earth and thus prevents the earth from acting “naturally.” The most accepted in-game explanation is this: Imagine the planet going through its seasons normally from year to year. Healing spells “go with the flow” of this cycle and do not disrupt the orderly process of living and dying that are part of this orderly system. Necromancy “goes against the flow” of this cycle by tapping into the chaotic forces that are not part of this system. Creating undead, for example, requires that a spirit behave in ways that are contrary to the orderly flow of the cycle. This in-game “theory” has been used in the past to explain large numbers of undead randomly appearing (“The chaos in this area is so strong that the cycle is being completely disrupted!”) as well as aberrant weather (“This cold wave this time of year can only be explained by too much necromancy being cast in the area!”). Of course, there are many scholars who believe that this theory is a load of goblin dung and that bad weather and undead rising are all part of the normal cycle. It is up to you to decide as your character how you feel about the issue. Assume for game purposes that there are many learned treatises on both sides and that people have been arguing the point for many hundreds of years.</p>
<p>Elemental Planes</p>
<p>There are twelve main elemental planes which exist across powerful dimensional boundaries. The world of Tyrra is made up of the combination of these elements and their intersections. Please see the Tyrran Cosmology document at NeroLarp.com for more information, but it is important to note here that each of the twelve elemental planes has an associated damage type: a power it uses to harm opponents. These planes and their associated damage types are as follows:</p>
<p>Planes – Life, Death, Order, Chaos, Dream, Reason, Light, Darkness, Earth, Air, Fire, and Water. </p>
<p>Damage Types, in order – Essence, Destruction, Order, Chaos, Dream, Reason, Light, Darkness, Stone, Lightning, Fire, and Ice.</p>
<p>Illegal Skills and Powers</p>
<p>No character can ever use a plot given power to gain information about a PC’s actions after the fact. This includes approved spells and skills such as Dreamvision as well as other abilities such as clairvoyance, clairaudience, tracking or scrying of any manner.</p>
<p>If a character wants to know what was said or done by a PC first hand, he must actually be present at the time of the action. Plot will never provide this information via one of the listed abilities, or through any similar means, and a PC can never claim to have known it due to ESP or other special abilities after the fact.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Chapter 5 : Spells</p>
<p>Every Spell listed here is available at every NERO Chapter.</p>
<p>The information after the spell’s in game name includes the spell’s level, whether it is Celestial or Earth, whether it can be made into a Potion or Scroll, whether it can be Manifolded, and its duration.</p>
<p>Spell Defenses</p>
<p>There are a few spells and effects that will defend the recipient from incoming spells or attacks. Each can protect against one spell or effect only. They are cast upon the recipient in advance and stay with the recipient until “activated” by the effect they are meant to prevent. The Spell Defenses are Displacement, Elemental Shield, Guardian of the Four, Magic Armor, Poison Shield, Reflect Magic, and Shield Magic.</p>
<p>In-game, you are always aware of what Spell Defenses are active on you. Once a Spell Defense is active, then it will affect the next applicable incoming effect, regardless of whether or not you would have been affected. It will then be used up.</p>
<p>All Spell Defenses must be called correctly, for example “Reflect Magic” or “Phase,” to be effective and must be called within three seconds or are lost or not used respectively.</p>
<p>Spell Durations</p>
<p>Concentration</p>
<p>This spell lasts as long as the caster maintains concentration. While concentrating, the caster cannot run or use any game skills.</p>
<p>Continuous</p>
<p>Continuous is a specific form of concentration which requires the caster to continually chant a litany, recite a verse, or sing a song with the limits listed under manifold page 39 except you do not need the Manifold skill or a Hearth. At the end of each repetition the caster may state the incant for the spell and deliver the effect as specified in the description of the spell. As long as the caster continues to repeat the verse they may continue to recast the spell using only one spell slot. Each spell with this duration may impose other limits upon the caster to continue the spell. The caster may not speak outside the words of the verse or incant and may not use other skills while continuing a spell and may not pause longer than 5 seconds. The limitations of Concentration also apply. If a continuous spell is used once the caster may simply state the incant.</p>
<p>Timed</p>
<p>Some spells last for a specific amount of time, either 5 seconds, 1, 5, or 10 minutes, 1 hour, or 5 days.</p>
<p>Instant</p>
<p>The duration of this spell is instantaneous, but its effects may be permanent. (Thus, any damage taken from these spells is permanent until cured.)</p>
<p>Indefinite</p>
<p>The effects of this spell are permanent unless the victim receives the proper counter spell or the spell’s effect is used up (or the victim dies). The counter spell will be listed in the spell description.</p>
<p>Line of Sight</p>
<p>This spell lasts as long as the caster could see the victim from wherever the caster is located. It also lasts if the victim could see the caster.</p>
<p>Basically, if you can draw a straight line between the caster and the victim without the line being obscured by any large, immovable obstacles, then the Line of Sight is still in effect. The caster closing their eyes or hiding behind someone else does not break Line of Sight.</p>
<p>If the caster breaks Line of Sight by imposing a very large object such as a building or large tree between the caster and the victim for longer than 10 seconds, the spell is broken. If view of the character is resumed before the 10 seconds is up, then the spell continues. These spells will cease immediately if the caster falls unconscious line of sight lasts for a maximum of 5 days.</p>
<p>Awaken</p>
<p>I command you to awaken.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:YesPotion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell awakens the recipient from a Waylay, any sleep effect, and the charm effects Calm, Calm animal, Calm, Calm Animal, Shun, shun Animal, Silence, Fear, and Vampire Charm. It does not in any way affect Enslavement.</p>
<p>Banish</p>
<p>With eldrich force I banish you.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:YesPotion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell sends any extraplanar creature from Tyrra to its plane of origin and will keep the creature on its own home plane for 24 Tyrran hours. All items carried by the creature will be left behind unless Spirit Linked. This spell cannot be used to return to Tyrra from another plane.</p>
<p>Bind</p>
<p>With mystic force I bind you.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: line of sight</p>
<p>This spell snares the victim’s arms, binding them straight to its sides. The victim may talk freely, but may not use any game skills requiring use of the arms, including using a weapon or shield, casting a spell, or activating a gas globe. The victim may walk, run, or leave the combat area as desired. This spell does not prevent the victim from being searched or being given a Killing Blow, although a moving victim is unlikely to allow either action.</p>
<p>Bless</p>
<p>I grant you the power of a bless.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell gives the recipient five extra Body Points. These points are the first Body Points lost to damage. This spell cannot be used to revive an unconscious person or harm an undead.</p>
<p>Calm</p>
<p>I command you to be calm.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>By means of this spell the caster can calm one target. This makes the target docile and non-aggressive for the duration of five minutes. The target might wander off, head for the tavern for a drink, or simply sit down and rest for a while. They cannot take any aggressive actions while under the effect of this spell, they will not participate in combat nor will they attempt to remove the spell. This is a form of charm and will over-ride any normal behavior so long as it is effective it can be stopped by the ability Resist Charm. If anyone attacks the target in any way this effect will immediately be dispelled. An Awaken or Dispel Magic will also work to remove this effect.</p>
<p>Calm Animal</p>
<p>I command this animal to be calm.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>By means of this spell the caster can calm one creature that is designated as an animal. This calm makes the creature docile and non-aggressive for the duration of five minutes. They cannot take any aggressive actions such as participating in combat nor will they attempt to remove the spell. The animal might wander off or simply sit down and rest for a while. This is a form of charm and will over-ride any normal behavior so long as it is effective it can be stopped by the ability Resist Charm. If anyone attacks the creature in any way this effect will  mmediately be dispelled. An Aw aken or Dispel Magic will also work to remove this effect. This will not affect magical animals, hybrid animals, animal men, only ordinary animals, fish, and birds. For example an eagle would be affected but it would not affect a gryphon, a phoenix, or a biata. A bull would be affected but it would not affect a minotaur or a bull scavenger. A horse would be affected but a unicorn would not. This spell has no effect on any being which is not designated as an ordinary animal though it will still trigger a Shield Magic or similar protective.</p>
<p>Cause Critical Wounds</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to cause critical wounds 30.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will deal 30 points of body damage to the target. It does not affect armor. It will cure 30 Body Points to an undead creature.</p>
<p>Cause Disease</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to cause disease.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell will infect the recipient with a debilitating disease. The infection is not contagious, but makes the target unable to run. The spell Purify Blood will not cure someone under the effects of this spell. This spell might not be effective against creatures with no metabolism.</p>
<p>Cause Light Wounds</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to cause light wounds 5.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will deal 5 points of body damage to the target. It does not affect armor. It will cure 5 Body Points of damage on an undead creature.</p>
<p>Cause Mortal Wounds</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to cause mortal wounds 40.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will deal 40 points of body damage to the target. It does not affect armor. It will cure 40 Body Points to an undead creature.</p>
<p>Cause Serious Wounds</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to cause serious wounds 20.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will deal 20 points of body damage to the target. It does not affect armor. It will cure 20 Body Points to an undead creature.</p>
<p>Cause Wounds</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to cause wounds 10</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will deal 10 points of body damage to the target. It does not affect armor. It will cure 10 Body Points to an undead creature.</p>
<p>Charm</p>
<p>I command you to be charmed.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>This spell makes the victim view the caster as his or her best friend in the whole world. While this spell is in effect, no amount of logic or role-playing will convince the victim that he or she has been Charmed, and the victim will not remember the casting of the spell until after it has worn off or been cured. An attack on the victim by the caster’s party will not immediately break the spell, but if the caster cannot come up with a good reason why he or she is not helping to defend the victim, then that will. If the caster attacks the victim, then the spell is broken immediately. A victim of this spell will not do anything completely against his or her own nature (such as attack his or her own party) unless a very good reason can be given by the caster. The spell does not turn the victim into a mindless robot blindly following orders, but it does require the victim to stay by the side of the new “friend” and listen to his or her suggestions.” (Note that this assumes that they both speak the same language. You cannot obey a “suggestion” that you don’t understand.) This spell only works on creatures that have a mind as defined by the game. Several creatures (such as lesser undead, golems, or some giant insects) do not have a mind that can be affected by this spell. After the spell’s duration expires, the victim remembers everything that happened except the actual casting of the Charm spell. Depending upon the circumstances,the victim might sometimes realize that he or she had been charmed. Note that this spell is not strong enough to override Control Undead, Fear, Enslavement or Vampire Charm Table 5-6 on page 64.</p>
<p>Circle of Harmony</p>
<p>With eldrich force I build a circle of harmony</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 1 Hour</p>
<p>This spell allows the caster to charm a single creature which must be an animal. This spell duplicates the Charm spell, except that it may only be cast on ordinary animals. Since the Animal will not understand the common tongue this in general only keeps the caster safe from the animal attacking him. If the caster is attacked the animal will generally attempt to defend him and if the caster interposes himself between the animal and another target the animal will understand that it shouldn’t attack the target. If the animal has been trained to follow commands it will listen to the caster as if he were the one who normally gives the commands and will perform any commands he is trained to at the request of the caster, this does not mean the animal will do anything they are not specifically trained to do. This spell is a type of charm and can be resisted with the ability Resist Charm, and it can be cured with an Aw aken spell or Dispel Magic spell. Stronger charms such as Vampire Charm or Enslavement will override its effects Table 5-6 on page 64. This will not affect magical animals, hybrid animals, nimal men, only ordinary animals, fish, and birds. For example an eagle would be affected but it would not affect a gryphon, a phoenix, or a biata. A bull would be affected but it would not affect a minotaur or a bull scavenger. A horse would be affected but a unicorn would not. This spell has no effect on any being which is not designated as an ordinary animal though it will still trigger a shield magic or similar protective.</p>
<p>Circle of Power</p>
<p>With eldrich force I build a circle of power.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 10 Minutes</p>
<p>The caster may draw out or construct an intricate circle which acts as a prepared hearth, for the school of magic from which this spell was cast, without the need to be indoors. The circle  ust consist of a circle within a circle to form a circular  band. Between the two circles their must be no less than eight symbols or glyphs. The circle must be fully prepared before the spell  s cast. The maximum radius of the outer circle is six feet, and the inner circle must be at least six inches smaller in radius. The area within the outer circle represents the area of effect. The  spell lasts for one hour or until the circle is in part or whole erased, pulled apart, destroyed, or a dispel magic is cast upon the phys-rep. The caster must place an individually recognizable  styled “H” in the center of the circle as if it were a hearth indicating it is active, the “H” is OOG the way a “W” is for a ward. The circle remains active even if the caster leaves it but if dispelled or otherwise disrupted the “H” must be removed. A player must confirm their “H” is still present before using a Circle of Harmony. A player may cast this spell from both schools of magic in order to have the effect of the hearth for both schools. If they do this the “H” must reflect this to them. Multiple characters can have this effect active on the same area, but each Circle of Harmony must have its own “H” which must be recognizable by the player who cast it and distinct  rom any others.</p>
<p>Confine</p>
<p>With mystic force I confine you.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Line of Sight</p>
<p>This spell snares the arms of its victim, binding them straight to its sides, and immobilizes the victim completely from the neck down making them helpless. The victim may talk freely, but  may not use any game skills requiring use of the arms, including using a weapon or shield, casting a spell, or activating a gas globe. The victim may not walk, run, or be moved in any way  Any item the victim is holding cannot be dropped. However, since the effect allows the victim to be searched, anyone else can choose to physically remove a hand-held item from the  victim by simply “searching” them. Even a victim with Superhuman Strength cannot prevent himself from being “searched” in this manner. This spell does not prevent the victim from being given a Killing Blow.</p>
<p>Control Undead</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to control undead.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>This spell allows the caster to control one lesser undead for 5 minutes. Tasks may not involve any sentient thought higher than an animal: “Guard this” is fine, but “Count all the leaves on that tree” requires sentience and will not work. The most recent Control Undead effect takes precedent, if there is a conflict. This spell will not affect a living target, although it will remove a living person’s Shield Magic or Reflect Magic. This effect is stronger than calm, Calm animal, Charm, Charm Animal, Shun, Shun Animal or Fear. The most recent Control Undead, Vampire Charm or Enslavement effect will take precedent if there is a conflict Table 5-6 on page 64.</p>
<p>Corruption</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to corrupt you.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 1 Minute</p>
<p>This spell restores an undead target or other target healed by necromancy or chaos to his or her full body points. Once the spell is successfully cast, the target will begin to regenerate as per the rules of the special ability Regeneration. Corruption requires that the character stand or sit in one place for one minute and concentrate. If this process is interrupted before its  completion, the spell is lost for no effect. The target may not be restored to a total of body higher than is appropriate for his race and level via this spell. This spell may not be used to aid a living character in any way. This spell only affects targets which are healed by necromancy or chaos. This spell does not remove any other negative effects. This spell is the reverse of Regeneration.</p>
<p>Create Undead</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to create undead.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>This spell only works on a corpse that has not previously been animated  and will pull the character’s spirit back to reanimate its former body.  The resulting zombie will then follow the caster’s commands as if a control undead spell had been cast upon it.  Note that this spell must be cast within the fie minute period between a character’s death and the point where the spirit heads to the Earth Circle for resurrection. This spell transforms the individual into a mindless berserker who will fight at their normal speed until reduced to no hit points or until ordered to stop by the caster.  The creature’s visual appearance does not change.  While Created as an undead the fie minute count until resurrection is suspended. If the zombie is reduced to zero Body Points or takes effect from a Dispel Magic  then the spell ends and the resurrection count resumes where it left off.  The spirit will remember nothing of the time spent as a zombie. The zombie created will have the maximum body points the victim had in life.</p>
<p>Cure Critical Wounds</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to cure crtical wounds 30.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will restore up to 30 points of body damage but never more than a character’s maximum.  It will restore an unconscious or dying character but will not resurrect a dead one.  Against undead  this spell will deal 30 points of body damage.</p>
<p>Cure Disease</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to cure diease.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will cure a character infected with a disease.</p>
<p>Cure Light Wounds</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to cure light wounds 5.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will restore up to 5 points of body damage but never more than a character’s maximum. It will restore an unconscious character but will not resurrect a dead one. Against undead, this spell will do 5 points of body damage.</p>
<p>Cure Mortal Wounds</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to cure mortal wounds 40.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will restore up to 40 points of body damage but never more than a character’s maximum. It will restore an unconscious character but will not resurrect a dead one. Against undead, this spell will do 40 points of body damage.</p>
<p>Cure Serious Wounds</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to cure serious wounds 20</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will restore up to 20 points of body damage but never more than a character’s maximum. It will restore an unconscious character but will not resurrect a dead one. Against undead, this spell will do 20 points of body damage.</p>
<p>Cure Wounds</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to cure wounds 10.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will restore up to 10 points of body damage but never more than a character’s maximum. It will restore an unconscious character but will not resurrect a dead one. Against  undead, this spell will do 10 points of body damage.</p>
<p>Curse</p>
<p>I curse you with destruction.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell will cause the victim to take double damage from all attacks that would affect them. It can be removed by a Remove Curse or a Dispel Magic. The damage taken is doubled before any Spell Defenses are applied. The Curse effect does not lower a creature’s Threshold, nor does it make the creature affected by additional attacks that would not normally affect it.</p>
<p>Death</p>
<p>I grant you the gift of death.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell causes the victim’s spirit to flee its body, if it has a metabolism. Any armor the character was wearing is still intact, but any spells active on the victim will disappear. This spell brings a character to death, and the only thing that will save the victim is a Life spell.</p>
<p>Delayed Endow</p>
<p>I grant you the power of a delayed endow.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell endows the recipient with the ability to do two extra points of damage for one swing if it hits the target.  The total damage must be announced while swinging.  Once called  the spell is used up whether the blow was successful or not.  Unlike a normal Endow  the recipient may choose when to use a Delayed Endow. The recipient may also expend this spell to rip form Pin as per the monster ability. Delayed endow ill not benefit creatures that have Superhuman Strenght greater than +1  and will only add +1 to a creature with +1 strength. The spell may be stacked iwth other Blade Effects(maximum three spells total)</p>
<p>Desecrate</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to desecrate you.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>The recipient is protected against all non-ranged atacks from living creatures. ranged attacks (such as spells  missle weapons  and gas globes) can affect the recipient. this spell will remain in effect as long as the subject's hands are crossed on their chest and they do not recieve any body damage. I f you are unsure if an attacker is living or not  you will affected by them. YTou may not call a Hold or otherwise go out of game to asertain their status. the cahracter with a Desecrate active may use no game abilities ecept touchcasting on themselves. Attempting to pick up an item will distrupt the spell.</p>
<p>Destroy</p>
<p>I summon a force to destroy your <item>.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will render any tagged object up to the size of a normal door, useless. It can not be used to create a door-sized hole in an object larger than a door. It can target a suit of armor, although the Shield spell, and Dexterity Armor will be unaffected. Armor successfully destroyed will require the tag to be discarded as useless. This spell will not work on an item that has been Rendered Indestructible. It may also be cast at a creature to affect such an item, or to target the creature directly as some creatures may be harmed by this spell. If the caster does not specify an item or if the spell is received from a carrier attack, then it is the target’s choice as to which currently non-rendered item matching the description becomes Destroyed. If no item exists call “got it” see stacking spells "Stacked Effects" on page 47. Destroying an item that has other items within, hanging from, or fastened to it will destroy all of the items. This spell will destroy not only a shield but also any scrolls , or Gas globes, etc. attached to the back. Destroying a trapped door or item will set off and destroy the trap as well. After the item is destroyed the prop for the item remains, but is unusable.</p>
<p>Destroy Undead</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to destroy undead 70.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will destroy any one lesser undead creature. Greater undead will take 70 points of body damage. this spell will not affect a living target  although like all spells it will remove a living person's shield magic or reflect magic.</p>
<p>Detect Magic</p>
<p>I call fourth mystic power to detect magic.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>Casting this spell on an object or person will reveal to the caster and only the caster if any magic is present. Any visible items worn or carried by the target will be revealed, but items hidden under clothing or in bags or boxes will not be. This spell will cover up to a door sized area. The subject must tell the caster which (if any) magic items are visible, and which schools of magic are present on all of the detected items (Earth, Celestial, Both or Other.) If the subject has any spell defenses currently active (such as Endow or Magic Armor), then the subject will detect as magical to the caster. This does not overshadow any items on the person. In other words, the fact that a subject has a Shield spell upon him or her does not cover the fact that a magic item is worn. If cast upon a Circle of Power or Ward, this spell will not only detect the target’s school, but also whether the target’s duration is ten minutes, one hour, one year or two years.</p>
<p>Dispel Magic</p>
<p>I call fourth mystic power to dispel magic.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will dispel all active non-formal magical effects on a given creature or object unless specifically noted by the spell description. A Shield Magic or Reflect Magic will protect all   ther spells on a person from a Dispel Magic, but will be used up in the process. A Dispel Magic potion isn’t stopped by a Shield Magic or a Reflect Magic, and will dispel those spells and all others spells active upon the drinker.</p>
<p>Displacement</p>
<p>I grant you the power of a displacement.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell grants the caster, and only the caster, a shield against the first effect that hits them. It may not be cast upon another target. This will always be the first protective spell lost if it is appropriate to defend against an attack and will be used before a Shield Magic, Elemental Shield, Magic Armor or any other automatic protective effect, though a Formal Magic Cloak or Bane can be used before a Displacement. The caster may choose to accept a touch cast effect under the protection of this spell. When struck by an appropriate attack the defense is automatically triggered. Displacement cannot be Imbued via Formal Magic Cantrip, placed into a Magic Item of any kind (including a Spell Store item), or by any other means transferred to someone else to cast. The proper call for this defense is “Phase.”</p>
<p>Dragon's Breath</p>
<p>I call fourth a dragon's breath 40.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell allows the caster to cast a bolt of magical fire, dealing 40 hit points of eldritch fire damage to the target. The fire is eldritch in origin and will not otherwise set anything alight.</p>
<p>Eldrich Blast</p>
<p>I call fourth a  <flame ice lightning or stone>  blast 45.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell allows the caster to affect a target with a bolt of magical fire, ice, lightning or stone dealing 45 hit points of eldritch damage. The caster may choose which type of damage to throw at the time of the casting, signifying such through the verbal. The damage will not otherwise set anything alight or freeze anything. This spell may also be called <Fire, Ice, Lightning or Stone> Blast for the purposes of magic deliverance, monster abilities, magic items, and similar situations.</p>
<p>Elemental Blade</p>
<p>I grant you the power of an elemental blade.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell allows the recipient to do five extra points of damage for one swing if the blow is successful. The spell is used up whether the blow is successful or not. Unlike an Endow, the recipient may choose when to use an Elemental Blade. The recipient must announce the total damage while swinging. This damage will not set anything alight, freeze it, turn it to stone, etc. The extra damage comes from the spell’s eldritch effect, and its bonus can added fully to damage done by creatures with Superhuman Strength. The spell may be stacked with two other Blade Effects see Table 5-6 on page 64, but the spells will only work one at a time. It does not allow you to hurt a  monster that can only be damaged by magical weapons. When using this spell, you may call out “Fire, Ice, Lightning or Stone” as a damage type. The user of the spell chooses the type of damage done. The damage type is chosen when the damage is added to the weapon blow.</p>
<p>Elemental Shield</p>
<p>I grant you the power of an elemental shield.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell protects the recipient from the next effect with the word “elemental” in the verbal. It is then immediately used up. When used, the call is “Elemental Shield.”</p>
<p>Empathic Healing</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to transfer <effect>.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell allows the caster to transfer one detrimental effect from the target to the caster. The effects this spell may transfer to the caster are Disease, Curse, Paralyze, Silence, Sleep, Taint Blood, Weakness, Wither Limb, Drain, Drain Life, Feeblemind, Hallucinoid, Intoxicant, Nausea, Paralyze, and Vertigo. No effect not on this list may be transferred using Empathic Healing. The caster cannot use spell protectives or combat abilities like Dodg e or Phase to negate the effect upon them. If the effect is not inflicted upon the caster because of immunity to the effect, a formal magic defense, or a magical item, then the spell fails. The caster must take the effect or use a racial resist for the spell to succeed. The caster must begin the duration of the negative effect they take upon themselves from the point they take the effect not when it was originally cast on the one they removed it from.</p>
<p>Enchanted Blade</p>
<p>I grant you the power of an enchanted blade.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell allows the recipient to use the “Magic” weapon type against one opponent for the one battle, in the manner of a Critical Attack page 35 The recipient may choose when to use the Enchanted Blade, and must announce the total damage of the swing while saying “Magic” instead of “Normal” or “Silver.” The spell may be stacked with other Endow/Blade spells (maximum three spells total), but the spells will only work one at a time. Enchanted Blade will have no effect with a Damage Aura or Magic Aura.</p>
<p>Endow</p>
<p>I grant you the power of an endow.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell endows the recipient with the ability to do three extra points of damage on the next swing, if it hits the target. The total damage must be announced while swinging. Once called, the spell is used up whether the blow was successful or not. The spell may be stacked with two other Blade Effects see Table 5-6 on page 64 , but the spells will only work one at a time. It does not allow you to hurt a monster that can only be damaged by magical weapons. Endow will not benefit creatures that have Superhuman Strength greater than +1, and will only add one to a creature with +1 strength.</p>
<p>Enflame</p>
<p>I summon a force to enflame your <item> 20.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell causes any hand-held itemto burst into fire for 5 seconds, dealing 20 points of eldritch fire damage to the person or creature carrying the item as if they were struck by a Flame Bolt. It will also act as a Fumble spell towards that item if the creature was affected by the fire. A defense against Fire will negate this spell.</p>
<p>Extended Hearth</p>
<p>With eldrich force I build an extended hearth.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>When this spell is cast on an existing circle of power or ward it will allow the circle or ward to act as a prepared hearth for the caster for the school this spell was cast from. The prepared hearth will last as long as the circle or ward if they are not already extended through formal magic. If they are already extended through formal magic this spell will last for five days. The extended hearth is only dispelled if the circle or ward is destroyed, a Dispel Magic will not suffice. When cast the caster must place an individually recognizable stylized “H” up on the door or wall or within the center of the circle obviously indicating that a hearth is in affect, the “H” is OOG the way a “W” is for a ward. If the effect is dispelled the “H” must be removed. A player must confirm their “H” is still present before using an extended hearth. A player may cast this spell from both schools of magic in order to have the effect of the hearth for both schools. If they do this the “H” must reflect this to them. Multiple characters can have this effect active on the same area, but each Extended Hearth must have its own “H” which must be recognizable by the player who cast it and distinct fromany others. This spell cannot be thrown.</p>
<p>Flame Bolt</p>
<p>I call fourth a flame Bolt  20.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell deals 20 points of eldritch fire damage to the victim.</p>
<p>Free Undead</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to free undead.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell free an undead creature from the effects of a Trap Undead spell. This spell will not affect a living target, although it will remove a living person’s  Shield Magic or Reflect Magic.</p>
<p>Fumble</p>
<p>I summon a force to fumble your  <item>.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell causes the target to be unable to use a specific hand-held item. Only the item named may be fumbled in this manner. Saying a general description like “weapon” is fine, although if the target is holding two items which match the description, then it is the target’s choice as to which they cannot use. A shield is not considered a “weapon” for purposes of this spell. Spell packets cannot be affected, while orange gas globes can be affected.</p>
<p>Guardian of the Four</p>
<p>I grant you the power of a <fire, ide, lightning or stone> shield.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell grants a shield to fire, ice, lightning, or stone as determined by the caster at the time of casting. This will nearly always be the first protective spell lost if it is appropriate to defend against an attack and will be used before a Shield Magic, Elemental Shield, Magic Armor or any other automatic protective effect other than Displacement which still comes before this spell. This spell will defend against packet delivered attacks and weapon delivered attacks as long as the damage or effect type is appropriate. For combined effects such as Enflame where the spell is both a fire attack and another effect this spell will protect against both. A player may have only a single casting of this spell upon them if another casting is placed upon them it will replace the prior one. When struck by an appropriate attack the spell automatically goes off the target may not choose to accept the spell and save this protection for later. This protective will be set off prior to any more general protective such as a Shield Magic. The caster may choose to accept a touch cast effect under the protection of this spell. When used, the call is “<fire, ice, lightning, stone> Shield.”</p>
<p>Harm Undead</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to harm undead</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will deal 30 points of body damage to an undead creature. This spell will not affect a living target, although like all spells it will remove a living person’s Shield Magic or Reflect Magic.</p>
<p>Help Undead</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to help undead.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will heal an undead creature for 30 points of body damage. This spell will not affect a living target although like all spells it will remove a living person’s Shield Magic or Reflect Magic.</p>
<p>Ice Bolt</p>
<p>I call fourth an ice bolt  15.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell does 15 points of eldritch ice damage to the victim.</p>
<p>Ice Storm</p>
<p>I call fourth an ice storm 35.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell does 35 points of eldritch ice damage to the victim.</p>
<p>Illumination</p>
<p>I grant you the power of illumination.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Days</p>
<p>This spell produces a glowing light and allows the caster to kindle a light wand. The light can then be used by anyone. It will not work without a phys-rep. You cannot cast a Illumination spell at a person or tree and have the person or tree glow. There must be a properly dimmed flashlight or other out-of-game light source provided. The spell lasts until it is dispelled. If using a flashlight for this spell, the lens of the flashlight must be covered by a cloth, tissue paper or a gel to diffuse the light. Do not shine the light in anyone’s face. This spell can not be thrown.</p>
<p>Imprision</p>
<p>With eldrich force I build a prison.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 10 Minutes</p>
<p>This spell seals the victim into a rigid, form-fitting and unbreakable barrier, trapping them within. The victim cannot move, speak, touch-cast, Gypsy Curse, or perform any game skills requiring movement. The spell lasts for ten minutes, but may be dropped by the caster at any time if he or she touches the victim and states “Imprison down.” This statement is out of-game, and can be used even if the caster is Silenced or inside the Imprison. Any observers who hear the statement are aware that the Imprison was dropped, and they might know who dropped it. A Dispel Magic will bring down the Imprison, but will not dispel any other spell effects on the creature inside. Any creature sealed within an Imprison spell cannot be affected by any effect or damage, nor can they be moved. A victim of the Imprison is completely aware of his or her surroundings and unless unconscious or otherwise impaired will remember all that occurred while Imprisoned. This spell will prevent the victim from being searched and only the caster may deliver a Killing Blow to the recipient with the phrase “Imprison Down” after the three count. If the Killing Blow fails (for example, if the creature inside is immune to the caster’s attack), then the Imprison will drop as soon as the Killing Blow is completed and the creature may then defend itself.</p>
<p>Improved Hearth</p>
<p>With eldrich force I build an improved hearth.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 1 Hour</p>
<p>This spell must be cast on an area already prepared as a hearth using the skill Prepare Hearth. Once cast by the character who prepared the hearth the duration of the hearth is extended to 1 hour but only works for the school of magic from which it was cast. The hearth no longer ends if the caster leaves it, is targeted with a Dispel Magic, or dies but it will end if the room is targeted with a Dispel Magic. When cast the caster must place an individually recognizable stylized “H” up on the door or wall obviously indicating that a hearth is in affect, the “H” is OOG the way a “W” is for a ward. If the room is dispelled the “H” must be removed. A player must confirm their “H” is still present before using an improved hearth. A player may cast this spell from both schools of magic in order to have the effect of the hearth for both schools. If they do this the “H” must reflect this to them. Multiple characters can have this effect active on the same area, but each Improved Hearth must have its own “H” which must be recognizable by the player who cast it and distinct from any others. This spell can not be thrown.</p>
<p>Inspiration</p>
<p>I grant you the gift of inspiration.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>The recipient chooses one daily use skill that they have purchased with build points and that they have already used that day to be refreshed. This spell will restore only normal times per day skills including a single spell slot. It will not renew powers from items or production skills or special abilities of any kind, only skills conforming to the current edition of the NERO rules. It will renew a single level of formal magic if the target so chooses but only for use in casting a Cantrip not for casting of formal magic. If used to renew a Critical Slay or Assassinate it will renew only the 100 slay or assassinate it will not renew a 200 slay or assassinate selectively unless all other slays or assassinates have been renewed through some other means first. A single target may only be affected by one inspiration for each time they can study to reset their skills (This means once per reset) and spells and casting the spell on them again will have no effect until after the next reset point.</p>
<p>Lesser Divestiture</p>
<p>With eldrich force I remove your investiture.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will Divest a person from a Ward or Mystic Lock. The caster of this spell must already be Invested. If Divesting from a Ward, the caster and the subject must both  be within the Ward at the time of casting. If Divesting from a Mystic Lock, the caster and subject must both be touching the Mystic Locked chest at the time of casting. The subject’s name must then be removed from the appropriate marshal notes. A person Divested is no longer Invested in the Ward or Mystic Lock. This spell can not be thrown.</p>
<p>Lesser Investiture</p>
<p>With eldrich force I grant you investiture.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 days</p>
<p>This spell will Invest a person into a Ward or Mystic Lock. The caster of this spell must already be Invested. If Investing into a Ward, the caster and the subject must both be within the Ward at the time of casting. If Investing into a Mystic Lock, the caster and subject must both be touching the Mystic Locked chest at the time of casting. The subject’s name must then be added to the appropriate marshal notes. This spell can not be thrown.</p>
<p>Life</p>
<p>I grant you the gift of life.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell must be cast within five minutes of a creature’s death. It restores the creature to one Body Point and the creature is not forced to resurrect. This spell is the only thing that can save someone who has been given a killing blow or hit by a Death effect. This spell will not normally affect a living target or an undead creature, although it will remove a living person or ndead creature’s Shield Magic or Reflect Magic.</p>
<p>Lightning Bolt</p>
<p>I call fourth a lightning bolt  10.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell does 10 points of eldritch lightning damage to the victim.</p>
<p>Lightning Storm</p>
<p>I call fourth a lightning storm 30</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell does 30 points of eldritch lightning damage to the victim.</p>
<p>Magic Armor</p>
<p>I grant you the power of a magic armor.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>A Magic Armor spell will protect the recipient from the next single strike by a NERO-safe weapon or any attack with the word “physical” in the verbal. The recipient must state “Magic Armor.” The attack and the Magic Armor will then be expended. This does not protect against a Killing Blow or a fall, nor does it work against any traps other than weapon traps. A Magic Armor will be blown even if the amount of damage called is “zero.”</p>
<p>Magic Missle</p>
<p>I call fourth a magic  missle 5.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell does 5 points of eldritch damage to the victim.</p>
<p>Magic Storm</p>
<p>I call fourth a magic storm 5.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Concentration</p>
<p>This spell allows the caster to continuously channel eldritch energy so long as their feet remain planted. At the time of casting, the caster must plant both feet. As long as both feet remain planted and Concentration is maintained, the caster may throw a packet after completing the incant “Magic Storm 5” While the spell is in effect, the caster can perform no other skill  nor cast any other spell, nor activate magical items, but can speak. Each packet thrown acts as a separate spell which causes 5 points of eldritch damage to the target.</p>
<p>Mystic Lock</p>
<p>With eldrich force I build a mystic lock.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Days</p>
<p>This spell magically seals a single box or chest which becomes immobile once the spell is cast. It will not work on a container that already has magical properties. The size of the box is limited to a rectangular solid 3ft x 3ft x 6ft and no larger. No effect, person or object may pass through the Mystic Lock unless as described below. Anyone touching the Mystic Lock during the casting of the spell will receive an Investiture to the Mystic Lock. The names of the people Invested must be written in the room’s marshal notes. Investiture in a Mystic Lock allows you to place and retrieve items within the chest, however no people or dead bodies may ever be placed inside a Mystic Lock. Mystic Lock is not affected by Dispel Magic. The chest must be visibly marked to indicate the presence of the Mystic Lock by attaching a large clearly visible “W”. You may not Mystic Lock a box in order to obstruct or hinder movement. This spell cannot be thrown.</p>
<p>Paralyze</p>
<p>I curse you with paralysis.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>This spell completely immobilizes the victim. The target may not move any part of their body and may be given a Killing Blow while thus trapped. If the victim is rendered unconscious or someone  attempts to pose them, they will collapse to the ground but will remain Paralyzed. An Unparalyze spell or a Dispel Magic will release a victim from the Paralyze. A Release spell will not work. This spell only works on creatures that have a metabolism. Some creatures such as undead, golems or some elementals are not affected by this spell.</p>
<p>Pin</p>
<p>With mystic force I pin you.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Line of Sight</p>
<p>This spell will root the target’s right foot in place. The target may pivot their body 360 degrees but may not move their right foot. The Pin can be removed with a Release spell or a Dispel Magic.</p>
<p>Poison Shield</p>
<p>I grant you the power of a poison shield.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell protects the recipient from the next attack with the word “poison” in the verbal. It is then immediately used up. It will not protect against ingested elixirs. When used, the call is “Poison Shield.”</p>
<p>Purify Blood</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to purify your blood</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will cleanse the recipient’s blood, removing any and all alchemical effects or monster effects with the word “poison” in the verbal that are currently active on the character,  even beneficial ones. It will also remove the effects Berserk, Feeblemind, Forget-it-Well, Forget-Me-Not, Hallucinoid, Intoxicant, Nausea, Paranoia, and Vertigo regardless of the delivery type. It will not remove a Poison Shield or Enslavement. It is also a very good in-game cure for an in-game hangover. Purify Blood will not cure any damage previously wrought by a numerical poison effect.</p>
<p>Refit Armor</p>
<p>I summon a force to refit this armor.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell instantly refits armor to its full value This spell only works on actual physical armor.</p>
<p>Reflect Magic</p>
<p>I call fourth mystic power to reflect magic.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell will reflect the next spell cast at the recipient back upon the caster, after which it is used up. The recipient must say “Reflect Magic” to inform the caster that the spell was returned. The original caster is still the caster of the spell. This spell lasts until used up or Dispelled, and cannot be used in conjunction with a Shield Magic. If you have a Reflect Magic active, you may still “accept” spells that are touchcast. You cannot “accept” thrown spells. See"Spell Disruption" on page 46 for more details. Reflect Magic will only work on spells delivered via packet, Glyph (See the Formal Magic section for more details), or Spell Strike.</p>
<p>Regeneration</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to regenerate you.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 1 Minute</p>
<p>This spell restores a living target to his or her full body points. Once the spell is successfully cast, the target will begin to regenerate as per the rules of the special ability Regeneration. Regeneration requires that the character stand or sit in one place for one minute and concentrate If this process is interrupted before its completion, the spell is lost for no effect. The target may not be restored to a total of body higher than is appropriate for his race and level via this spell. This spell may not be used to aid a dead character in any way. This spell only affects targets which are healed by earth magic. This spell does not remove any other negative effects.</p>
<p>Release</p>
<p>With mystic force I release you.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will release a creature caught in a Pin, Bind, Web or Confine effect, as well as negating all active Paste of Stickiness effects upon the creature. It will not free someone who has been Paralyzed or Imprisoned. A Release spell can also be used to free someone bound by any non-magical means (such as handcuffed, tied up, or gripped by a tentacle). It will not unlock a cell door, but will open a stock if the creature is locked in one.</p>
<p>Remove Curse</p>
<p>I rid you of your curse.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will cancel a Curse spell but will not restore any Body Points lost. It will not rid anyone of a Gypsy Curse.</p>
<p>Remove Drain</p>
<p>I rid you of your drain.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>The target of this spell is cured of the drain effect but not of the Drain Life effect which still requires a Life spell to remove.</p>
<p>Remove Fear</p>
<p>I rid you of your fear.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will remove the effect fear from the target. The caster may continue to perform the verse without actually casting the spell on a target each time the verse is stated without disrupting the spell.</p>
<p>Remove Physical Affliction</p>
<p>I rid you of your physical affliction.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will remove all currently active effects with “Physical” in the verbal from the target. Damage is not cured.</p>
<p>Remove Weakness</p>
<p>I rid you of your weakness.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will remove all active Weakness effects on a creature.</p>
<p>Repel</p>
<p>With mystic force I repel you.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Concentration</p>
<p>This spell requires the caster to hit a target and hold the hand used to throw the packet palm out, facing the recipient. The victim and the target must then stay at least 10 feet apart while the spell is in effect. When the spell is first cast, the recipient must move 10 feet away from the caster. After that, neither the recipient nor the caster may approach within 10 feet of each other; the caster cannot approach the recipient any easier than the recipient may approach the caster. Either could back away. If it is impossible for the recipient to move more than 10 feet away from the caster because of physical obstructions when the spell is cast, the caster must first attempt to move 10 feet away from the recipient. The caster must hold out a hand, palm out, towards the recipient. That hand cannot be used for any other purpose. This spell is not a charm effect and cannot be resisted with the racial ability Resist Charm.</p>
<p>Restore Limbs</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to restore you limbs.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell causes all of the target’s Withered limbs to become usable and restored.</p>
<p>Sanctuary</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to grant you sanctuary.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell will remain in effect as long as the subject’s hands are clasped overhead and they do not receive any body damage. The recipient is protected against all non-ranged attacks from undead creatures. Ranged attacks (such as spells, missile weapons, and gas globes) can affect the recipient. If you are unsure if an attacker is undead or not, you will be affected by them. You may not call a Hold or otherwise go out of game to ascertain their status. The character with a Sanctuary active may use no game abilities except touchcasting on themselves.  Attempting to pick up an item will disrupt the spell.</p>
<p>Shatter</p>
<p>I summon a force to shatter your <item>.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell may be cast upon any weapon or shield or any item up to a shield in size. It may also be cast at a creature, to affect such an item. This spell will not shatter a shield-like hole in something larger than a shield, nor will it have any effect on armor. The item affected is rendered completely useless. This spell will not work on an unshatterable item or a magically  protected item. Shattering an item that has other items within or fastened to it will destroy all of the items. This spell will shatter not only a shield but also any scrolls attached to the back. Shattering a box or door will set off any traps present as well as the items within. After the item is shattered the prop for the item remains, but is unusable.</p>
<p>Shield</p>
<p>With eldrich force I grant you a shield 5.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell gives the recipient five extra Armor Points. These extra points are the first Armor Points lost due to damage.</p>
<p>Shield Magic</p>
<p>I call fourth mystic power to shield magic.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell will cancel the next spell cast at the recipient, including beneficial spells, after which it is used up. You must say “Shield Magic” immediately when this spell is used. Shield Magic will only work on spells delivered via packet, Glyph (See the Formal Magic section for more details), or Spell Strike. Shield Magic cannot be used in conjunction with a Reflect Magic. If you have a Shield Magic active, you may still “accept” spells that are touch-cast. You cannot “accept” thrown spells. See "Spell Disruption" on page 46 for more details.</p>
<p>Shun</p>
<p>I command you to shun me.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>This spell causes the victim to feel great discomfort around the caster. The victim will not attack the caster, and will immediately move at least 10 feet away from the caster and stay at least that far away while the spell is in effect. If the victim is within the 10 feet when the spell is cast, the victim must move away, but never in a manner that will endanger the victim or cause direct harm to them. In other words, they cannot be made to jump off a cliff or walk towards a magical rift or do any other action which would cause harm (much like a Charm spell cannot force the victim to take self-destructive actions). This spell does not create a 10 foot magical circle around the caster which is effective only upon the vic tim; if the victim has to come closer than ten feet in order to get away (say for example, to pass close to the caster in order to get to an exit), then that is permissible. While within that 10 foot area however, the victim can take no in-game actions against the caster. If the caster attacks the target, the Shun ends immediately. This spell is a type of charm and can be resisted with the racial ability Resist Charm, and it can be cured with an Aw aken spell or Dispel Magic spell. Stronger charms such as Vampire Charm or Enslavement will override its effects. See Table 5-6 on page 64</p>
<p>Shun Animal</p>
<p>I command this animal to shun me.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>This acts as a Shun spell, but will only affect an ordinary animal.</p>
<p>Silence</p>
<p>I command you to silence.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 minutes</p>
<p>The victim of this spell cannot talk and cannot cast any spell. The victim must still call out the damage points his or her weapons do if combat ensues while the spell is in effect, as well as any out-of-game “trigger” phrases such as “Reflect Magic” or “Parry.” The silence can be removed by either Aw aken or Dispel Magic. This is not a charm spell and thus it cannot be resisted by those with the Resist Charm ability.</p>
<p>Silver Aura</p>
<p>I grant you the power of a silver aura.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell will allow the recipient to use the weapon type silver against one opponent in the manner of a critical attack. It will not confer any additional damage. The target may choose to end the effect at any time but cannot reactivate it without using another casting of the spell. The spell may be stacked with two other Blade Effects see Table 5-6 on page 64 , but the spells will only work one at a time.</p>
<p>Sleep</p>
<p>I command you to sleep.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 minutes</p>
<p>Sleep causes the target to instantly fall into a deep sleep. The target will not awaken for 5 minutes unless someone shakes them vigorously while shouting for them to wake. It takes one minute of shaking and shouting to wake a person this way. An Awaken or Dispel Magic spell will wake the victim immediately. This spell will not work on some creatures without a metabolism, such as undead creatures, golems, or some giant insects. It can be resisted by creatures with a Resist Sleep ability.</p>
<p>Stabilize</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to stabilize you.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Continuous</p>
<p>When cast the target of this spell is stabilized as if the First Aid skill had been successfully used upon them. For this to work the target must have been able to be affected by the skill first aid. The caster may continue to perform the verse without actually casting the spell on a target each time the verse is stated without breaking the spell.</p>
<p>Stone Bolt</p>
<p>I call fourth a stone bolt 25.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell deals 25 points of eldritch stone damage to the victim.</p>
<p>Taint Blood</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to taint your blood.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell will introduce impurities into the victim’s blood. The victim is left extremely weak, and unable to fight or move faster than normal walking speed. The victim becomes unable to use any game skills. This spell might not function against creatures with no metabolism. This spell can be removed by a Purify Blood spell or a Dispel Magic spell.</p>
<p>Tarry</p>
<p>I grant you the gift of tarrying.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>The target of this spell must be dead and within their five minute death count and able to benefit from a Life spell. The target will have their death count extended by five minutes. This spell can be cast on a target multiple times but they must have five minutes or less left on their death count or it will not work and the spell will be lost. Tarry cannot extend a death count past the time of reset and if it has already extended the count past the initial five minutes when reset occurs the effect will end and the character will go to resurrect. This spell can never be used to allow the target to receive a life spell gained in the next reset period if the initial death count expired during the previous reset period. It can never be used to force a character to take multiple castings of the obliterate formal. At any point past the initial five minute death count the target may chose to end their count and r esurrect immediately, a spirit may not be held for longer than their initial five minutes using a tarry against their will even if enslaved or controlled in any other manner.</p>
<p>Trap Undead</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to trap undead.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Line of Sight</p>
<p>This spell will act upon a lesser undead as a Pin spell, but the undead may not rip free. This spell will not affect a living target, although it will remove a living person’s Shield Magic or Reflect Magic.</p>
<p>Turn Undead</p>
<p>I Call upon the earth to turn undead.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>This spell will affect lesser undead creatures, causing them to leave the area of combat immediately by attempting to break Line of Sight. A Dispel Magic or Free Undead will rid the  creature of this spell, allowing it to return. Greater undead are not affected by this spell in the same manner. This spell will not affect a living target, although it will remove any creature’s Shield Magic or Reflect Magic.</p>
<p>Unparalyze</p>
<p>I rid you of your paralysis.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will free the subject from all paralyzing effects.</p>
<p>Ward</p>
<p>With eldrich force I build a ward.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:No		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 days</p>
<p>This spell magically seals a single room or an entire building. The object affected must be an actual unmovable structure such as a building, a tent, or an unmovable wagon. No effect, person or object may pass through the Ward unless as described below. Anyone within the Ward during the entire casting of the spell will receive an Investiture to the Ward. The names of the people Invested must be written in the room’s marshal notes. Investiture in a Ward allows you to enter and leave the warded area at will as well as allow others to enter and leave by saying “The Ward recognizes you”, and otherwise follows the rules for Extended Circles of Power described on page 50. The building must be visibly marked to indicate the presence of Ward by placing a large “W” on the door. This spell takes five minutes to cast during which time the caster rests his hand upon the primary portal. Anyone inside a structure that is being warded will be aware of the casting and will be awoken by it if normally sleeping. This spell cannot be thrown. Ward is not be affected by Dispel Magic.</p>
<p>Weakness</p>
<p>I curse you with weakness.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell will curse the victim to do 5 points less damage with every swing (minimum damage being zero, of course). This spell does not actually reduce a creature’s strength. It affects all weapon damage in the same way, whether the weapon is used with one hand or two hands. This spell lasts until removed with a Remove Weakness or a Dispel Magic. Multiple Weakness effects do not stack.</p>
<p>Web</p>
<p>With mystic force I web you.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes	 :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Line of Sight</p>
<p>This spell snares the arms of its victim, binding them straight to its sides, and immobilizes the victim completely from the neck down. The victim may talk freely, but may not use any game skills requiring use of the arms, including using a weapon or shield, casting a spell, or activating a gas globe. The victim may not walk, run, or be moved in any way. Any item the victim is holding cannot be dropped. However, since the effect allows the victim to be searched, anyone else can choose to physically remove a hand-held item from the victim simply by  searching” them. Even a victim with Superhuman Strength cannot prevent himself from being “searched” in this manner. This spell does not prevent the victim from being searched or being given a Killing Blow.</p>
<p>Wither Limb</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to wither your <Limb>.</p>
<p>Celestial:No	 :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes		 ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell causes the target’s limb to become aged and infirm. The limb may be specified by the caster (right or left leg or arm). You can have up to four Wither Limb spells upon you at a time. No weapon may be wielded by that limb nor may the limb be used for locomotion or spell casting. If a leg is withered you must kneel down (unless you can’t due to a medical reason), you may not hop on the remaining leg. Only an arm or leg can be thus withered. Tentacles or similar appendages are considered arms for this purpose. The head, tongue, or any other such organ do not count as limbs. A Dispel Magic will remove all active Wither Limb spells. If the caster does not specify, or if the spell is received from a potion or carrier attack, then it is the target’s choice as to which currently un-withered limb becomes withered. If all your limbs are withered, call “got it.” See "Stacked Effects" on page 47.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Common Formal Magic Spells</p>
<p>Formal Magic Scrolls are magical scrolls of immense power in and of themselves and will always detect as magical. They are treated as Magic Items for purposes of stealing. A Formal Magic scroll can only be read or copied by one who has the skill Formal Magic in the appropriate school. To everyone else, the scroll will be unreadable.</p>
<p>Here is a description of some of the most common types of Formal Magic effects on Magic Items. This is not a complete list, but merely the ones which most players will encounter. Please see the Formal Magic Casting Rules and individual Formal Magic Spell descriptions for more details.</p>
<p>Bane</p>
<p>A magical defense that reflects the attack back upon the attacker. It works at will (even before a spell defense if desired), and protects against only one type of effect. For example, a Bane versus Sleep could be used against a Sleep spell or a Sleep gas poison.</p>
<p>Cloak</p>
<p>A magical defense that works at will (even before a spell defense if desired) and protects against only one type of effect such as Fire or Binding Magic. For example, a Cloak versus Fire could be used against both a Flame Bolt spell or an Elemental flame packet attack.</p>
<p>Obliteration</p>
<p>A very powerful Formal Magic that causes the victim to suffer the same effect as dying and resurrecting three times, although only one trip to the Earth circle is necessary. However, only one “pick” is made from death’s bag. After the Formal Magic is complete, the victim is still able to receive a Life spell for the next five minutes, and only one such spell is necessary to restore the creature to one body point. If a Life spell is received, the creature is not forced to resurrect at all.</p>
<p>Spirit Link</p>
<p>Spirit Link magically attaches an item to a spirit, thus making it unstealable. The item must always remain in contact with the creature to which it is linked. (It does not have to touch the body directly; a glove or other piece of clothing can come between the item and the person.) When a creature with a Spirit Linked item dies, the Spirit Linked item becomes insubstantial with the spirit and travels to resurrect, reforming with the spirit. If the item is a container, it does not bring the contents with it. If the creature permanently dies, the body and item return to the point where the body dissipated. The item is then linked to the next creature with a spirit that takes picks it up, even through gloves or other articles of clothing or armor.</p>
<p>Spirit Mark</p>
<p>Used to mark a particular person’s spirit. The mark is always present on the spirit’s body, in the location and with a design as decided by the original Formal Magic caster. This mark can be covered by normal means. </p>
<p>Vengeance</p>
<p>Causes a retributive strike of pure magical damage to any being inflicting a killing blow upon the bearer of this formal magic. This damage occurs after the killing blow and is not avoidable in any manner. When a Vengeance is triggered, the call will be “<number> Arcane Vengeance”</p>
<p>Formal Magic Components</p>
<p>In order to cast a spell from a Formal Magic scroll, one must also have the Formal Magic Components. These components are represented in-game by a tag with a description of the item and its level and type. Some chapters also provide the actual prop itself. If your chapter does not, it can only increase your role-playing fun if you were to provide your own props. </p>
<p>Formal Magic Components may be found as treasure in a module, on an NPC, or randomly in the woods. </p>
<p>Any character can tell if they are looking at a formal component automatically. To identify the level and type of components (i.e. P4 or C1) you must possess one level of the formal magic skill of either school.</p>
<p>Components come in various ‘flavors’: Power (P), Creation (C), Elemental (E), Time (T), Void (V), Destruction (D), Spirit (S).</p>
<p>Each component has a value of 1, 2 or 4. Formal Magic costs are listed with the total value of each type of needed component. For example, P5 means any combination of Power components totaling a value of 5. One spell, Gr eater Extension, specifically requires a Power component of value 2 or 4 in addition to other components. Components expire no longer than 2 years after the issue date.If there is no printed expiration date then the expiration date is assumed to be one year.</p>
<p>Extended Circles of Power</p>
<p>In order to use the powers of an Extended Circle, you must be Invested in that Circle. Investiture is a Formal Magic Spell that must be cast upon you in that Circle.</p>
<p>In order to pass into or out of the Circle, you must be “recognized” by an invested member of the Circle. The invested member must clearly gesture, touch, or name the subject creature and must state “the Circle recognizes you.” This is an out-of-game statement, so it can be made while Silenced. The effect is understood in-game by all who hear it.</p>
<p>Upon being recognized, a person must immediately enter or exit the Circle. If the recognized person does not immediately act upon the recognition, then the recognition will expire.  </p>
<p>Invested members may walk freely into or out of the Circle, since it is assumed that they “recognize” themselves. Invested members who are unconscious (or conscious, yet unwilling) will not pass through the Circle unless recognized by someone else. When using combat skills or spells, you must be completely inside or outside of the Circle of Power. For example, you cannot begin a spell incant inside the Circle, and then step out to throw your packet.</p>
<p>If you want to raid a Circle of Power, the same rules as raiding a cabin will apply; you must have a marshal present. See “Searching a Cabin” on page 95</p>
<p>Identify</p>
<p>An Extended Celestial Circle is capable of performing an Identify on an item or person. The item or person to be Identified and the invested person performing the Identify must be within the circle completely. The invested person touches the target of the identify and says “Identify”.</p>
<p>If the target is an object directly then the invested person reads the tag describing the item’s properties and learns them in the time it takes to read the information.</p>
<p>If the target is a person then the target tells the invested person which active spells or Formal Magic spells are active on them as well as what magical items they have in their possession and what the properties of those items are and how to activate them as though the items had been directly identified by the invested person. Sometimes an Identify will reveal additional properties of magical creatures. It takes as long to perform an identification of a person as it does for the target to describe all of the results.</p>
<p>Everyone who hears or observes the Identify call/process is aware of an identification taking place though they should attempt not to overhear the results. If you are Out of Game able to tell who the person performing the identification is, then you know who it is in game as well. If a transform is active and Identified, the school of it and the name of it are revealed, but neither the presence nor any information about a dormant transformation is revealed. You can prevent an Identification unless you’re helpless.</p>
<p>The time to Identify is In Game. If you’re interrupted then you are interrupted (including if contact is broken by the subject). </p>
<p>While there is no set order to presenting the information and you decide where to start, you must give out all the information you have with the chance of 3rd party interruption</p>
<p>Resurrection</p>
<p>An Extended Earth Circle is capable of providing Resurrections.</p>
<p>The spirit to be Resurrected must be in the Circle. This will take 5 minutes to complete and will bring a body to full body points.</p>
<p>During the 5 minutes, it is apparent to all observers that a resurrection is occurring, although the exact identity is unrecognizable to all except the invested healer performing the resurrection. The</p>
<p>healer may choose to reveal the identity of the person they are resurrecting, if desired. For more on resurrections, see “Matters of Life and Death” on page 22.</p>
<p>Magic Items</p>
<p>Magic items can be found or made through the NERO Formal Magic System©. Most give the wearer the ability to utilize a spell and some items grant the wearer effects from the Formal Magic system.</p>
<p>Until you have an item Identified, you will not have the tag for the item and thus will not be able to use it, even if you are already aware of the item’s power. You must proceed to the Mages’ Guild or monster camp to receive the tag. If you are given the item and are told in-game what the item’s powers are and how it is used, you may use the item but must go to the Mages Guild or monster camp immediately thereafter to get the tag. Make sure that any player that gives you a Magic Item phys-rep also gives you the Magic Item Tag.</p>
<p>Activating Magic Items</p>
<p>Spells from a magic item act just like a regular spell. They provide the character, no matter what class or level, the ability to use that spell. The correct process to activate an item is to use the phrase “Activate” followed by the spell incant. For Example: “Activate With Mystic Force I Bind You”.</p>
<p>In addition, all the normal rules for casting apply. You must have your hand free, have a packet, be conscious, etc. So you cannot activate an item when in a Web, unconscious, dead, or when tied up. Activating an item IS NOT a Game Ability, so you CAN use an item when you cannot otherwise use a Game Ability or Skill, such as when under the effects of a Taint Blood spell.</p>
<p>Magic Item Slots</p>
<p>Chapters may specify how many magic items a player may have active at any given time. This number is between one and five and is clearly posted at event check-in or on the chapter’s website.</p>
<p>If a character has more items on them than the allowed limit they must have a clearly delineated method to separate the active and inactive magic items tags. In order to switch between an active and inactive item at least one minute must be spent while you physically switch your tags between active and inactive. You may only make one switch at a time. If you lose possession of a magic item tag that item becomes inactive for you. During this time you may use no game skills. Characters must be conscious with at least one hand free to switch items between active and inactive states.</p>
<p>The following Formal Magic Spells will not cease to work on a magic item when it goes from active to inactive: Render Indestructible, Extend Form al Magic, Gr eater Extension, Spirit Link, Spirit Lock, and Delimit.</p>
<p>Any item can still be used while inactive, but only with the benefit of the effects listed above.</p>
<p>This limitation on active magic items applies to both Unrestricted and Local Chapter Only Items only as a total (ex: 2 LCO and 3 Unrestricted “active” items in a 5 item slot campaign.)</p>
<p>Spirit as Magic Item</p>
<p>For only the purposes of Magic Item Slots, a character’s Spirit counts as a single magic item that can be made active as a whole.</p>
<p>Only the following formal magic spells count for the purposes of this “item:” Enchant, Cloak (Minor), Bane (Minor), Spell Store, Protection Aura, Cloak, Bane, Expanded Enchantment, Spirit Link, Spirit Lock. All other Spirit targeting formal magic spells fall outside of the Magic Item Slot rules. Please note that Spirit Link and Spirit Lock do not cease to work on an item that has been made inactive. </p>
<p>A PC is always aware of all formal magic spells on their spirit, including, school, specific type, and duration as applicable. </p>
<p>Chapter 6: Game Play </p>
<p>Combat</p>
<p>Safety is NERO’s main concern. These rules are designed to give players the feel of medieval combat without the pain and suffering of the real thing.</p>
<p>The Hold Rule</p>
<p>This is the single most important rule in this entire book. Read it and take it to heart.</p>
<p>Anyone can call a hold in a fight if they see an unsafe situation happening or about to happen. “Hold!” should be yelled so that everyone in battle can hear it—otherwise, it may be followed by another flurry of swings. When a Hold is called, </p>
<p>1. Stay exactly where you are </p>
<p>2. Drop to one knee (unless you can’t due to a medical reason)</p>
<p>3. Do Not Move.</p>
<p>Do not look around you or talk to people about anything not connected with the Hold. You can use this time to update your tags and remove any spells that you have cast. You can also pick up spell packets from the ground or from your pouch as long as you return to your original spot before the game is resumed.</p>
<p>This is not a time to study someone and see if they are an NPC or a PC, nor is it a chance to look behind you and see if anyone is sneaking up on you. Please play fair and try not to gather information while the Hold is being sorted out. When the reason the Hold was called is resolved, then the person calling the hold should call a Lay-on. First, insure that everyone is ready to resume play, then call “3. . .2. . .1. . .Lay-on!”</p>
<p>Hold can also be called for excessive zeal on the part of an opponent. The infraction should be reported to a marshal. Repeated complaints will get a player removed from combat. </p>
<p>Hold can also be called if anyone’s eyeglasses are knocked off.</p>
<p>You cannot call a Hold to collect spell packets even though they are out of-game. You may pick up packets during a Hold that has been called for another reason.</p>
<p>Collecting tags or treasure is not a legitimate reason for calling a Hold. Tag bookkeeping should be done after the battle is over, not during it.</p>
<p>Anyone who ignores a Hold called for any reason will face severe disciplinary action and possible expulsion. This is usually used for emergencies and not to be treated lightly. Stop what you are doing immediately and find out why a Hold was called, then do what you can to help. You must return to your original spot before the Lay-on is called. If you see a crowd of people kneeling down, then they are probably in a Hold. Do not approach the group until the Hold is over.</p>
<p>If you are in the middle of a battle and everyone starts dropping to one knee, then a Hold has probably been called and you did not hear it.</p>
<p>Counted Actions</p>
<p>Some actions cannot actually be performed for reasons of safety or reality, but must be considered as taking some time to complete. Such actions will have a specific count, usually three, and a definite phrase to indicate what is happening.</p>
<p>For example, to simulate a zombie rising from the ground, the NPC playing the zombie could say “I climb out of the ground one, I climb out of the ground two, I climb out of the ground three.” During the time in which the player is saying this, he or she is completely vulnerable to attack and cannot use any game abilities except Dodge,</p>
<p>Phase, Return and Resist. These abilities cause the counted action to be interrupted. The skill is used up, and the count is aborted and must be started again.</p>
<p>A counted action such as breaking a binding effect (using “Rip From ...”), performing a Killing Blow, or going Gaseous requires the same number of seconds as the number of the count, or the duration of the count, whichever is the longest. This means that a Killing Blow requires at least 3 seconds to perform, no matter how fast the player says “Killing Blow 1, Killing Blow 2, Killing Blow 3”. </p>
<p>In the case of simultaneous, identical length counts, who ever started the count first “wins” it does not matter how fast you say it. Spell defenses such as Shield Magic do not interrupt a counted action. </p>
<p>For example, Cerik the vampire is turning gaseous. During the three count, he is hit with a Cure Light Wounds spell. He takes the damage from the spell but it is not enough to destroy him, so he can continue his three count. Example two: Cerik gets hit with a Destroy Undead spell. This would destroy him, so he uses his Phase skill. The use of that skill has interrupted his three count, so the Gaseous Form skill has been used up, and unless he has that skill twice, he cannot attempt it again.</p>
<p>Before performing a counted action, NPCs will often take their places while wearing a white headband. Players who see this can have their characters experience an “eerie feeling” that something is amiss. This is not an excuse to metagame as to exactly what will happen, but role-playing caution is acceptable.</p>
<p>This is not a way to invent your own abilities. All such actions are defined by NERO. Counted Actions are not appropriate for actions you can actually perform safely and within the rules.</p>
<p>Body Contact</p>
<p>The only contact allowed during battle is by weapon. Any other type of fighting contact such as grabbing someone, hitting, or kicking is strictly forbidden. Violation of this rule is the shortest path to disciplinary action.</p>
<p>Pinning and Trapping Weapons</p>
<p>Although “pinning” weapons is a mainstay of many swashbuckling movies, many of the moves used to free yourself from a weapon pinning are dangerous and as such not allowed in NERO combat. As a result, the following restrictions have been placed on “pinning” or “trapping” weapons:</p>
<p>Trapping</p>
<p>Any weapon shaped in such a way as to trap weapons (whether accidentally, or by design) is expressly forbidden.</p>
<p>“Trapping” occurs when one weapon is used to hold another weapon so that it becomes useless. A weapon with multiple tines for instance can be used to grab and twist the opponent’s blade, thus “trapping” it.</p>
<p>Any weapon that is reported as trapping weapons will not be allowed in game. A marshal has the right to reject any weapon for this reason.</p>
<p>Pinning</p>
<p>“Pinning” occurs when one weapon is used to apply force on an opponent’s weapon, capturing the weapon by holding it against a wall or a tree or other stationery object.</p>
<p>Pinning of weapons can only be done with another weapon, and only outdoors. Indoors, the limitations of the situation lead to an unnecessary chance of injury. If your weapon is pinned, you may pull the weapon straight back to free it. If the weapon is shaped in such a way that it is not possible to pull it out, then you’re stuck—the weapon is pinned and there’s nothing you can do about it. You can back up to try to free yourself and your weapon, but shoving your opponent or charging are not allowed.</p>
<p>Charging</p>
<p>During NERO combat you must never come into physical contact with your opponent. It is the responsibility of all parties involved in combat to ensure that there is always a safe distance between combatants. If you are crowding your opponent so much that he or she must step back to avoid body contact with you, you are Charging. No combatant should be able to touch the torso of an opponent in combat. If you can reach out and touch the torso of an opponent, then you are too close. Any combatant who has moved too close must increase the distance to be greater than his or her arm length, though at no time may someone shove away an opponent or otherwise initiate physical   contact. In the case of extreme differences in arm length, the combatant with the shorter arm length is allowed to approach close enough to strike their opponent so long as they cannot touch the opponent’s torso with their own hand.</p>
<p>Legal Targets</p>
<p>Legal targets include the entire body except the head, neck, throat, hands from the wrist out, and the groin. A player observed to be</p>
<p>hitting restricted areas repeatedly is subject to disciplinary action. </p>
<p>You may not intentionally block a hit with an illegal target.</p>
<p>Blocked and deflected shots do not count. This is admittedly a judgment call. If the block was good, then the weapon just grazed an arm or leg and the shot does not count. If the block was weak and the swing hit with about half or more normal force then the hit should count.</p>
<p>Unskilled Weapon Use</p>
<p>If you do not have the skill to use a weapon you are carrying, or if you are presently unable to use a weapon in which you are skilled, such as wielding a two handed weapon with one hand you must either immediately drop the weapon or take any damage that hits your weapon as if you had been hit.</p>
<p>Swinging your weapon</p>
<p>The NERO combat system is an honor system. Each player trusts that the person whom he is hitting is correctly counting his or her hits. “But I’m an evil thief.” You still have to count your hits. The NERO combat system relies on all players being honest in real life even if their character is a nefarious liar. Remember, even the NPCs are there to have fun, albeit by dying in a good clean fight. </p>
<p>NERO is a fantasy game with a fantasy combat style. The normal rules of armed combat don’t apply as they are geared toward doing all the things we strive to prevent, i.e. injure your opponent. So because of this some compromises must be made in realism.</p>
<p>Baseball Swing:</p>
<p>One thing you must remember: you are only trying to make contact, not hit a home run. Do not reach back, wind up, and take a huge swing at your opponent. It is usually not necessary to hit hard at all. When fighting an unarmored and unarmed opponent, an easy tap will do. You only need to apply enough pressure to make sure your opponent is aware of the attack.</p>
<p>For example, hitting an armored opponent from behind by surprise might require more vigor than a standard tap. And if it seems that your opponent is not taking his or</p>
<p>her hits, it might be because the hits are not being felt under all that armor. You should mention to your opponent when you think you got a hit in, and all players should call hits whenever possible.</p>
<p>Machine Gunning</p>
<p>If you are swinging so fast that you cannot announce the damage fast enough to keep up with the swings, then you are “Drum Rolling” or “Machine Gunning” and your opponent should count all of that as one or maybe two hits.</p>
<p>A good rule of thumb is to have your swing progress between 45 and 90 degrees. Most importantly swings must be controlled and must not hit too hard.</p>
<p>Shields</p>
<p>Shields cannot be used as offensive weapons. Shields are strictly for defense.</p>
<p>Shields do not protect the owner from any kind of trap other than a weapon trap, which uses a weapon blade or missile weapon to deliver its damage.</p>
<p>Shield Bashing</p>
<p>Shield Bashing is the intentional use of a shield to gain physical out-of-game advantage over an opponent. Shield Bashing is a serious a violation of NERO safety rules—it is similar to Charging. The potential for injury is great. Excessive use of Shield Bashing will result in warnings and possible loss of the Shield skill. </p>
<p>Shields cannot be used with two handed weapons. You may not wield a weapon with the hand or arm holding the shield. Also your shield arm may not have any other items or weapons attached to it. Tucking a dagger behind your shield arm would negate your ability to use the shield.</p>
<p>Spell Grounding</p>
<p>Any item you throw, toss, or let go of is still considered to be in your possession until it lands and comes to a complete rest. Any attack that hit such an item before it lands and comes to rest will affect its possessor.</p>
<p>If the attack targets the thrown/dropped item directly, such as Shatter or Destroy, the item is still affected.</p>
<p>Bucklers</p>
<p>A “buckler” shield (a small shield that is strapped onto the arm) must still follow all shield rules. In other words, you cannot have a buckler on your left arm and still hold anything in your left hand.</p>
<p>Turtling</p>
<p>“Turtling” or hiding behind an impenetrable shield (with little more than your head showing) is not allowed! Anyone using a shield in such a manner could be subject to warnings from the marshals and if necessary, loss of the shield skill. Shields in our game are not all that realistic, and as such you are artificially limited in what you can do with them.</p>
<p>In real life you could overbear someone who was hiding behind a shield, but such contact is not allowed in our game. If you are short and using a maximum sized shield that prevents any legal targets from showing then you are Turtling.</p>
<p>Delivery Methods</p>
<p>There are a few different ways for damage or effects to be dealt in the game. The following are methods in the game to use effects or deal/cure damage: Packet, Weapon, Ingested, Contact, Touch, Area of Effect, and Vengeance.</p>
<p>Contact</p>
<p>Contacts are effects delivered instantly through touch. With contact effects you can call defenses.</p>
<p>Ingested</p>
<p>These effects must be ingested to gain the effect. Ingested effects bypass protectives like Shield Magic and Poison Shield.</p>
<p>Packet</p>
<p>All packet-delivered attacks are effective on contact with the target or any of the target’s immediate possessions, such as a shield or cloak. Arrows are not considered packet attacks.</p>
<p>Packet attacks include spells, gas globes, and certain monster abilities. Note that unlike the weapon rules, a packet attack will count if it hits “non-legal targets” such as the head or groin but that’s not to say you should aim at these illegal targets.</p>
<p>Touch</p>
<p>An effect delivered though touch does not effect any defenses, instead the target of the touch, can choose to “accept” the effect or state “I do not accept”, at the time the effect is delivered.</p>
<p>“Touch-Casting” on page 46 for more information.</p>
<p>Vengeance</p>
<p>A vengeance is an effect that has a unique delivery method. It automatically targets whoever deals a killing blow to the owner of the Vengeance for more information on vengeance see the NERO Formal Magic Rules.</p>
<p>Weapon Blow</p>
<p>Weapon blows are dealt with nero safe hand held boffers, and thrown boffers. Arrows are also considered weapon blows even though they are phys-repped by yellow packets.</p>
<p>Effects Types</p>
<p>In addition to delivery methods, there are also effect types which change what protects you from the damage or effect. Once you take the effect, it is the same no matter what the effect type. </p>
<p>Arcane: Effects delivered this way are created from raw magical energies. They are not blocked by regular spell defenses. The same casting rules apply as spells except you do not need the ability to speak.</p>
<p>Magic: Magic Deliverance is a non verbal way of casting spells. The same casting rules apply as spells except you do not need the ability to speak.</p>
<p>Elemental: Effects and damage delivered elementally are created from elemental energy rather than a spell, so must be blocked by an elemental shield. Elemental effects can be removed by dispel magic. </p>
<p>Physical: Physical attacks represent an actual physical force such as a glob of ooze to form a Physical Web, a big rock to form a Physical Stone Bolt, or a burst of wind to cause a Physical Repel. </p>
<p>Poison: Effects delivered as poison are stopped by Poison shields. They represent a monster with poisoned claws, fangs, or spittle.</p>
<p>Spell: Effects delivered as spell are blocked by a Shield Magic.</p>
<p></p>
<p>Calling Weapon Damage</p>
<p>When you swing a weapon in NERO, you must call out a verbal that indicates the attributes of the attack. The verbal will have up to four parts, with the first two always present and the latter two only used in special circumstances. The parts are, in order,</p>
<p><damage amount> <weapon type> <damage type> <effect>.</p>
<p>When in combat with the same opponent, there is no need to continue calling your damage beyond the first or second swing. Weapon verbals are out of game and can thus be made while under the effects of a Silence or Gypsy Curse, however anyone who hears them will know what it is.</p>
<p>Damage Amount</p>
<p>The damage you are dealing with each swing as a numerical value.</p>
<p>Weapon Type</p>
<p>A Weapon’s Type determines the nature of the weapon. There are four weapon types: Normal, Silver, Magic, and Massive.</p>
<p>Damage Type</p>
<p>Some creatures may take an increased or decreased amount of damage from certain damage types. The valid Damage Types are variable and up to the local plot team or as</p>
<p>granted by effects within these rules so long as the call does not duplicate a game effect. </p>
<p>The most common damage types are the thirteen core elements (fire, water, order, chaos, etc.) and the Effect Types listed above. The only Effect Types which may not be used as a Damage Type are "Magic" or "Spell". To Specify a Carrier Attack as a magical effect you must use the "Arcane" Effect Type.</p>
<p></p>
<p>Calling Hits</p>
<p>Calling hits against yourself is strongly encouraged by role-playing being struck. Acknowledging which hits you are accepting and which ones you feel you blocked will help the flow of combat.</p>
<p>Throwing/Tossing Items</p>
<p>You cannot throw any weapon, shield, etc., that is not NERO approved for throwing. Basically, if a local safety marshal has approved the weapon to be thrown (thrown weapons, javelins, etc.), you can throw it, otherwise you cannot.</p>
<p>In addition, you cannot use the “toss and grab ” method on any item to avoid the effects of a spell. If you toss an item and grab it before it lands on the ground, the item is still under your control, and is still considered in your possession.</p>
<p>For the purposes of spells that target the item itself (such as Shatter), an item is still considered under a player’s control until it comes to a complete rest on the ground out of the player’s grasp</p>
<p>Special Abilities </p>
<p>There are many creatures in the NERO world that have special abilities or powers. The effects of these are described below.</p>
<p>Some monsters are represented by multiple NPCs. These are either organisms that can divide into many segments, or are larger than man sized. In some cases, these creatures will be affected differently by battle magic spells. The spell may only affect one of the creature’s segments. A spell such as Pin may only affect the segment it hits, allowing the creature to pivot around the affected part. Once again, the monster should have documentation describing any special allowances it may have. </p>
<p>Occasionally, a monster’s abilities may change from event to event or even during an event! This can be the result of many things, from mutation to strange magics to a new tribe moving into the area.</p>
<p>Packet Attacks</p>
<p>Packet attacks follow the same basic rules as any other skill involving a packet, the user must say out loud in a clear voice the “verbal” then they may throw the packet. All attacks that duplicate a spell or effect that contains a number must include that number at the end of the verbal (ex. A monster hurls a Physical Cause Wounds packet, the correct verbal before throwing is “Physical Cause Wounds 10”).</p>
<p>These attacks represent monsters’ abilities to generate ranged attacks such as poisonous spittle, breathing fire, or charming you with their will. There are only 5 different delivery types for packet attacks; Arcane, Elemental, Magic, Physical, and Poison. The delivery type determines what delivery type specific spell defense(s) can be used. The effect itself would be cured by whatever is listed in its description, by any other effect whose description allows it to cure the effect (ex. Awaken’s description specifically allows it to cure Sleep), or from the list below. Limitations on curing in the description still also apply if the description says the effect can only be cured by specific effects or cannot be cured by specific effects. None of these attacks may use orange or yellow packets as orange packets as orange are used to physically represent gas globes and yellow packets are arrows. A creature must have use of its arms and may not be holding any other in-game object in its hand in order to use a packet attack, even if it is touch-casting the ability. This includes claws, which must be retracted in order to use any packet-based ability.</p>
<p>Base Claws/Body Weaponry</p>
<p>Monsters with this ability can strike with large claws or fists. The phys-reps will always be covered in red duct or kite tape; however, you cannot tell the difference between claws and real weapons unless you can actually see the red tape. The claws cannot be Fumbled, Shattered, or Destroyed. The NPC cannot call a Hold to pull out claws. Consider the claws retractable. </p>
<p>Control Undead</p>
<p>Some undead creatures can control other less powerful undead in the area, making them do whatever they want. This effect is stronger than Calm/Calm Animal Charm / Charm Animal, Shun/Shun Animal, or Fear. The most recent Control Undead, Vampire Charm or Enslavement effect will take precedent if there is a conflict See “Table 5-6.”</p>
<p>Curse of Transformation</p>
<p>Some monsters (notably werewolves and vampires) have the ability to curse their victims so that they will turn into versions of themselves under appropriate  circumstances. Werewolves can turn their victims into werewolves who will then change on the next full moon (and every full moon thereafter). Vampires can turn their victims into lesser vampires. These curses cannot be resisted as per spirit targeting formal rules. The character is usually not dead when they are afflicted with a Curse of Transformation. Once Cursed, when the appropriate circumstances are met,the character will transform into a lesser form of the master who Cursed the character. All life and death rules are still in effect - the player will enter her death count when she is reduced to -1 body  points, she will have 5 minutes to receive a Life spell,  the Life spell may or may not cure the “Curse”. You will always receive a card that states the additional abilities of your curse that you will then carry with your character card at all times. </p>
<p>Drain</p>
<p>This attack causes the victim to be unable to use any in game skills and may not run. Drain will last for 5 minutes or it can be removed with a Life or Remove Drain spell. This effect is not affected by a Dispel Magic.</p>
<p>Drain Life</p>
<p>This attack is the same as Drain but lasts until a Life spell is given or the victim resurrects. It cannot be removed by a Dispel Magic or Remove Drain.</p>
<p>Fear</p>
<p>Some creatures have the ability to invoke a magical fear. The racial ability Resist Charm can be used as a defense against this ability and an Awaken or Remove Fear spell will free someone who is Feared. The feared victim must attempt to break Line of Sight and cannot attack the creature they fear in any way. If breaking Line of Sight is impossible, the victim will stay as far from the attacker as possible. Even if Line of Sight is broken the effect lasts for five minutes or until the creature is dead.</p>
<p>For example, Drina gets Feared by a vampire. She runs screaming around a corner and ten seconds later (as per the “Line of Sight” rule), she feels calm again. If the vampire then appears around the corner, Drina must run screaming again, as the five minutes are not up. The victim cannot cast an Aw aken spell on himself or herself until out of Line of Sight.</p>
<p>Infection</p>
<p>Some creatures have the ability to infect helpless victims with material that will turn the person into a version of the creature. Unlike a werewolf or vampire curse, this is only a physical transformation of the victim’s body. Players will be told of specific triggers if necessary. Victims will lose all memory of their former lives, and the player must follow the commands they are given by the Monster Master until the character is slain. </p>
<p>The character may then be killed and then given a Life spell and be cured of the infection. If the player dies the spirit may then proceed to the Healers’ Guild to be resurrected as normal. Infection is done just as a Killing Blow, with a count of “I infect you 1, I infect you 2, I infect you 3.”</p>
<p>Lesser</p>
<p>Some NPCs will be able to deliver “Lesser” versions of attacks. The word “Lesser” is used as the first word in a verbal and indicates that the following effect will only last 10 seconds if it normally has a duration greater than instant. If the duration is instant then Lesser is meaningless. For example, a ghoul calls “Lesser Poison</p>
<p>Paralyze” and throws a packet at Steve. Steve, lacking any defense to prevent it taking effect, is now Paralyzed for 10 seconds.</p>
<p>Massive</p>
<p>Some creatures can use the Massive weapon type. Massive damage cannot be blocked by weapons or shields. If a blow delivering this type of damage strikes a weapon or shield, the bearer of the item struck takes the damage delivered, as well as any carrier effects (when appropriate, i.e. once Body Points are damaged). The skills Parry and Dodge will work as normal against this type of damage, as will all applicable protective spells such as Magic Armor or Displacement.</p>
<p>Physical Strike</p>
<p>This ability functions as Spell Strike but is stopped by a Magic Armor or Parry instead of a Shield Magic or Reflect Magic. The proper verbal is “Physical Strike <Effect>”.</p>
<p>Spell Strike</p>
<p>A few powerful magical creatures have the ability to generate spell effects in their weapons. The spell effects are just as the spell, except that they are delivered with a weapon strike instead of a spell packet. As with any weapon strike, all weapon safety rules must be followed. The spells are still subject to spell defenses as a normal spell. This ability does not require Body contact. When this power is used, the player will call “Spell Strike <Effect>” and will deliver a NERO-safe hit. The skill can still be used even when silenced, but the effect is recognizable to all who hear it. </p>
<p>The spell portion of a Spellstrike is only stopped by defenses that would stop the attack if it were delivered by packet. Therefore, Magic Arm or, although it stops “the next single strike by a NERO Safe weapon” , does not stop a Spellstrike. Since a Spellstrike is weapon-delivered, the user must have the in-game skill to wield the weapon in order to use the Spellstrike.</p>
<p> For example, if the user is under a game effect that prohibits the use of in-game skills, then they cannot use a Spellstrike. Also, if the Spellstrike is delivered by a non-ranged weapon, then the attack will not affect creatures under the effects of a Sanctuary and Desecrate, as appropriate.</p>
<p>Superhuman Strength</p>
<p>Any creature with superhuman strength can do more damage with any particular weapon than can a normal human. This bonus damage is split in half if the creature is fighting with any weapon other than a two handed one. Note, that creatures with Superhuman Strength can gain only limited advantage from either an Endow or a Delayed Endow. (See the spell descriptions for more details).</p>
<p>Vampire Charm</p>
<p>Vampires can charm a person if they can maintain eye contact for 10 seconds. More powerful Vampires can deliver packet attack Vampire Charms as well. This power does not require body contact. If you are charmed by a Vampire, then you must obey all commands the Vampire gives you. These commands are absolute and are much more powerful than a Charm spell; if a vampire tells you to commit suicide, you will do so unquestioningly. Spell defenses appropriate to the delivery type can be used to stop a packet-delivered Vampire Charm. The racial skill Resist Charm will protect the character from this effect. The effect lasts five minutes. This effect is stronger than Calm/ Calm Animal Charm /Charm Animal, Shun/ Shun Animal, or Fear. The most recent Control Undead, Vampire Charm or Enslavement effect will take precedent if there is a conflict. See Table 5-6 on page 64.</p>
<p>Special Defenses and Vulnerabilities</p>
<p>Some creatures have special defenses that protect the creature from attacks, or weaknesses that make it more vulnerable to certain effects.</p>
<p>Damage Cap <X></p>
<p>This ability allows the creature to limit the amount of damage taken from weapon attacks that would otherwise affect it. The call for a Damage Cap is “Cap x”, where “x” is the amount of damage the creature is taking. Damage Cap never affects spells, slays or assassinates.</p>
<p>Double from <damage type or effect></p>
<p>Some creatures take double damage from certain effects or spells and it is always written on their character documentation. All damage of that type that would normally affect the creature is doubled by the recipient when they are hit.</p>
<p><Effect> Shield</p>
<p>This monster ability acts just like Resist except that it must be used on the first applicable attack that would affect the creature. This means they can only be used after Spell Defenses like Shield Magic and Reflect Magic.</p>
<p>Focus</p>
<p>Creatures with this ability are not subject to Disruption for one or more of their attacks.</p>
<p>Gaseous Form</p>
<p>Creatures that are forced into gaseous form when they are killed drop their possessions. Creatures which voluntarily turn into gaseous form while still “alive” can bring their possessions with them. Creatures that turn gaseous will drop any other creatures being carried at that time. While they are in this form they are immune to all attacks except Ar cane Solidify. They may only move at a normal walking rate. They cannot speak or move objects. Creatures in Gaseous Form still appear as they normally do. Voluntarily Turning gaseous or solidifying is a three counted action.</p>
<p>Harmed by <damage type or effect></p>
<p>Some creatures take damage when struck by certain spells or effects.</p>
<p>Heal by <damage type or effect></p>
<p>Some creatures are healed by certain types of spells or effects (For example, air, earth, fire, water, or all of them). Creatures with this ability cannot be healed by weapon attacks (except Spellstrikes), but can be healed by packet attacks. Creatures healed by a damage type or effect are immune to weapon attacks (except Spellstrikes) using those types or effects.</p>
<p>Immune to/from <damage type or effect></p>
<p>Many creatures have immunities to some spells or effects. Creatures must call “No effect” when using this ability.</p>
<p>Immune to <Type> Weapons</p>
<p>Several types of creatures require special weapons (for example, silver or magic) to damage them. Normal weapons will do no damage, but the special weapon will do full damage. These creatures will tell you “ No effect” if your damage is not affecting them.</p>
<p>Mind Abilities</p>
<p>Some creatures can perform mental abilities such as “mind melds.” These abilities are all completely role-playing in nature. Generally speaking, a creature with this ability can instill or remove roleplaying insanity or otherwise “cure” mental damage. This ability can not be used to tell if another player is telling the truth or to counteract forget-it poisons or otherwise get around any NERO rule. A player always has the right to refuse to role-play any of these skills and can at any time decide to “break off” the contact or be cured. In order to use this role-playing skill, the players must be touching each other and be concentrating completely by either staring in each other’s eyes or having their eyes closed. You cannot perform any in-game skills while role-playing this.</p>
<p>Natural Armor</p>
<p>Some monsters have a skin that acts like armor. It can be refit in sixty seconds. It cannot be Shattered or Destroyed in any way nor can it be salvaged after the creature is killed.</p>
<p>No Metabolism</p>
<p>Some monsters lack a metabolism. The standard definition is as follows: Imm une to Death, Disease, Drain, Drain Life, First Aid, Life, Nausea, Paralyze, Poisons, Sleep, Taint Blood, Waylay, Wither Limb.</p>
<p>Non-Corporeal Form</p>
<p>Some monsters are non-corporeal, having no physical form but made mainly of magic or energy. While they are in this form they are immune to normal weapons, and are immune to Pin, Bind, Web, and Confine.</p>
<p>Phase</p>
<p>Some creatures can become non-corporeal for an instant, avoiding an attack as the Dodge skill, and announcing “Phase.” Unlike Dodge, Phase can be used even if the creature is completely immobilized, such as if in a Confine or Paralyze.</p>
<p>Reduced Damage</p>
<p>Some monsters take less than normal damage from certain attacks. The NPC must call “reduced” when using this ability.</p>
<p>Regeneration</p>
<p>Some creatures can regenerate Body Points by spending time to regenerate, much like refitting armor. The time it takes to regenerate is most often one minute but this may vary from creature to creature. If the regeneration time is interrupted by a weapon blow or a spell that affects the creature, the process must begin again. If the process is completed, then the creature regains all lost Body Points. Some creature can do this at zero body, in this case nothing interrupts the regeneration except a killing blow that affects the creature.</p>
<p>Renew <option></p>
<p>This ability allows a creature to renew one or more abilities or skills that have limited uses by fulfilling some condition defined by that creature’s abilities. The most common condition is to take a minute to reset the ability in a manner similar to resetting armor, where any interruption prevents the abilities from returning. Some creatures may also renew skills when entering an area or even if they use another power like Revive. The options for this ability are a “single skill” chosen by the target, a “<specific skill>” chosen by the creature using the Renew ability, or “all” skills and abilities.</p>
<p>Resist <effect></p>
<p>This ability is similar to an Immunity except that it is for a limited number of times per day. Unlike an <Effect> Shield, the creature with this skill can decide when to use it.</p>
<p>Return <type></p>
<p>A creature with the ability to Return <type> will cause a specific type of effect directed at it to be returned to its point of origin. It functions like the Resist skill in that the creature can choose when to use a Return. Returned effects are instantly restored to the character’s skill set, although the character will not be able to use the skill again until they Meditate for 1 minute. Return can only be used on daily or times ever effects such as spells, Cr itical Slays, Assassinates, etc. Return can be used against stored spells/effects from formal magic items and/or production items, and in this case the Return acts like a Resist in that it prevents the effect and the charge is lost. The creature card will specify the types of Return available to that creature in a similar way to Resists.</p>
<p>Revive</p>
<p>A creature with this skill can rise back up after five minutes of semi-death. Instead of dissipating and going to resurrect, the creature rises with full Body Points. The creature will either have a limited number of uses of this ability or there will be some special method of preventing the creature from reviving; for example, some creatures can be prevented from using this skill by applying a Killing Blow with a silver blade.</p>
<p>Rift /Gate</p>
<p>Some creatures can open a rift to another plane to allow for entrance or exit or open a Gate to another place. This is a three counted action unless a fully represented gate prop is used. Some of these creatures also have the power to abduct others and force them to rift or gate out against their will. Rip from Pin/ Bind/Web/Confine</p>
<p>Some creatures can rip free from binding spells. This is a three-count action with the phrase “I rip free one, I rip free two, I rip free three.” While the creature is doing the three-count, it is vulnerable to attack and a Killing Blow begun prior to the Ripping. While ripping free, the creature may not use any skill requiring movement, such as Dodge. A creature with the skill Rip from Pin/Bind/Web/Confine can only use this skill upon itself, never upon others. </p>
<p>Solidify</p>
<p>This skill forces a gaseous form to become immediately solid. It is packet delivered with the verbal “<delivery type> Solidify.” Note that the creature may still turn gaseous again. </p>
<p>Suicide Ability</p>
<p>Some creatures have the ability to destroy themselves if they are captured. This ability may be the equivalent of a Killing Blow or it may cause the creature to instantly dissipate and seek resurrection. </p>
<p>Threshold</p>
<p>This allows the creature to take only a single point of damage from any blow equal to or below its Threshold. The creature must call “Threshold” whenever a blow is landed. However, don’t expect to hear the call for every blow. Once you’ve acknowledged the call, the creature is under no obligation to continuously call “Threshold”, unless new players join the fight. These fights sometimes last a long time, so common courtesy on both sides is highly recommended. If you can exceed the limit of the hide, then the creature will take full damage from your blow. A Killing Blow can always go through a Threshold. Spell Defenses and suits of armor are affected by all blows, even if the creature wouldn’t normally be affected.</p>
<p>So You Want to Be a Thief?</p>
<p>Stealing an Item</p>
<p>“Stealing an item” refers only to the in-game stealing of in-game items. You must be very careful when attempting to steal anything in-game. You are never allowed to harm or destroy real property (using in-game spells to Shatter or Destroy is fine because you aren’t harming or damaging real property) in order to steal something. You may not pickpocket characters in NERO.</p>
<p>There are special rules for each type of in-game item and you are required to know them. If you are caught stealing something incorrectly, then you are cheating—and ignorance of the rules is no excuse!</p>
<p>Game Money, Magic Items, and Jewelry</p>
<p>You are always allowed to take whatever game money you can find in-game. When taking jewelry or an item, always check to make sure there is an item tag with the item phys-rep. If there is an item tag, then the item tag is now yours. You must temporarily take the item’s phys-rep, which should be promptly given to a rules marshal as soon as you are in a safe area, (before the end of the event), so the phys-rep can be returned to its owner. If there is no tag, the item does not represent an in-game item and cannot be taken because it is merely a costume piece.</p>
<p>If you have a magic weapon or item phys-rep stolen, you must immediately find one of the Rules Marshals for that chapter and turn over the magic item tag. You can find a Rules Marshal out-of-game.</p>
<p>If you have a piece of jewelry or other game item that you wish to make into a stealable item, you must obtain an item tag for that item. You can do this at logistics at any NERO event. The item will be evaluated to figure out its monetary value. You will then be required to pay the in-game amount that the item is worth.</p>
<p>Weapons</p>
<p>You must actually take the weapon you are stealing.</p>
<p>Once you have stolen a weapon, you should then head immediately to the designated area for stolen weapons (usually the NPC camp or an NPC Weaponsmith shop). You cannot actually keep that particular weapon phys-rep since it is the personal property of the player from whom you stole it, but the marshal in charge will give you the tag from that weapon which you can then attach to your own weapon phys-rep or attempt to sell in-game.</p>
<p>If your weapon is stolen, you should head to the designated area. That is why it is so important for you to write your name on your weapon! (In some chapters, you do not steal the weapon, but only the tag.)</p>
<p>Some monsters will have weapons that are stealable. However, for logistical reasons, these monsters will simply hand you a tag instead of the actual weapon.</p>
<p>Other in-game items</p>
<p>NERO often provides props such as maps, notes, books, and other informational items. If you find these in a module or on an NPC, you should ask a Rules Marshal to see if you need to return the props to NPC camp or if you can keep them. If you steal them from another player, you should have a Rules Marshal contact the person you stole them from out-of-game and make sure that they were stealable.</p>
<p>Searching a Person</p>
<p>If you waylay, kill, or control a person or monster through a spell, you may search that being. Simply say “I search you.” All game items must be turned over at that point. Note that it is impossible to completely hide something on your body. If you are searched, you cannot claim that something was “really, really hidden.” If you are searched, you also have the option of saying, “Go ahead and describe your search and I will tell you the results step by step.” This is not only to help you to hide items, but it also takes up the time that the search should take. You must really have the item hidden where you say it is. In other words, you can’t say “I’m pretending to have a secret compartment in my shoe, and he didn’t search for secret compartments!”</p>
<p>If someone steals your magic item, do not give them the tag that describes your magic item. Immediately go to a Rules Marshal and turn over the tag. It is up to the person who stole the item to find out what the item is and how it works. This applies to magical weapons as well.</p>
<p>Searching a Cabin</p>
<p>In order to search a cabin, you MUST have a marshal present. We cannot overemphasize this point! If you enter a cabin without a marshal, you are really breaking and entering and NERO may be forced to bring legal action against you!</p>
<p>The marshal does not have to actually be right next to you (after all, how can you sneak with someone else tagging along beside?), but the marshal must be within sight somewhere.</p>
<p>Once you have managed to successfully open the door, the marshal will then check the marshal’s notes that will be affixed to the inside of the door. These notes will list any magic spells that may be active in, or on, the cabin, which character cast these spells upon the cabin, who is invested in any Circles of Power that are in the cabin, who is invested in the cabin’s Ward (if one is present), and any other things that the local chapter requested be placed on the Marshal’s Notes. </p>
<p>You must actually search the cabin yourself. The marshal will not simply look at the notes and go and retrieve items for you. Do not take any items marked “personal” or any items stored under a bed. In-game items may not be put under a bed. When you leave the cabin, you must show all items you have taken to the marshal. Only game items can be stolen! The marshal will return non-stealable items. The marshal is also there to make sure that you properly disarm any traps that may be on the door or window. Destroying property such as window screens or door hinges is not allowed. </p>
<p>Remember you can search anywhere in a cabin except for bags marked personal or behind dividing curtains or under beds. However, not everything in gameplay is stealable, so always talk to a Rules Marshal if you have any questions or concerns.</p>
<p>Securing your Cabin</p>
<p>Tyrra can be an unsafe place, so it’s always a wise idea to guard your valuables. There may be places in-game where you can buy or rent a lock for your cabin. Some of these places will also install it for you for a small fee. Of course, these locks can be picked by a good thief, but at least it will slow the rascal down. You can also buy or make traps for your cabin. Each trap must be accompanied by the trap’s item tag see Traps & Locks below.</p>
<p>It is a smart idea to take your personal items and put them under your bed. Any items placed under the bed are considered to be out of play, so don’t cheat and put game items there. If you like, put a dividing curtain up in your cabin, and place all the beds and your personal items behind it. Put any game items in front of the divider. </p>
<p>If you are sleeping in-game during the night, make sure that your bed is in front of any dividing curtain or barrier you have put up. </p>
<p>Any special security precautions you take must be entered on the marshal’s notes sheet in the holder on your cabin door. Make any appropriate entries there, with the spell labels and/or trap cards necessary. That way anyone marshaling a thief through your cabin can dole out any damage that the villain may take. If no precautions have been entered on the marshal’s notes, then there is nothing protecting the cabin in-game!</p>
<p>Anyone who does not reside in a particular cabin caught reading the marshal’s notes will be subject to disciplinary action. These notes are for marshals only, and only when marshaling a thief into the cabin.</p>
<p>Traps & Locks</p>
<p>In order to make a trap, you must have the skill Create Traps. This skill works on the Production system as described in the chapter “Physical Representations” on page 105. All trap designs must be checked and approved by a Rules Marshal from the chapter where the trap will be used. The trap must be approved at every event, regardlessof whether it has been approved in the past. All traps must make a noise or flash a light or otherwise be constructed so that it is obvious when the trap has been set off. A trigger must be physically attached or cenected to a trap.</p>
<p>Traps are never considered ”NERO-safe” weapons and cannot be thrown or used in battle as a weapon. Doors may only be secured through in-game means such as in-game locks or a Ward spell. The use of out-of-game locks, barricading a door closed with other objects or attempting to hold it closed against an intruder is not permitted.</p>
<p>Trap Types</p>
<p>There are 7 different types of traps each with different building parameters.</p>
<p>Weapon Traps</p>
<p>A weapon trap is a trap which contains a weapon on a spring mounted mechanism. These traps cost 1 Production Level per 2 points of damage with a minimum damage of 2 and a maximum damage of 40. Weapon traps may be reset by anyone with the Disarm /Arm Tr aps skill without paying the cost to rebuild them. These traps must be mounted to a door, wall or inside a large chest to be effective. If not mounted to a heavy, stable object of this sort, they cannot be set with enough force to be effective. You cannot attach these traps to a body.</p>
<p>The mounted weapon must be any standard NERO-safe boffer weapon. This is the only trap that can be blocked, Parried, Dodged or stopped by the Magic Arm or spell.</p>
<p>Massive Mechanical Traps</p>
<p>Massive mechanical traps represent collapsing ceilings, rockfalls, giant scythes, and other such contraptions. They are completely immovable. They have a minimum size of 3” by 3” by 3”. Anyone struck by any part of the trap when it goes off takes the full damage of the trap. Massive mechanical traps must be rebuilt after they are set off; they cannot be reset. </p>
<p>These cost 1 Production Level per 4 points of damage with a minimum damage of 16 and a maximum damage of 80. Massive mechanical traps are usually  represented with pillows, plastic trash bags filled with newspapers, and other soft items. Whoever is touched by the phys-rep will take the complete damage from the trap.</p>
<p>Fire / Acid Traps</p>
<p>A fire or acid trap represents a trap which sprays a burning or caustic liquid in a 5 foot radius measured from the center of the trap phys-rep. Anyone inside this radius when it detonates takes the full damage of the trap plus the additional effects listed below. </p>
<p>In addition to a trigger and detonating mechanism, there must also be a physical representation for the oil / acid “container.” The required size of this container is 216 cubic inches. The detonation mechanism must be attached to the container. The radius effect is measured out from this container. </p>
<p>The damage from fire traps can be negated by Cloak vs Fire or Guardian of the Four (Fire.)</p>
<p>These cost 1 Production Level per 3 points of damage with a minimum damage of 12 and a maximum damage of 60. This trap is destroyed when it detonates.</p>
<p>Explosive Traps</p>
<p>Explosive traps are very similar to Fire/Acid Traps except that the container represents the explosive. These traps have a 5’ radius. All destructible items in the area of effect are destroyed. Armor will provide its numerical protection against the damage caused by the blast and then be destroyed. Sealed containers will not protect items from explosions. All in-game items except un-shatterable items will be destroyed by an explosive trap. Items within an indestructible sealed container will not be affected if they are in the radius of an explosive trap, unless the trap is inside that container or the container is open. Defenses such as Cloak or Bane versus Shatter or Destroy have no effect against an explosive trap.</p>
<p>Explosive traps, like Fire/Acid traps and Gas traps, must have a “container.” This container is always 216 cubic inches, regardless of the trap’s effects.</p>
<p>To make these traps costs 1 Production Level per 2 points of damage with a minimum damage of 30, and a maximum damage of 60. This trap is destroyed when it detonates.</p>
<p>Gas Traps</p>
<p>The Production Level cost for creating a gas trap is equal to the highest Production Level gas the trap is designed to hold. The trap builder must also include a dose of the gas poison in the trap itself.</p>
<p>A gas trap is rated at the Production Level used to make it. To make a gas trap with a Paralyze gas within will cost 9 Production Levels for the trap (and 9 production Levels for the gas, which must be supplied separately).</p>
<p>Remember that the trap must contain both a trap card and the gas poison tag. Gas which is contained in a Gas trap cannot be removed, reused, or “salvaged,” under any circumstances.</p>
<p>Multiple Cause Damage gases can be placed into a single gas trap up to the limit of the level of the trap but no other gases can be “stacked” to increase their damage potential or mix their effects. </p>
<p>These traps have a 5’ radius. Anyone inside this area when the trap goes off will be affected as if they had been struck by a gas poison of the same name. The effects of any gas trap, even traps with multiple gases, will be blocked by a Poison Shield or the skill Resist Poison. If two or more traps have the same trigger, then they are all set off together and one Poison Shield or Resist Poison will block them all.</p>
<p>Gas traps, like Fire/Acid traps and Explosive traps, must have a “container.” This container is always 216 cubic inches, regardless of the trap’s effects. Gas trap mechanisms that go off are reusable though the gas inside will have to be replaced.</p>
<p>Alarms and Noise Makers</p>
<p>These are traps that do no damage but set off loud alarms and other noises. They cost 1 Production Level each to make. Alarms and Noise Makers do not have a minimum container size. They are as large, or as small, as they must be to make a noise. When this type of trap is tripped, it must make its own noise. Although it takes a person with Disarm Tr aps to disarm an Alarm or Noise Maker trap, once it has been set off anyone can attempt to muffle the trap’s sound by throwing blankets over the trap, or by using some other method.</p>
<p>Trap Mechanics</p>
<p>Setting Traps</p>
<p>Setting a trap takes the real setting time of the trigger followed by 60 seconds of counting while both hands remain on the trapped item. Both weapon traps and massive mechanical traps must be mounted on large or heavy objects to be properly set.</p>
<p>Backfire</p>
<p>If either hand is removed from the trap, or the person setting the trap is struck by a physical blow or packet attack, then the trap backfires on the setter. The backfire will hit only the person setting the trap; there is no radius effect.</p>
<p>Setting off a Trap</p>
<p>Traps can be set off in 3 ways: by being moved, being destroyed, or their trigger being sprung. The trap must be armed to be set off.</p>
<p>Being Moved</p>
<p>After a trap has been set, it cannot be moved more than five feet without automatically setting it off, even if the person moving it has a Disarm Tr aps skill. In the case of weapon traps, they will automatically hit the person carrying the trap.</p>
<p>Destroyed</p>
<p>An armed trap will be set off (then destroyed) if affected by a Shatter or Destroy effect. This includes traps and other game effects that duplicate Shatter and Destroy. Traps that are not armed will not be set off in this manner (although they will still be destroyed).</p>
<p>Trap Triggers</p>
<p>All traps must have a real, physical trigger. Setting off the trap must produce a noise or light that is detectable by an impartial observer. It must always be possible to see how to disarm a trap, although it may require light and a small mirror. To be used, a trap must be approved by a Marshal.</p>
<p>A simple trap trigger can be made out of a clothespin (the kind with a spring in it), two tacks, some string or thread, two pieces of wire and a small piece of cardboard. Attach the wire to the tacks just below the heads of the tacks.</p>
<p>Now pull the clothespin apart and place the parts outside-down on a table. Push a tack through each half of the clothespin so that the two tack heads will contact each other when the clothespin closes. Reassemble the clothespin.</p>
<p>Punch a small hole in the piece of cardboard and tie one end of the piece of thread to the cardboard. The cardboard can now be placed between the jaws of the clothespin to keep the tacks from conducting electricity.</p>
<p>The other end of the string can be tied across a doorway or path so that when someone hits it with their leg it will pull out the cardboard and make a connection. This trigger can then be used to set off a buzzer or other device to indicate the trap has gone off. You can also deliberately set off a trap like a claymore mine if you use a pull cord.</p>
<p>Dealing Damage</p>
<p>Traps that have an area effect have their effect area measured from the center of the trap phys-rep. If there is a large, trapped box with a 10 foot tripwire attached and a player sets the trap off at the end of that tripwire they are not affected by the trap since the phys-rep (the center of the trap radius) would be 10 feet away. It is not measured from the tripwire/snapper/etc, but from the rep for the trap itself. This will allow you to have a 50ft pull cord on a trap box in the field and use it like a claymore mine since the effect goes off from the box/rep/trigger and not from the cord.</p>
<p>Disarming Traps</p>
<p>Traps may be disarmed by any method that does not permanently destroy the trap. For example, popping a battery clip off would represent disarming a spring. </p>
<p>Permanent damage is defined as any damage that cannot be fixed by the marshal within ten minutes with no tools.</p>
<p>If the trap was successfully disarmed, the gas trap may of course be reset, but in no case can the gas be taken from the trap.</p>
<p>Containers</p>
<p>Fire / Acid, Explosive and Gas traps must have a container representing their explosive or liquid contents. This container must be at least 216 cubic inches in size.</p>
<p>Picking Locks</p>
<p>Anyone wishing to put a lock on a box, chest, or door must use one of the NERO approved locks (for sale by various characters). These locks are simple and can be fairly easily picked using thieves’ tools. Generally speaking, if you wish to place a lock on your door and you can pick the lock yourself in the presence of a Marshal, then you will be allowed to use that lock. Combination locks are not allowed to be used by players (although they may be found in modules).</p>
<p>Marshals</p>
<p>Marshals are the referees and guides of NERO. They will be with you in modules and available for you at other times. If you have a question about rules or if you need someone to witness an action in order to make it official, you must see the appropriate marshal.</p>
<p>If there is a dispute over a rules interpretation by one or more players, then a Marshal should be consulted. If you are on a module, then your Module Marshal will be the arbiter. If you are on a full NERO event, then you will need to find a Full Marshal or one of the marshals on duty for the event.</p>
<p>If you wish to appeal a Marshal’s ruling, you can speak to an Adjudicator. When dealing with a NERO Marshal or other representative, you can help yourself and your case considerably by staying calm. Present your case and once the ruling is made, play along with it. Your marshal may be aware of something you have missed, or may be making a decision based on what was intended by the rule. If you feel the marshal’s judgment was incorrect, you can bring the ruling to adjudication later. Don’t dwell on it in the meantime or it will spoil your enjoyment of the rest of the game. You should also try not to nitpick details of a situation. You should understand and follow the intent of the rules. Play fair and be considerate of everyone’s enjoyment of the game. You will be taken more seriously and be respected by those who have to deal with you. Arguing the specific wording of a rule or taking advantage of a misprint can look like manipulation of the rules for your benefit and will not win you any friends in the long run.</p>
<p>Marshals are appointed positions only. Generally, marshals remain in game play as their characters but are able to step in and make judgments if needed. Anyone impersonating a marshal will be subject to immediate disciplinary action, as are marshals who attempt to marshal themselves or their friends in game play. </p>
<p>Marshals are never allowed to marshal themselves through an encounter, and a marshal should never marshal his or her adventuring group if at all possible. If a marshal appears biased, it ruins the credibility of the marshal to give fair judgments in future decisions.</p>
<p>Cheating and Metagaming</p>
<p>Players who are caught cheating or metagaming raise the risk of being suspended or kicked out of NERO. Remember, you do not have a right to play our game.</p>
<p>If you know of someone cheating, you should immediately report this to a marshal.</p>
<p>Metagaming is harder to call. It is difficult to keep from bragging about your adventures to people out-of-game. And sometimes people do not remember if they got information in-game or out-of-game. If you do not want people to act of information they have discovered out-of-game, the best solution is to never tell any secrets!</p>
<p>Peer pressure counts for a lot here. Don’t let your teammates cheat or metagame. Sooner or later, he or she will get caught and everyone will  assume that you are guilty as well.</p>
<p>This leads to a tender subject: Gossip about cheaters and metagamers. It is common for players to gripe about other players and call them cheaters or metagamers but the fact is that NERO is very proud of the fact that we have so few. Gossip can ruin our game. We all need to watch what we say about other players. Hearsay and innuendo have no place in NERO. If you think that someone is cheating or metagaming, don’t whine and complain to your friends about it- report it to a marshal! And if a marshal comes to you and asks about a possible cheating situation, please cooperate and don’t take it personally.</p>
<p>If someone makes an accusation against someone else ask, “How do you know that?” If they have firsthand knowledge, ask ”Why haven’t you reported that to a Marshal?” If they don’t have firsthand knowledge, refuse to listen to them.</p>
<p>Only by working together and trusting each other enough to give the benefit of the doubt can we keep this game running fairly for everyone. Your cooperation is crucial to make sure we have a fair, fun game.</p>
<p>Build Cheating</p>
<p>Any player that knowingly reports a false amount of build or levels, or abuses the award system will be suspended from all NERO ® Chapters for a minimum of six months. In addition, their character Example – Joseph is 10th level with 106 build. He goes to an event in another chapter, tells the check in staff he doesn’t have his card, but is 12th level with 123 build. After he is caught, he will be suspended for a minimum of 6 months, and his new amount of build will be 53.</p>
<p>NERO Sportsmanship Policy</p>
<p>All NERO Participants</p>
<p>Follow the spirit of the rules, as well as the letter of the rules.</p>
<p>Play fairly and honestly.</p>
<p>Be considerate of all other NERO participants.</p>
<p>Remember, everyone has the right to enjoy NERO as much as you do.</p>
<p>Contribute to the fun of all NERO participants.</p>
<p>Don’t play in a style that detracts from the fun of the event, or anyone’s chance to have fun at an event.</p>
<p>Staff, Marshals, etc...</p>
<p>Abide by the expectations that apply to all NERO participants.</p>
<p>It is your job to run the event. Remember, you are not playing against the players. Everyone’s enjoyment of the event is your top priority.</p>
<p>All participants must be treated equally and equitably, by you and by other participants. Favoritism will not be tolerated.</p>
<p>Run events in a professional manner. Remember that you represent NERO to anyone present at an event, whether participating or observing.</p>
<p>Administration (National, Local, etc...)</p>
<p>Abide by the expectations that apply to all NERO participants, Staff, Marshals, etc....</p>
<p>Respond and communicate in a timely, respectful, and articulate manner.</p>
<p>Uphold the authority of your staff, and do not overrule them without careful investigation.</p>
<p>Code of Conduct</p>
<p>NERO expects its members to act responsibly as adults, to respect other players, and abide by the NERO rules and policies.</p>
<p>NERO will not tolerate dangerous non-game physical violence, damage or theft of non-game items or property, vandalism, display of pornographic materials, open and gross lewdness, or any actions by an individual or group which demonstrates a wanton lack of respect for the safety or security of the people, property or environment at any NERO site.</p>
<p>NERO does not condone any form of out-of-game bigotry or discrimination against any group or individuals because of their out of game afflictions, including race, gender, age, religion, ethnic background, ideology, sexual orientation, physical appearance, handicap or disability. Or any other part of a player’s background. </p>
<p>All players in the NERO game are responsible for knowing the rules contained in the rule book and following them in the course of play. NERO reserves the right to remove you from play or otherwise limit you participation in NERO if it is found that you have disobeyed the NERO rules. NERO will make every reasonable effort to inform you of all rules changes, interpretations and corrections.</p>
<p>Remember that in all case it is the spirit of the rule and not the literal meaning of the rule that should guide you. If you find a loophole in a rule that obviously goes against the rules intention, then you should bring this your local rules committee. Knowingly trying to take advantage of this unintended loophole is cheesy at best and could be considered cheating at worse if your interpretation is gravely contrasted.</p>
<p>If there is a dispute over a rules interpretation between players, a Marshal should be called to act as an arbitrator. When dealing with a marshal or other NERO representative, you can help by presenting your case calmly and by answering all of the marshals’ questions as directly as possible. Once a decision is made, play along with it and don’t question the marshal’s ruling- the Marshal may have been aware of facts unavailable to you or may be making a decision based on what was intended by the rule.</p>
<p>If you feel a Marshal’s ruling was incorrect or unfair, you may bring this to the attention of an Adjudicator.</p>
<p>Do not nitpick on the details of the situation - understand and follow the intent of the rules. If you play fair and be considerate of everyone else’s enjoyment of the game, your comments will be taken more seriously and will be better respected. </p>
<p>NERO will remove any member who NERO suspects is intoxicated or high.</p>
<p>Content</p>
<p>References to explicit sexual behavior or concepts, particularly violent  ones, are not allowed.</p>
<p>Safety</p>
<p>Alcohol</p>
<p>Alcohol is prohibited from NERO events no matter what your age. In all cases, all laws regarding Alcohol must be adhered to. Our adventures are not an excuse for getting drunk out in the woods with your friends. Anyone caught with any controlled substance will be subject to severe disciplinary action. Take this point very seriously and report anyone you see with  alcohol or drugs.</p>
<p>Medic</p>
<p>If your character or another character is injured In-Game, you can shout for a “Healer”. However, if you or someone else is injured in real life, shout for a Medic and call a Hold. Do not call for a Medic unless it is a Out of Game emergency. If you hear the call for a Medic, drop to one knee and remain still and silent. Only the persons who have been identified as a Medic by Chapter Staff should respond to the call of Medic.</p>
<p>Real Weapons</p>
<p>If you bring a real weapon into a NERO game, you will be told to put it away. Real weapons can never be carried on your person. (Swiss army knives, small thieves’ tool knives and other such devices are acceptable.) Daggers may be carried for eating/utility purposes, but they must be “peace bonded” (tied in a sheath) when not at the table.</p>
<p>Page Status</p>
<p>A Page is a person who, for one reason or another, cannot enter combat. Some chapters will allow children to play NERO under Page status, and adults with a medical condition can also choose to play NERO as a Page. If you are planning on bringing your children to an event, it is best to contact the Chapter first for details. In most chapters, any child under 14 years old must be a Page. A Page can be a member of any race and any class, but cannot use combat skills or throw packet delivered attacks.</p>
<p>A Page should never be struck with a weapon or claw. In order to attack a page, you can point your weapon or packet at the Page and state “I kill you, page!”, or “I down you” (bleeding out) or any number of other actions. If there is someone within 5 feet of the Page, they can choose to defend the page and block your attack. To do so, they must state “I defend you” and role-play accordingly. A person cannot defend a page if they do not have a weapon, shield, or other ability to do so. All pages must wear an Orange headband to signify they are under Page status.</p>
<p>Smoking</p>
<p>Smoking is only permitted in designated smoking areas. Generally, you are discouraged from smoking in public areas because of consideration for the other players, for fire safety regulations, and because it takes away from the medieval feel of the games. </p>
<p>Torches and Flames</p>
<p>The rules on torches and flames vary based on the campsite’s rules. </p>
<p>Generally speaking, torches are not allowed. No open flames are allowed in cabins, including candles (although candle lanterns and oil lanterns are fine). In any event, flames are never to be left unattended.</p>
<p>In order to use a flashlight for in game purposes, you must have someone cast an Illumination spell. The flashlight must be diffused by either taping a cloth over the end or using a red filter and must be pointed towards the ground or up in the air. A flashlight can never be pointed near a person’s face. If at all possible, please avoid using flashlights as they distract from the medieval feel of the game.</p>
<p>A Liquid Light elixir can also be used but preferably the phys-reps for these should be chemical “light sticks.” The small battery operated glass “candles” and other small battery operated lighting devices cannot be used while adventuring. These things tend to break very easily and can be dangerous. If you want to use your flashlight to represent a candle or a small torch, you must have in your possession somewhere a real candle or torch that the flashlight represents.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Chapter 7 Adventuring Gear</p>
<p>Physical Rerepresentation</p>
<p>If you acquire any potions, scrolls, poisons, or alchemical substances during your adventures, then they should have appropriate Tags attached. If you create your own through the Production system, then you must supply a physical representation for the item, and the tag must be attached. This physical representation can be stolen, at which point the thief will take the tag and the item.</p>
<p>A scroll or potion that does not have a tag attached cannot be used. If the tag is lost, stolen or destroyed, the item is not usable. The tag by itself is not the item. If someone hands you an out-of-game tag and says “Here, drink this!” you should reply “Drink what?” since nothing is being shown to your character in-game. This rule exists because after all, these things take up room and add weight. You can’t carry around 100 potions as easily as you could 100 tags.</p>
<p>If your character finds or is given a magic weapon, you are sometimes given a physical representation for it (You should return it to the NERO Chapter you found it in when its magic expires). You cannot alter the weapon in any way except to repair it when needed. If the phys-rep wears out, then another must be built that looks just like the original. Magic items cannot ever be modified and must always look the same. This has the advantage of making it easy to spot your stolen sword if you should ever see it again. See “So you want to be a thief?” on page 94.</p>
<p>Game Items</p>
<p>All game items (such as jewelry and magic items) should be labeled with a number. This is for the marshals to be able to tell the worth of the item and the magic use (if any).</p>
<p>If you steal an item that does not have a number on it, then you should immediately return it as it is obviously personal property and not part of the game. See “So you want to be a thief?” on page 94.</p>
<p>Armor</p>
<p>Armor points</p>
<p>There are three ways a player may possess Armor Points: Physical Armor, Dexterity Armor, and Arcane Armor. The three types may be used together and add to your total of Armor Points. You can not use more armor points than your character can wear.</p>
<p>Wear Points</p>
<p>Your character’s Wear Point total is the limit of armor points you can use or “wear” at one time. Your base Wear Point total depends on your class, as  shown in figure 7-1.</p>
<p>Wear Bonuses</p>
<p>You can add Wear Points to your base by purchasing the skill wear extra armor or by wearing good costuming.</p>
<p>Wear Extra Armor: The skill wear extra armor adds 5 wear points per purchase to your characters wear point total up to a maximum of 40 points.</p>
<p>Costume Bonus: Any player will be awarded five wear points simply for being fully in costume with their entire visible costume fully fitting with the in game atmosphere see “Costumes” on page 121. A marshal must be consulted to see if your costume warrants the bonus. You should do this at every chapter you go to as some chapters have different criteria to make this decision.</p>
<p>The maximum Wear total a player can have is 40 (45 with good costuming), no effect can augment this bonus higher by any means. Armor points granted by the spell “Shield” are considered Armor but do not count toward your Wear Point total. </p>
<p>Example, Mandrake the scholar has 10 base wear points, he purchases Wear extra armor and now has 15 wear points. His costume is reviewed by a marshal and is given the 5 wear points for costuming. So he can now wear up to 20 Armor points.</p>
<p>Physical Armor</p>
<p>The Physical Armor Types are Leather, Chain Mail, and Plate. Table 7-6 shows the value of each Armor Type for each Body Location. Each location is worth one point for leather, two points for chain, and three points for plate except the chest and back which are worth three times as much since they cover a larger area. </p>
<p>A suit of armor may be rejected at any point on grounds of safety for such things including, but not limited to; protrusions, sharp edges, and unsafe materials.</p>
<p>Characters may select the armor type to use at each separate body location, making it easier for players to create their own personalized armor. Each location is considered covered in armor if at least three quarters of the entire area is covered. Locations with overlapping armor types count as the higher type. </p>
<p>A Suit of Armor is evaluated by adding the armor point value for each body location covered.</p>
<p>Armor does not have to be real to count for armor points, so long as it looks real.</p>
<p>The tag for armor allows a character to gain protection from a phys-rep rated up to the value on the tag. To claim the entire value of an armor tag the player must wear a phys-rep which has been evaluated by a marshal to be worth at least the value of the tag, you cannot wear 20 points of coverage, have a 30 point tag and claim 30 points of armor in game.</p>
<p>Leather: Leather is any material, natural or synthetic, that looks like leather.</p>
<p>Chain Mail: Chain Mail is made of material of interlocking links whose holes are small enough not to easily catch a finger.</p>
<p>Plate: Is armor made of rigid material that does not easily deform, or of material that accurately recreates the look of plate, either medieval or fantasy. Plate is made up or large pieces of metal or metal looking material.</p>
<p>Refitting Physical Armor</p>
<p>When a suit of armor takes damage it can be refitted to its full value. Refitting in this way can only be done by the armor’s wearer, and requires that the person spend an uninterrupted minute during which he can use no other game skills, cannot walk around, or be struck in any way. You may choose to interrupt yourself at any time. During the refitting the character will adjust (i.e. tighten straps, reposition plates) his armor so that it offers the best protection possible. If the character is struck by any packet or weapon, the refit is interrupted for no effect and must be begun again.</p>
<p>The smithing special ability Rapid refit and the spell Refit Armor can also refit physical armor.</p>
<p>Weapons</p>
<p>Weapon Combat</p>
<p>Safety is always the primary concern in weapon construction. Unfortunately, even the safest weapon could cause injury if improperly used. Therefore, in addition to safe weapon construction guidelines, practice in the use of the weapon is needed to ensure that all players enjoy the game as much as possible. Below are additional restrictions on specific weapons</p>
<p>Latex Weapons: may never be used for thrusting, stabbing or poking.</p>
<p>Blunt Weapons: If a blunt weapon does not have a “head” on it, it will inflict one less point of damage than normal. Blunt weapons may not be used for thrusting, and are required to have a padded thrusting tip for safety reasons.</p>
<p>Bows: You can use the bow in combat for blocking, but you may not attack with it. Once it blocks an attack, the bowstring is considered cut or unstrung by combat. The PC cannot fire arrows from it until he restrings the Bow (see below). For safety reasons, no taut bowstrings are allowed though a loose one may be used to sling the bow for carrying.</p>
<p>Restringing involves at least 3 seconds of role-play. No physical representations for extra bow strings are needed.</p>
<p>To Fire, the Bow must be held in front of the archer at arm’s length and must be aimed at the target when the packet is thrown. The archer must take the packet out of the quiver, touch the packet to the hand holding the bow, then throw. The packet must be thrown in the normal flight path of an arrow fired from the bow. It cannot be thrown overhead or around corners. It cannot be “flicked.” The damage call must be completed before throwing the packet.</p>
<p>The hand throwing the arrow (yellow packet) is the hand that concerns Proficiencies. Master Proficiencies carry over to archery. </p>
<p>All Vorpal Poisons, Enchanted Blade, Silver Aura and Elemental Blade spells work normally. Vorpal tags are to be taped to the bow, not the packet.</p>
<p>Damage Aura or Magic Aura upon a bow confers the ability for the archer to throw packets for the weapon type “magic.” All weapons that fall under the skill Archery will have the weapon type of each missile altered if the weapon itself is targeted by a magical aura of any type. This includes a Damage Aura, Elemental Aura, and/or Magic Aura, and means that each individual missile does not need to be targeted by the formal magic spell in order to create the desired effect.</p>
<p>Bows that are un-shatterable still need to be restrung after blocking.</p>
<p>Real bows and arrows are not permitted.</p>
<p>Spears: One handed spears can only be used to perform thrusting attacks and can never be thrown. A character hit by any part of a spear other than the 8 inch head takes no damage.</p>
<p>Two handed weapons: Two handed weapons must be used with both hands at all times. If you lose the use of one arm (as from a Wither Limb effect), then you cannot wield the weapon at all.</p>
<p>Weapon Safety Checks</p>
<p>Before every NERO event, all weapons must be approved at check-in by the weapons marshal. Since the requirements the construction of weapons are fairly strict, it is not unusual for a weapon to be disqualified at check-in. Even a weapon which qualified at a previous event may be disqualified (Weapons do wear out). NERO reserves the right to fail any weapon that is deemed unsafe or hazardous.</p>
<p>Any experimental weapon using unusual materials can fail safety check at any time. Bring a couple of standard weapons with you as a backup in case yours fails inspection. Often the deficiency can be corrected with the addition of a little open cell foam or tape, so it is good to bring these extra supplies with you in case your weapon is not allowed so you can fix it.</p>
<p>If you are having trouble with weapon construction, then bring what you have so far to a NERO event, and you can show it to the marshals who will give you a hand when they can. The old saying “practice makes perfect” is especially true with both weapon making and use.</p>
<p>Weapon Tags</p>
<p>Every weapon must have two tags. The first is the Weapon Safety Tag. This tag proves that your weapon has gone through safety check and is approved to be used for that event this tag will be affixed to the weapon.</p>
<p>The second tag is the Weapon Tag. This is the tag that shows that the weapon is in-game. When you purchase a weapon from a weaponsmith or from logistics, you will be buying this tag to keep on you.</p>
<p>A player may only carry as many tags as he/she has physical representations.</p>
<p>Some weapons can be strengthened to withstand two or more Destroy or Shatter spells. When you have this done to your weapon, you will be given a new tag to reflect the changes. Weapons can also be silvered which can be very useful when fighting certain monsters, as with strengthening, you will receive a new tag. See “Smithing*” on page 42.</p>
<p>Weapon Construction</p>
<p>Weapon combat is a large part of the NERO game. Because of NERO’s reliance on weapons, proper weapon construction is necessary to insure safe yet semi-realistic combat.</p>
<p>The guidelines in this section cover making a boffer weapon and choosing a latex or other manufactured weapon for play in the NERO game.</p>
<p>Pre-made weapons</p>
<p>There are a number of manufactured weapons that fall into the NERO guidelines for safety. If you purchase a pre-made weapon, it is your responsibility to determine the type of construction that was used. You must know what type of core the weapon has and what type of foam was used. Latex weapons are not required to have a thrusting tip, and may never be used for thrusting, stabbing or poking.  Latex and boffer swords are available for sale and many can be used for NERO combat resolution. A current list of approved vendors and styles for latext weapons as well as latex weapon construction guidelines can be found online at www.nerolarp.com </p>
<p>Make Your own</p>
<p>You may also choose to make your own boffer or latex foam weapons. Making a weapon can range from very simple to very hard depending on the materials you choose and the design of your weapon. The following sections walk through the construction of a very simple weapon, but also provide information about some advanced materials you can try later on. It is highly recommended that you build a simple weapon for you first attempt.</p>
<p>There are a number of weapons that fit within a medieval fantasy setting that are not mentioned here. NERO allows creativity in developing new weapons but all must be approved before use. Experimental weapon types must conform to the basic standards of safety. You should check with the marshals before and during construction so that you do not end up wasting time and materials on a weapon that will not be allowed in the game, even so it still may not pass in all NERO chapters. </p>
<p>Weapon Parts</p>
<p>Below is a list of terms that will be useful to know when constructing a weapon. These terms detail sections of the weapon and what they are used for.</p>
<p>Thrusting Tip</p>
<p>A thrusting tip consists of at least two inches of open cell foam padding beyond the end of the pipe insulation. If the foam tip is too small, opponents could get hurt with a stiff thrust. If the tip is too large, it could easily break off or fold over, making it useless. All thrusting tips do count towards the weapon’s overall length. The tip must collapse about 50% of its length when pressure is applied. The tip should also be the width of the weapon, and should not easily fit in an eye socket. Weapons with two possible striking ends, such as a staff, should have thrusting tips on both ends. For weapons with heads, the thrusting tip may be incorporated into the head design.</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft</p>
<p>This is the section of the weapon that is above the grip of the weapon. Blade/Shaft lengths of weapons can be determined by measuring from the end of the grip to the end of the thrusting tip. The Blade/Shaft area must be continuous 5/8” closed cell foam.</p>
<p>Head</p>
<p>Some weapons, such as a polearm, hammer, or spear, have an additional element(s) added to the weapon. The head(s) extend outwards from the shaft, must be a minimum of 6 inches in length along the shaft, must be made of open cell foam, and must be at least 1 inch thick or thicker. Each head can be a maximum of 2 cubic feet. The head must be positioned near the top of the weapon. </p>
<p>Crossguard</p>
<p>A crossguard is used in certain types of weapon and is a blocking surface that is perpendicular to the weapon. This blocking surface cannot have any kind of core inside of it, and can only be constructed of foam, and is a maximum length of 18” across.</p>
<p>Grip</p>
<p>This section of the weapon is the location where the weapon is held. With the exception of the special cases listed above, this section of the weapon does not need to be padded. The length of</p>
<p>the grip is the length of the weapon from the bottom of the blade/Shaft to the inside of the pommel see figure 7-1.</p>
<p>Pommel</p>
<p>The pommel is used to protect the butt end of a weapon; it is located at the end of the grip. The pommel should have closed cell foam that extends an inch past the end of the core and is then capped by a piece of closed cell foam.</p>
<p>Weapon Specific Specs</p>
<p>Certain weapons types may have additional requirements, which can be found below.</p>
<p>Bow</p>
<p>The NERO Bow (referred to hereafter as Bow) must be curved and formed in the shape of a bow. Overall length in a straight line from tip to tip must be between 34 and 58 inches. Thrusting tips must be on both ends.</p>
<p>Crossbow</p>
<p>The NERO Crossbow (referred to hereafter as Bow) must be a T-shape, with a stock length of 12 to 24 inches. The cross piece must be at least half the stock length and may not exceed 24 inches. Thrusting tips must be on all ends.</p>
<p>Arrows/Bolts</p>
<p>These are represented by yellow packets. Yellow packets are considered in-game items until they are fired and cannot be held in the same hand as another game item while either item is in use.</p>
<p>Arrows are always stoppable by Shields and weapons.</p>
<p>Quiver: An archer needs a Quiver in which they must carry their shots. There are 30 shots (arrows, bolts, etc.) in each quiver. Each time the character shoots his missile weapon whether he hits or the character shoots his missile weapon whether he hits or misses his target, a single shot is lost from his quiver.</p>
<p>Arrows and other missiles (bolts, etc.) are not recoverable items. Thrown Weapons such as small thrown weapons and javelins are recoverable.</p>
<p>Each quiver physical representation must be able to hold at least 30 yellow packets and, look like a real quiver. Each quiver can hold no more than 30 yellow packets, and a character cannot have  tags for more than 30 yellow packets per quiver rep on his person. The archer may carry as many quivers as he wants, as long as he has a physical representation for each.</p>
<p>Daggers/One Handed Swords/Two Handed Swords</p>
<p>Daggers, one handed swords, and two handed swords all follow the same basic construction guidelines. Each sword-type weapon has a blade, crossguard and pommel, and a grip area. There may be no gaps in foam between the top of the grip and the thrusting tip at the end of the blade.</p>
<p>In the case of swords without a perpendicular-style crossguard, such as katana, the blade area may extend from the top of the grip to the thrusting tip.</p>
<p>Maces/Axes/Hammers (Bludgeon/Hatchet/Sap)</p>
<p>There are five main parts to all maces, axes and hammers: the pommel, grip, shaft, head and thrusting tip. With the exception of the head that must be crafted of open cell foam, all styles are the same basic design. Weapons that do not have areas of 1” thick open cell foam, which have pointed edges, or areas that “catch” other weapons may be deemed unacceptable by any marshal. Axes may have a crossguard incorporated into the design. A Bludgeon is a small mace, a Hatchet is a small Axe, and a Sap is a small hammer.</p>
<p>Polearms/Spears</p>
<p>There are five main parts to all polearms and spears: the pommel,grip, shaft, head and thrusting tip. The thrusting tip is often incorporated into the head of polearms in order to reduce the tendency for it to shear off on a swing, and the thrusting tip for a spear should be incorporated into the head of the spear. Spears may only be used for thrusting. Spears and polearms may both have a crossguard incorporated into the design. </p>
<p>Staves</p>
<p>A staff is very simple to make, with whole of the core covered by foam, or you may have two hand holds not covered by foam. A staff must have thrusting tips on both ends. The middle 6” of the staff must be padded with a minimum of 1/2” thick pipe insulation.</p>
<p>Thrown Weapons</p>
<p>Thrown rocks, throwing stars, thrown daggers, javelins and other thrown weapons may not contain a core of any sort. Rocks must be made of a 6”x 6”or larger piece of open cell foam, and can be covered with duct tape, kite tape or fabric. Throwing stars, daggers or axes may be made of closed cell foam with no core, and should be cut into the appropriate shape, with tips not less than 2” wide. All thrown weapons must be a minimum of 6” long and may be a maximum of 18” long. </p>
<p>A javelin must be made of 3 feet of closed cell pipe foam with thrusting tips at both ends. A javelin may not include a core of any sort.</p>
<p>Thrown weapons may not be used in melee combat, they must be thrown. Since there is a wide range of shapes and sizes that can be used, approval is based on a case by case basis by the weapons marshal.</p>
<p>Weapon Safety Guidelines</p>
<p>Please see the NERO International Website www.nerolarp.com for the most updated information regarding weapon safety rules. There are several basic rules regarding weapon construction in NERO and they are as follows:</p>
<p>•	All weapons must all within the minimum and maximum length, grip and blade requirements for their weapon type.</p>
<p>•	All weapons must be approved by a NERO safety marshal before they can be used in play.</p>
<p>•	All home made weapons must have a thrusting tip.</p>
<p>•	All weapons must be padded from the tip of the blade to the hand grip. All weapons must be padded with at least 5/8 inch wall thickness closed cell foam regardless of blade size.</p>
<p>•	A weapon must have at least 0.5 inch but no more than 1.5 inches of closed cell foam extending beyond the end of the core before the thrusting tip is added.</p>
<p>•	All tips must be rendered safe with tape/cloth and padding. In a melee, it is possible to accidentally hit someone with the pommel or cross guard, so these parts must be protected as well.</p>
<p>•	All blade areas or areas of the weapon that may come in contact with another player must be protected with at least 5/8 inch weapons such as axes, hammers, maces, etc.</p>
<p>•	All weapons must be fairly rigid so as not to act as a whip when swung quickly. Under most circumstances, a weapon tip should not bend more than 6 inches from true when moderate force is applied to the tip and the grip is held level. Conversely, all weapons must also have some give to them when contact is made.</p>
<p>Construction Materials</p>
<p>Core</p>
<p>The core is the interior portion of a weapon that gives it strength and rigidity. There are several materials that can be used for cores including various types of PVC piping, some types of spiral wound fiberglass tubing, and several other types of materials. Please note that you may never use wood or heavy metals as part of your core in weapon construction.</p>
<p>The core of the weapon can be made of different materials based on the size of the weapon to be constructed.</p>
<p>Below is an overview of suggested cores and the types of weapons that can be created with each material.</p>
<p>Standard</p>
<p>The standard core for weapons is PVC of which there are 2 types: white PVC used in plumbing and grey PVC or CPVC used for electrical work. The following list uses the inner diameter of the tubing. Please note that schedule 20 CPVC has a thin wall and is more flexible than schedule 40 CPVC. If you use schedule 20, use one size higher based on the weapon you are making.</p>
<p>1/2 inch: This core can be used to make small and short and long weapons. This type of core has more give and should not be used in weapons longer than 46 inches.</p>
<p>3/4 inch: This core can be used to make two handed weapons.</p>
<p>Ultralight</p>
<p>Ultralight cores include carbon fiber, kitespar tube, fiberglass tube, and wrapped graphite tube. Aluminum core may only be used for polearms and staves. These material can be used to make most weapons, however the diameter of the kite pole determines which type of weapon it is best suited for. The following list uses the outer dimension of the tubing.</p>
<p>0.414 inch: This core can be used to make small, short and long weapons. This type of core has more give and should not be used in weapons longer than 46 inches. Please note that depending on the style of weapon construction, this core may have too much give at the maximum length for long weapons.</p>
<p>0.505 inch: This core can be used to make short and long weapons and spears. This type of core has more give and should not be used in weapons longer than 54 inches.</p>
<p>0.610 inch: This core can be used to make staves, two handed weapons and spears. This type of core has more give and should not be used in weapons longer than 64 inches.</p>
<p>0.745 inch: This core can be used for all two handed weapons. This type of core should not be used in weapons shorter than 54 inches.</p>
<p>Closed Cell Foam</p>
<p>This durable water resistant material is used in the construction of weapons in NERO. There are three types of closed cell foam that can be used for weapon construction: Pipe foam insulation, Pool Noodle, and Camp pad.</p>
<p>Pipe foam Insulation: The most common type of closed cell foam is pipe foam insulation. Closed cell pipe foam insulation is used to pad the blades of weapons, and must be at least 5/8 inch wall thickness. Please note that most foam found in home improvement stores does not posses the correct thickness.</p>
<p>Closed cell foam of the appropriate wall thickness can be difficult to locate. Currently the foam is available from a variety of places;</p>
<p>Merchantswares.com – LARP Gear supply house.</p>
<p>McMaster-Carr (a commercial tool company) and here is a list of part numbers:</p>
<p>• Part #4530K161 is usable for .414” kite spar, .505” kite spar and 1/2” PVC.</p>
<p>• Part #4530K162 is usable for .610” kite spar and 1/2” PVC.</p>
<p>• Part #4530K163 is usable for .745” kite spar, 3/4” PVC.</p>
<p>Pool noodle: Pool noodle is thicker than pipe insulation, and not all pool noodles fit PVC. You should bring measuring tape or a piece of pipe with you when you buy it.</p>
<p>Camp Pad: This material is used to make more advanced, sculpted weapons. The average camp pad found in stores such as Walmart is 1/4” thick. To achieve the correct thickness you must laminate multiple pieces together with contact cement. Weapons made with this material are held up to more scrutiny. Visit www.nerolarp.com for specifications for sculpted weapons. You should not attempt to make your first weapon out of this material.</p>
<p>Open Cell Foam:This material is a less dense foam that is commonly used to stuff couches and pillows and is found in most fabric stores. This foam is used in the construction of thrusting tips, weapon heads and some thrown weapons. The foam should be easily squeezable and not too dense. Alternatively you can also use a car sponge found at hardware stores.</p>
<p>Tapes</p>
<p>There are several types of tape that are commonly used in weapon making:</p>
<p>Duct Tape: Duct tape is the standard type of tape used in weapon making. It can be used for blades, thrusting tips, crossguards, and pommels. Duct tape can be found in a variety of colors and various thicknesses. Certain types of duct tape are heavier and less suitable for weapon construction.</p>
<p>Kite Tape: Kite tape or Nylon rip stop repair tape is a type of tape that is used normally for fixing kites. It is an extremely light form of tape that can be used in weapon construction. It is available in a variety of colors and can be purchased from a number of kite supply stores.</p>
<p>Strapping Tape: Strapping tape is a tape that has strands that run vertically along the tape. It is used for securing portions of a weapon together. Strapping tape does not rip, break or tear and makes a great light-weight reinforcement for cross guards, anchor points, thrusting tips and seams. Strapping tape is not used to cover a weapon, but is used under the duct tape to hold things together.</p>
<p>Gaffer Tape: This incredibly durable tape is used in stagecraft. It is a very dense strong tape. This type of tape should not be used on any striking surface of a weapon due to its weight and lack of give. It is useful for making sturdy crossguards.</p>
<p>Weapon Sock: This is sewn piece of fabric (that should be water repellent) that can be used to cover the striking surface of a weapon. This is used sometimes instead of taping the blade of a weapon. Ripstop nylon is a good fabric to use for this.</p>
<p>Weapon Dimensions</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Bow  Ranged</p>
<p>Base Damage : x</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft : x” - x</p>
<p>Head : x”- x”</p>
<p>Total Length : 34”- 58”</p>
<p>Core Size PVC: 1/2" Ultralight x</p>
<p>Grip 5” - 14” </p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Corssbow  Ranged</p>
<p>Base Damage : x</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft : x” - x</p>
<p>Head : x”- x”</p>
<p>Total Length : 12”- 24”</p>
<p>Core Size PVC: 1/2" Ultralight x</p>
<p>Grip 1” - 8” </p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Arrow  Missle</p>
<p>Base Damage : 3</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft : x” - x</p>
<p>Head : x”- x”</p>
<p>Total Length : 12”- ”</p>
<p>Core Size PVC: x Ultralight x</p>
<p>Grip x” - x” </p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Bolt  Missle</p>
<p>Base Damage : 3</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft : x” - x</p>
<p>Head : x”- x”</p>
<p>Total Length : 12”- ”</p>
<p>Core Size PVC: x Ultralight x</p>
<p>Grip x” - x” </p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Javelin  Missle</p>
<p>Base Damage : 2</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft : x” - x</p>
<p>Head : x”- x”</p>
<p>Total Length : 36”- 40”</p>
<p>Core Size PVC: x Ultralight x</p>
<p>Grip x” - x” </p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Throwing Dagger  Missle</p>
<p>Base Damage : 1</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft : x” - x</p>
<p>Head : x”- x”</p>
<p>Total Length : 12”- 18”</p>
<p>Core Size PVC: x Ultralight x</p>
<p>Grip x” - x” </p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Bludgeon  Small</p>
<p>Base Damage : 1</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft : 8” - 17</p>
<p>Head : 6”- 18”</p>
<p>Total Length : 12”- 26”</p>
<p>Core Size PVC: 1/2" Ultralight .412,.505</p>
<p>Grip 1” - 6” </p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Dagger  Small</p>
<p>Base Damage : 1</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft : 8” - 17</p>
<p>Head : 6”- 18”</p>
<p>Total Length : 12”- 26”</p>
<p>Core Size PVC: 1/2" Ultralight .412,.505</p>
<p>Grip 1” - 6” </p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Hatchet  Small</p>
<p>Base Damage : 1</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft : 8” - 17</p>
<p>Head : 6”- 18”</p>
<p>Total Length : 12”- 26”</p>
<p>Core Size PVC: 1/2" Ultralight .412,.505</p>
<p>Grip 1” - 6” </p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Sap  Small</p>
<p>Base Damage : 1</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft : 8” - 17</p>
<p>Head : x”- x”</p>
<p>Total Length : 12”- 26”</p>
<p>Core Size PVC: 1/2" Ultralight .412,.505</p>
<p>Grip 1” - 6” </p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Short Axe  Short</p>
<p>Base Damage : 2</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft : 18” - 24</p>
<p>Head : 6”- 18”</p>
<p>Total Length : 27”- 34”</p>
<p>Core Size PVC: 1/2" Ultralight .412,.505</p>
<p>Grip 1” - 14” </p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Short Hammer  Short</p>
<p>Base Damage : 2</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft : 18” - 24</p>
<p>Head : 6”- 18”</p>
<p>Total Length : 27”- 34”</p>
<p>Core Size PVC: 1/2" Ultralight .412,.505</p>
<p>Grip 1” - 14” </p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Short Mace  Short</p>
<p>Base Damage : 2</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft : 18” - 24</p>
<p>Head : 6”- 18”</p>
<p>Total Length : 27”- 34”</p>
<p>Core Size PVC: 1/2" Ultralight .412,.505</p>
<p>Grip 1” - 14” </p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Short Sword  Short</p>
<p>Base Damage : 2</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft : 18” - 24</p>
<p>Head : 6”- 18”</p>
<p>Total Length : 27”- 34”</p>
<p>Core Size PVC: 1/2" Ultralight .412,.505</p>
<p>Grip 1” - 14” </p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Long Axe  Long</p>
<p>Base Damage : 2</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft : 25” - 36</p>
<p>Head : 6”- 18”</p>
<p>Total Length : 35”- 46”</p>
<p>Core Size PVC: 1/2" Ultralight .412,.505</p>
<p>Grip 1” - 14” </p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Long Hammer  Long</p>
<p>Base Damage : 2</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft : 25” - 36</p>
<p>Head : 6”- 18”</p>
<p>Total Length : 35”- 46”</p>
<p>Core Size PVC: 1/2" Ultralight .412,.505</p>
<p>Grip 1” - 14” </p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Long Mace  Long</p>
<p>Base Damage : 2</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft : 25” - 36</p>
<p>Head : 6”- 18”</p>
<p>Total Length : 35”- 46”</p>
<p>Core Size PVC: 1/2" Ultralight .412,.505</p>
<p>Grip 1” - 14” </p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Long Sword  Long</p>
<p>Base Damage : 2</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft : 25” - 36</p>
<p>Head : x”- x”</p>
<p>Total Length : 35”- 46”</p>
<p>Core Size PVC: 1/2" Ultralight .412,.505</p>
<p>Grip 1” - 14” </p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Spear  Long</p>
<p>Base Damage : 2</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft : 20” - 45</p>
<p>Head : 8”- 8”</p>
<p>Total Length : 48”- 58”</p>
<p>Core Size PVC: 3/4" Ultralight .505,.616</p>
<p>Grip 1” - 30” </p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Polearm  Two Handed Sword</p>
<p>Base Damage : 3</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft : 38” - 44</p>
<p>Head : 44”- 18”</p>
<p>Total Length : 60”- 72”</p>
<p>Core Size PVC: 3/4" Ultralight 0.616</p>
<p>Grip 1” - 36” </p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Staff  Two Handed Sword</p>
<p>Base Damage : 3</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft : 24” - 32</p>
<p>Head : 32”- x”</p>
<p>Total Length : 60”- 72”</p>
<p>Core Size PVC: 3/4" Ultralight 0.616</p>
<p>Grip 0” - 9” </p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Two Handed Blunt  Two Handed Sword</p>
<p>Base Damage : 3</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft : 40” - 48</p>
<p>Head : 18”- 24”</p>
<p>Total Length : 48”- 62”</p>
<p>Core Size PVC: 3/4" Ultralight 0.616</p>
<p>Grip 1” - 36” </p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Two Handed Sword  Two Handed Sword</p>
<p>Base Damage : 3</p>
<p>Blade/Shaft : 40” - 48</p>
<p>Head : x”- x”</p>
<p>Total Length : 50”- 62”</p>
<p>Core Size PVC: 3/4" Ultralight 0.616</p>
<p>Grip 1” - 22” </p>
<p> </p>
<p>---</p>
<p>How to Make a Weapon</p>
<p>Constructing a weapon requires time and patience, but it is not that hard once you have practiced a bit. The next section will describe the steps to create various weapons, but focused on a basic one handed edged weapon.</p>
<p>In each of the steps, there will be a description of the materials and techniques.</p>
<p>Tools and materials:</p>
<p>Below is a list of tools and a list of materials you’ll need to make most weapons.</p>
<p>Materials</p>
<p>1. Core</p>
<p>2. Closed cel foam</p>
<p>3. Duct tape</p>
<p>4. 2” x 2” x weapon diameter Open Cell foam tip(s)</p>
<p>Tools</p>
<p>1. Marker</p>
<p>2. Measuring tool</p>
<p>3. Stapping/Duct tape</p>
<p>4. Saw</p>
<p>5. Scissors/Xacto/</p>
<p>6. Carving knife</p>
<p>1. The core of the weapon</p>
<p>After gathering your materials, the next step in creating a weapon is selecting an appropriate core for the type of weapon that you wish to make. You will need to do several things to prepare the core for weapon construction. First you will need to determine the length of the weapon that you wish make. Then you will have to cut the core approximately 3 inches shorter than the overall length of the weapon, 5 for weapons that require thrusting tips on both ends. This allows for padding both ends and the thrusting tip(s).</p>
<p>Cut the core to the right length with a hacksaw. If you are using a fibrous material, like kitespar, wrap a piece of tape around the area you are cutting to keep the fibers from fraying. Take care not to score areas that will be on your finished weapons. You will then need to clean up the edges of the cut so that there are no burrs or other protrusions. Lastly, you will need to cover both ends of the core with tape so there are no open ends.</p>
<p>2. Pad the striking area</p>
<p>The next step in creating a weapon is padding the striking area of the weapon. There are several things that you will need to do in this step. First, you should measure and cut the pipe foam to the desired blade/shaft length. Remember to measure the blade length to account for the the thrusting tip and the 1/2” overhang from the core. Next, you should slide the pipe foam over the core so that a 1/2” of foam hangs over one end. Make sure that the foam is snug to the core; if it rattles then the closed cell foam is too large and you will need to build out the core so that foam does not rattle. Cut off 1” of pipe foam (not from the piece you are using for the blade) and cut it into two equal halves. Compress one of the halves and stuff it into the end of the blade foam. Using a piece of tape, cover the small piece of foam that has been put into the end of the blade.</p>
<p>3. Add a crossguard (optional)</p>
<p>The next step is an optional step when creating a weapon though it is strongly encouraged. Certain weapon types have cross guards, including most types of swords and occasionally other hafted weapons. First, you need to cut a section of closed cell pipe foam of the appropriate size. Then cut a hole in the middle of the cross guard foam and slide the crossguard down the core until it meets the blade. Secure the crossguard to the blade using two strips of duct tape, then stuff the ends of the crossguard with open cell foam to strengthen the crossguard. Close off the ends of the crossguard with tape. Secure the cross guard to the grip by taking strips of tape from the crossguard to the grip. This will secure the blade and crossguard to the grip.</p>
<p>4. Add a pommel</p>
<p>The next step is to add a pommel at the end of the weapon. Cut a piece of closed cell foam so that is about 3 inches long. Place the foam on the butt end of the weapon so that the foam hangs at least one inch over the weapon’s core. As with the blade tip, place a half circle of compressed closed cell foam into the end of the foam and cover it with tape. Secure the pommel to the core with tape in such a way that at least one inch of closed cell foam extends past the core. Make sure that the pommel is secure to the core and is not loose. </p>
<p>6. Add a thrusting tip</p>
<p>The tip of the striking surface must have a thrusting tip. This tip is 2” of open cell foam. Longer thrusting tips tend to bend. Cut the foam to cover the tip. Once the tip is in place, use tape to cover it. Take a length of tape and place it so it goes across the end of the tip and down both sides, attaching the tip to the weapon. If the tip is round, use a razor to cut the corners so the tape conforms to the tip. Now add another piece of tape so that it goes across the end and down the exposed sides of the foam tip. Use a razor to cut the corners so the tape overlaps slightly and conforms to the tip. Finally, poke many tiny holes all over the tip so the air can escape and the tip can contract and expand freely.</p>
<p>7. Cover the blade</p>
<p>The next step is to cover the exposed foam with tape or with a weapon sock. Any striking surface on a weapon should be covered with either a weapon sock or tape. If you choose to use tape, all of the tape on the striking surface of a weapon should run vertically from the thrusting tip to the pommel and should slightly overlap the piece next to it. Do not use overuse tape on striking surfaces and thrusting tips, one layer with slight overlap is enough. Excessive layering may make your weapon hard and un-passable. Tape should NEVER be spiral wrapped around the weapon.</p>
<p>8. Add a grip</p>
<p>The last step of the weapon making process is to cover the exposed grip with tape so that it is easy to wield. Use electrical tape or hockey grip tape spiral wrapped around the grip section of the weapon, so that it can be held easily. If the weapon is not thick enough to comfortably wield, you may use padding beneath the grip tape.</p>
<p>Maintaining Your NERO Weapon</p>
<p>Any latex foam or boffer swords must be stored and maintained properly in order to remain safe. There are a few simple things you can do to increase the longevity of your weapon.</p>
<p>Do not store foam weapons in extreme heat or cold for any length of time. Storing it in your car in the sun may cause paints to stick, tape to wrinkle and general degradation of the weapon over time.</p>
<p>Avoid soaking weapons in water and do not use your weapons if they have become waterlogged.</p>
<p>Do not rest weapons on the tips, lean on the foam ends or otherwise mash the foam at the ends. The tip foam will break down leaving less padding on the core, which will lead to failure of weapons safety check.</p>
<p>You may want to consider a fabric bag for individual latex weapons to keep their finish protected while in storage. </p>
<p>Shields</p>
<p>Safety is the prime consideration when constructing a shield. You may use almost any strong material such as wood, plastic or aluminum, but all edges must be covered with 5/8” pipe insulation. The face and edges of your shield may not have any sharp edges, bolts or other protuberances that would potentially cut or otherwise injure another person.</p>
<p>The longest dimension of a shield may not exceed 36 inches, including the pipe foam that covers the edges. The maximum area of a shield is 531 square inches (a 26” diameter circle). The area of a shield includes any cavities, recesses, voids or holes in the shield. A shield may be made in any shape, be it circular, oval, “kite” or “coffin” shaped, teardrop shaped or make to another design. The parts of a shield consist of the face, padded edging, and handle. Corrugated plastic, round sled blanks or wood are inexpensive and easy to cut to your preferred shape. You can obtain a handle from almost any hardware store, and then use a 1” to 1 1/2” strip of nylon strapping, or part of a belt to make the strap that will hold the shield to your forearm.</p>
<p>Take care to attach the handle and strap in a manner that does not leave sharp bolts or edges on the outside of your shield and trim any edges on the inside that may cut the shield user. While a shield may not be used offensively at NERO, and may not be used for “shield bashing”, it is possible that you could trip or fall on your shield, or someone else could fall into you. Safety is important, and any shield not considered safe by a weapons marshal will be failed at safety check.</p>
<p>Potions</p>
<p>The effects of potions and scrolls are the same as for a cast spell. </p>
<p>A scroll or potion physical representation is not valid unless it has an actual scroll or potion tag attached to the phys-rep. Likewise, a scroll or potion tag without a physical representation is also invalid. If you receive tags without physical representations (for example, after using your Production Points to create items), then it is your responsibility to provide the appropriate physical representation and make sure the tag is attached. All potion phys-reps must be large enough to hold, or appear to hold, at least a minimum of a quarter ounce of liquid. The phys-rep does not actually have to contain any liquid to be valid. </p>
<p>When the potion is used, the “used” potion tag must be given to the recipient or a Marshal as appropriate. To use a potion, you must role-play the proper drinking motions, and this must take at least three seconds. You do not have to count it out loud.</p>
<p>A potion may be “force fed” to an unconscious or sleeping person by someone else, but such a character cannot “accidentally” drink one. You cannot attach a potion or elixir to your collar or shield and “bite” into it to get its effects while bound or in battle. Potions cannot be mixed into food or drink or diluted or mixed together in any way. All potions affect the drinker only, and bypass any protective spells such as Shield Magic or Reflect Magic. Note that potions affect only the drinker and do not give the drinker the ability to cast the spell effect of the particular potion. For example, a person drinking a Dispel Magic potion does not gain the ability to cast a Dispel Magic instead, the potion will dispel all magic on the drinker.</p>
<p>Scrolls</p>
<p>To use a scroll, you must pull out the scroll, hold it before you, have enough light to be able to read it, touch a spell packet to the scroll, actually read the scroll, and then throw the packet. If your scroll is attached to a weapon or shield, you may not be swinging it while reading the scroll. </p>
<p>After the scroll is used, the tag is removed but the paper remains. The magical writing is inert although anyone can tell what spell used to be on the scroll. You must have an actual scroll phys-rep for each scroll tag.</p>
<p>All scroll phys-reps must be at least 16 square inches (For example, a scroll that is 2 inches tall by 8 inches long would be fine).</p>
<p>Alchemy </p>
<p>Players with the skill of Alchemy can create certain contact substances, elixirs and gases. These substance do not detect as magical by Detect Magic. Alchemical effects are not affected by Dispel Magic.</p>
<p>Anyone can drink an elixir or feed one to someone else or apply Vorpal Coatings. To apply other poisons you need one level of Alchemy. To throw gas globes you must have the same number of alchemy levels as the gas’ production level. In essence you must be able to make a gas to throw it.</p>
<p>Creating Alchemical Substances</p>
<p>Alchemy is a production skill and is governed by the Production system as described in The skill System chapter page 33. You may make any alchemical substance that you possess the skill to make that has a cost in the Production Levels chart.</p>
<p>Damage from Alchemy</p>
<p>Characters can be affected by alchemical substances in many ways. The effects are instantaneous. “Cause” poisons do body damage only, since they bypass armor. This damage can not be reversed by an antidote, but can be healed as normal damage. Berserk, Feeblemind, Hallucinoid, Nausea, Paralyze, Sleep, and Vertigo are all visible to any viewer while they are in effect, so long as they take the time to observe them and ask the affected player “Visible Effects?” and the affected player will respond “Visibly <effect>ed”. Many substances can be reversed by a specific antidote if taken after exposure to the substance. The spell defensive Poison Shield will not stop ingested substances from taking effect, but will stop all other attacks with the word “poison” in the verbal. The spell Purify Bl ood will cleanse the body of all active poison effects present except for Ensl avement. Al chemical Solv ents, Vorpal Coatings, Liquid Lights, Pastes of Stickiness , and Oils of Slipperiness are not affected by Purify Bl ood and will not set off a Poison Shield or a Resist Poison.</p>
<p>Mind Effect Restrictions</p>
<p>A chapter may, at their option, restrict the use of the following effects: Ensl avement, Forget-It-Well , and Forget-Me-Not. The chapter may restrict these effects in one of two ways. They can choose these effects to be void and unusable in their chapter, or they may opt to allow their usage only against NPCs.</p>
<p>Information on whether your local chapter uses the Mind Effect Restrictions rule, and which Game Effects this rule applies to will be available on the chapter’s Web site, and will also be announced at the Opening Ceremonies of all of their events. </p>
<p>Types of Alchemical Substances</p>
<p>Elixirs</p>
<p>Elixirs may be drunk like potions or they may be placed in food or drink. This is signified by either attaching the tag to the underside of the food vessel, placing a token in the food, or having a marshal witness you make pouring motions over the food or drink. Mixing two elixirs does not cancel the elixirs. If a food or drink has more than one elixir present, all elixirs will affect the victim and be used up after the first bite or drink. One use of the racial skill Resist Poison will block all elixirs present.</p>
<p>Gases</p>
<p>Gases are delivered by an orange packet. Unlike a spell packet, gas containers are in-game. They work on a single target, indoors or outdoors. Before throwing the packet, the user must announce “<Type> gas poison;” for example “Sleep gas poison.” This phrase simulates preparing the gas. The “verbal” is not in-game so even a silenced or mute character may use one. If the “verbal” is not said properly then the attack is unsuccessful as the gas was not “prepared” properly (Imagine preparing a hand grenade). The packet must hit the target or the target’s possessions and otherwise must follow all spell packet rules. Even though the “verbal” is not in-game, the effect is recognized by anyone who hears it. (In-game, assume each gas has a different color and texture associated with it to allow for identification.) If the poison does numerical damage, the number is added to the end of the “verbal” and must Figure 7-4. c Contact: ffl£ Elixir: (__^ Gas: ( « | be said before the packet is thrown. Thrown Alchemy is subject to Disruption.</p>
<p>Note that gas globes, since they are in-game, can be fumbled and stolen. To steal a globe, you must steal the actual globe physical representation itself and not the tag. You may then either go out-of-game to the person from whom you stole the globes in order to get the tags, or can get a Marshal to do it.</p>
<p>Gases can also be put into gas traps. See “Gas Traps” on page 97.</p>
<p>Contact Poisons</p>
<p>Contact poisons must be represented by a gel-like substance that can be smeared on the object to be trapped. (Petroleum jelly works fine). If the person applying the substance comes in contact with it, he or she will be affected as well (if applicable). poison shield and resist poison will protect the victim from being affected by contact poisons. Multiple contact poisons which would normally affect a victim simultaneously are protected by a single poison Shield or resist poison.</p>
<p>Vorpal Coatings</p>
<p>Vorpal Coatings add 5 points to the base damage of the weapon, for a set number of hits per application. They take effect immediately, doing damage to Armor Points and then Body Points after all Armor Points have been removed.</p>
<p>Damage should be called by adding 5 points to the weapon damage (with any other magical or skill bonuses also added, of course).</p>
<p>A hit is used up only if the strike lands or it is negated by a defense, but cannot be saved up to use on later swings once applied; the damage increase is for the first 1, 3, or 5 hits depending on the coating used. </p>
<p>Applying a vorpal coating takes time to apply. It cannot be done with a quick touch in the middle of battle. The tag must be taped onto the weapon. The taping of the tag onto the weapon represents the time it takes, which may never be less than three seconds. If you do not have the tag taped to your weapon then the vorpal coating is not effective. A new tag must be put on the weapon each time a new vorpal coating is applied. Only one vorpal coating can be on a weapon at a time.</p>
<p>Alchemical Substances</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Alchemical Solvent</p>
<p>Level Contact : 2</p>
<p>Level Elixer : </p>
<p>Level Gas : </p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This solvent, covering one square foot per dose, will remove either an Oil of Slipperiness or a Past of Stickiness. Once used, the entire dosage is consumed.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Antidote (Contact)</p>
<p>Level Contact : </p>
<p>Level Elixer : 2</p>
<p>Level Gas : </p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>Antidotes are used to cure lasting effects, such as from Sleep elixirs and not from instantaneous effects such as damage. Antidote (Contact) cures any contact substance. Antidote (Ingested) cures any ingested elixir. Antidote (Gas) cures any gas substance. It does not remove any monster carrier attacks. Gas Antidote will remove Monster Packet attacks only if the attack included the word “Gas”. Enslavement needs a specific antidote.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Antidote (Gas)</p>
<p>Level Contact : </p>
<p>Level Elixer : 4</p>
<p>Level Gas : </p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>Antidotes are used to cure lasting effects, such as from Sleep elixirs and not from instantaneous effects such as damage. Antidote (Contact) cures any contact substance. Antidote (Ingested) cures any ingested elixir. Antidote (Gas) cures any gas substance. It does not remove any monster carrier attacks. Gas Antidote will remove Monster Packet attacks only if the attack included the word “Gas”. Enslavement needs a specific antidote.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Antidote (Ingested)</p>
<p>Level Contact : </p>
<p>Level Elixer : 5</p>
<p>Level Gas : </p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>Antidotes are used to cure lasting effects, such as from Sleep elixirs and not from instantaneous effects such as damage. Antidote (Contact) cures any contact substance. Antidote (Ingested) cures any ingested elixir. Antidote (Gas) cures any gas substance. It does not remove any monster carrier attacks. Gas Antidote will remove Monster Packet attacks only if the attack included the word “Gas”. Enslavement needs a specific antidote.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Berserk</p>
<p>Level Contact : </p>
<p>Level Elixer : 10</p>
<p>Level Gas : </p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p></p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Cause Damage</p>
<p>Level Contact : </p>
<p>Level Elixer : 2</p>
<p>Level Gas : 3</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This substance does 10 points of body damage.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Cause Light Damage</p>
<p>Level Contact : </p>
<p>Level Elixer : 1</p>
<p>Level Gas : 2</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This substance does 5 points of body damage.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Cause Serious Damage</p>
<p>Level Contact : </p>
<p>Level Elixer : 4</p>
<p>Level Gas : 5</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This substance does 20 points of body damage.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Charm</p>
<p>Level Contact : </p>
<p>Level Elixer : </p>
<p>Level Gas : 8</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>This alchemical substance will cause the victim to be under the same effects as a Charm spell. The victim will be Charmed to the creature who administered the poison. It can be resisted by those with a Resist Charm ability.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Cure Light Damage</p>
<p>Level Contact : </p>
<p>Level Elixer : 1</p>
<p>Level Gas : </p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This substance heals 5 points of body damage.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Death</p>
<p>Level Contact : </p>
<p>Level Elixer : 9</p>
<p>Level Gas : </p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This causes death immediately, see Table 2-2 on page 23. This elixir does not leave any traceable marks, and cannot be identified as the cause of death. The only thing that will save the victim of this poison is a Life spell given within five minutes.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Enslavement</p>
<p>Level Contact : </p>
<p>Level Elixer : </p>
<p>Level Gas : </p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>The victim of this poison will be enslaved to the person administering the poison and will obey absolutely any and all commands given by the person to whom they are enslaved, and will even commit</p>
<p>suicide. Otherwise, it is has the same effects as a Charm spell. Enslavement can only be cured by a specific antidote. This effect is also removed if the character resurrects. This effect is stronger than Calm, Calm Animal, Charm, Charm Animal, Shun, shun animal, Control Undead, or Fear. See Table 5-6 on page 64. Please note that additional Enslavement effects will override another </p>
<p>Enslavement effect, see “Charm Effects” on page 47.</p>
<p>Enslavement is a powerful ability which particularly has the potential to ruin the fun of any player. As such the use of this effect can never be used by a PC on a PC.</p>
<p>No other effect (either LCO or otherwise) may duplicate the ability of Enslavement.</p>
<p>In addition, the following rules apply to Enslavement: </p>
<p>You cannot administer Enslavement to yourself.</p>
<p>You cannot be enslaved to “act normally,” However a person under the effects of enslavement does not act like a robot or strangely, they are just compelled to follow the wishes of the enslaver.</p>
<p>The duration of Enslavement is permanent, and it can only be cured by the specific antidote or the resurrection of the target.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Enslavement Antidote</p>
<p>Level Contact : </p>
<p>Level Elixer : 10</p>
<p>Level Gas : </p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This antidote is the only thing that will release a victim from the effects of an Enslavement poison. After the Enslavement is cured, the victim remembers everything that happened and knows they were enslaved and to whom.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Feeblemind</p>
<p>Level Contact : </p>
<p>Level Elixer : 6</p>
<p>Level Gas : 7</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>This alchemical substance lowers a character’s intelligence to that of an idiot for 5 minutes. While under its effects, a character cannot use any skills and is so stupid that he or she is not even aware of the poisoning.</p>
<p></p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Forget-it-Well</p>
<p>Level Contact : </p>
<p>Level Elixer : 10</p>
<p>Level Gas : </p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This poison will cause the victim to forget everything that happened within the last hour. This amnesia becomes permanent if not cured within ten minutes by a Purify Bl ood spell or the appropriate antidote. A Killing Blow within the ten minutes will not reverse the memory loss effect of this poison, and neither will resurrection, but if the victim’s body dissipates before the 10 minute period has elapsed, then the poison will be negated and the memories restored.  Forget-it poisons, like all poisons, may never be used on a creature that is dead.</p>
<p></p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Forget-Me-Not</p>
<p>Level Contact : </p>
<p>Level Elixer : 7</p>
<p>Level Gas : </p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This alchemical substance will cause the victim to lose memory of the last 15 minutes. In every other way it acts the same as a Forget-it-Well .</p>
<p></p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Hallucinoid</p>
<p>Level Contact : </p>
<p>Level Elixer : 2</p>
<p>Level Gas : </p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>This alchemical substance causes the victim to hallucinate. They will see pink elephants and other strange things for 5 minutes. The victim will probably be aware that they are under the effects of a poison but will be unable to do much about it. When under its effects, game skills can be used, but the player will most likely use them against imaginary creatures.</p>
<p></p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Intoxicant</p>
<p>Level Contact : </p>
<p>Level Elixer : 1</p>
<p>Level Gas : </p>
<p>Duration: 1 Hour</p>
<p>This acts as a strong alcoholic drink. It will render the victim quite drunk for 1 hour.</p>
<p></p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Liquid Light</p>
<p>Level Contact : 1</p>
<p>Level Elixer : </p>
<p>Level Gas : </p>
<p>Duration: 5 Days</p>
<p>This substance will allow a glow stick or other light physical representation to be used in game as per the Illumination spell. It cannot be applied to a tree or other object to make it glow; it can only be used on a phys-rep that gives off light. Please note that Alchemy 1 is required to activate a Liquid Light, but not to hold, or otherwise use one, once it has been activated.</p>
<p></p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Nausea</p>
<p>Level Contact : </p>
<p>Level Elixer : 5</p>
<p>Level Gas : 6</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>This elixir will cause the victim to be nauseous for five minutes, during which time no in game skills can be used.</p>
<p></p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Oil of Slipperiness</p>
<p>Level Contact : 5</p>
<p>Level Elixer : </p>
<p>Level Gas : </p>
<p>Duration: 1 Hour</p>
<p>This is a contact oil that will last for one hour once exposed to air. If put on an item, the oil will make the item impossible to pick up. It could also be placed on the ground (if enough were used) to prevent anyone from standing in the area. You would not be able to even crawl out of the area unless you could grab a hold onto something or someone outside of the area to pull free. One dose will cover an object up to one square foot in area. It can be counteracted by an Alchemical Solvent or a Paste of Stickiness . </p>
<p></p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Paralyze</p>
<p>Level Contact : </p>
<p>Level Elixer : 8</p>
<p>Level Gas : 9</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>This poison is identical to a Paralyze spell.</p>
<p></p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Paranoia</p>
<p>Level Contact : </p>
<p>Level Elixer : 2</p>
<p>Level Gas : 3</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>This causes the victim to think that people he or she normally dislikes are out to kill them. It lasts one hour.</p>
<p></p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Paste of Stickiness</p>
<p>Level Contact : 5</p>
<p>Level Elixer : </p>
<p>Level Gas : </p>
<p>Duration: 1 Hour</p>
<p>It can also be used to pin people to the ground if enough is available. Note that this paste will have no effect in combat as it takes three seconds to set; thus you cannot put it on your shield or sword to “capture” enemy weapons. It can be counteracted by an Alchemical Solvent, an Oil of Slipperiness , or a Release spell.</p>
<p></p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Poison Shield</p>
<p>Level Contact : </p>
<p>Level Elixer : 4</p>
<p>Level Gas : </p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This elixir works exactly as the spell of the same name. It grants a Spell Defense to the recipient. It cannot be stacked with the spell of the same name, nor can it be removed by Purify Blood.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Sleep</p>
<p>Level Contact : </p>
<p>Level Elixer : 6</p>
<p>Level Gas : 7</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>This poison acts as a Sleep spell.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Vertigo</p>
<p>Level Contact : </p>
<p>Level Elixer : 5</p>
<p>Level Gas : 6</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>This poison will cause the victim to lose balance and be unable to remain standing for five minutes, during which the victim can not use any in-game skills.</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Vorpal Coating 1</p>
<p>Level Contact : 1</p>
<p>Level Elixer : </p>
<p>Level Gas : </p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>Putting this contact gel on a weapon makes the weapon do 5 extra points of damage for a set number of hits. It comes in three variations: 1 hit Vorpal Coating, 3 hit Vorpal Coating, and 5 hit Vorpal Coating.</p>
<p></p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Vorpal Coating 3</p>
<p>Level Contact : 3</p>
<p>Level Elixer : </p>
<p>Level Gas : </p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>Putting this contact gel on a weapon makes the weapon do 5 extra points of damage for a set number of hits. It comes in three variations: 1 hit Vorpal Coating, 3 hit Vorpal Coating, and 5 hit Vorpal Coating.</p>
<p></p>
<p>---</p>
<p>Vorpal Coating 5</p>
<p>Level Contact : 5</p>
<p>Level Elixer : </p>
<p>Level Gas : </p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>Putting this contact gel on a weapon makes the weapon do 5 extra points of damage for a set number of hits. It comes in three variations: 1 hit Vorpal Coating, 3 hit Vorpal Coating, and 5 hit Vorpal Coating.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>NERO Formal Magic</p>
<p>Welcome to the NERO® Formal Magic System©. The system may be modified from time to time by NERO International. Suggestions for modifications to these rules should be directed to NERO International at jvalenti@nerolarp.com with “NERO FORMAL MAGIC” as the subject. These rules may not be modified in any way by the NERO chapters, nor can any game effects change the way these rules work. Local chapters may not alter the mechanics of any of the rules contained in this rulebook. This includes “weekend” effects as well as “area-specific” effects. None of these types of effects are ever allowed under any circumstances. Scrolls may not contain modifications or flaws of any kind, except to make the scroll unable to be copied or destructible. The scrolls listed here may not be changed in any way. If used, they must be used exactly as written. Urgent questions and interpretations of these rules will be left to the local Formal Magic marshal. Any questions, interpretations, and local rulings should be brought to the attention of NERO International, which serves as final arbitrator of these rules. NERO International will not overturn decisions made by the local Formal Magic Marshal unless it is absolutely necessary, although wording may be added to the system to negate any confusion in the future.</p>
<p>Definition of Basic Terms</p>
<p>The following is a definition of terms used throughout this document:</p>
<p>Affinity: When a transform(not curse of transformation) is cast cast on a spirit it leaves a mark called an “Affinity”. The affinity is specific to the transform creature of the scroll cast and level of the scroll.</p>
<p>The duration is permanent, and will remain even after the transform that left it has expired.</p>
<p>Affinities are needed to upgrade Transforms, once you have a 7th lvl affinity you can upgrade to an 8th, even if your 7th level transform has expired. Once you have a 8th lvl you can cast a 7th 8th or 9th lvl of the appropriate creature.</p>
<p>It does not count against a character’s spirit effect limit.</p>
<p>Affinity can be removed by casting a Destroy Magic spell on the target, casting a transform to a higher level creature of the same type, or casting a transform to any other creature.</p>
<p>The existence of an Affinity is not revealed during a Celestial IDENTIFY. Plot may allow some NPCs to sense a character’s transform, though they may have direct knowledge of what it is. For example, an Ice Wolf may bristle in the presence of a character with a fire-related Transform, even though it is not aware of the specific enchantment on that character.</p>
<p>Chapter: The local NERO game in which you are playing.</p>
<p>Marshal: Throughout this document, the term “Marshal” will be used to refer to the Formal Magic Marshal. Some chapters require a separate certification process for becoming a Formal Magic Marshal.</p>
<p>Caster: This term always refers to the Formal Magic Caster. This person is also known as the Primary Caster.</p>
<p>Secondary Caster: This term refers to those Formal Magic Casters (other than the Primary Caster) who are participating in a batch.</p>
<p>Levels: This always refers to the number of levels of Formal Magic possessed in the appropriate school. For instance, if a character is casting a Celestial Formal Magic, then only count the number of levels of Celestial Formal Magic he has purchased. </p>
<p>Dark Territory: This term refers to a formal magic that might not succeed. The outcome is determined by the Marshal using random means, usually the role of one ten sided die(1=success, 2-5=flaw, 6-9=fail, 10=backlash).</p>
<p>The chosen means of random determination must be explained to the caster and performed in the presence of the caster. “Pick a number” is never acceptable. The marshal must record the chosen means (and the outome) in the Formal Magic Log.</p>
<p>Batch: A group of formal magic castings of the same school of magic are lumped together into a single “Batch” so long as there is a gap no longer than a 60 seconds between each casting attempted. If more than 60 seconds elapses between formal magic castings within a batch, then the batch is finished. The formal magic Glyph of Protection can only be the first formal magic in a batch.</p>
<p>If the caster has cast other formal magic within the same batch, all formal magic attempted by that caster within that batch will count in the same game day – the game day in which the batch is begun.</p>
<p>Circle: This term refers to the representation used for the formal magic casting. </p>
<p>Extended Circle of Power: A circle created by the Create Protective Circle or Create Extended Circle of Power formal magic. </p>
<p>Components: This term refers to the Formal Magic Components being used for this formal magic casting. Components come in various “flavors”: Power (P), Creation (C), Elemental (E), Time (T), Void (V), Destruction (D), and Spirit (S). Each component has a value of 1, 2 or 4. Formal Magic costs are listed with the total value of each type of needed component.</p>
<p>For example, P5 means any combination of Power components totaling a value of 5. One spell, Greater Extension, specifically requires a Power component of value 2 or 4 in addition to other components. Components expire no longer than 2 years after the issue date. If there is no printed expiration date then the expiration date is assumed to be one year. </p>
<p>Scroll: This is the Formal Magic Scroll being used for this casting. </p>
<p>Spell: This term always refers to a magic spell of the appropriate school, level one through level nine.</p>
<p>Weapon: This refers to any item on the weapon production chart, including Bow or Crossbow, but not including Arrows or Bolts. </p>
<p>Unrestricted: This term refers to an item that was placed into game according to the Treasure Distribution Policy issued by NERO. Magic items are also given this classification if they are constructed using only components, scrolls, and production items of Unrestricted classification.</p>
<p>Local Chapter Only (LCO) : This is a special Plot related item that can only be used in the issuing chapter. To all other chapters, the item does not exist for use in-game. These items are not intended to be used to alter the rules or create effects that are outside the system.</p>
<p>Pyramid: This term is used to describe formal magic castings that accumulate power based upon multiple castings within a batch. The scrolls Damage Aura, Protection Aura, and Spell Store are examples of this type of formal magic. The first step requires only a single casting, the next step requires two additional castings (for a total of three castings). To go further, three additional castings are needed (for a total of six castings), with the last step involving four additional castings (total of ten castings). These types of formal magic can never go past ten castings (four steps), and some may be limited below that number. Each step counts as one effect with regard to the 5 formal magic effect limit. </p>
<p>Healing Effects: Effects that, if cast normally, include the word “Earth” in the incantation.</p>
<p>Necromantic Effects: Effects that, if cast normally, include the word “Chaos” in the incantation.</p>
<p>Special Types of Formal Magic</p>
<p>Scroll-Specific</p>
<p>A formal magic designated as scroll-specific means that the scroll is limited to a single specific type of that formal magic; it is never all the possible choices on a single scroll. For example, the formal magic Cloak is scrollspecific - the scroll will list the specific type of Cloak that it can be used to create; it may not be used to cast any type of Cloak not listed on the scroll.</p>
<p>Transform</p>
<p>This term refers to a category of formal magic that only affects a spirit after it permanently dies. The formal magic does not normally activate until this time. Subsequent castings of any type of Transform always override the previous casting.</p>
<p>All Transform formal magic is considered dormant. The existence of a Transform is not revealed during a Celestial Identify. At the time of the target’s permanent death, the target becomes an NPC at the chapter where the transform was cast. Even after permanent death, certain Transforms can upgrade or weaken the creature. See the individual formal magic scrolls for details. After the permanent death of the target, the formal magic takes effect to permanently transform the target into the specified creature. This may take place immediately, or may take several weeks. The details are left to local NERO Plot. Once transformed into the creature, the Transform formal magic is complete. The newly transformed creature will have the currently-active spirit-affecting formal magics as they did before the transformation, except for the Transform itself.</p>
<p>Effects exist which may for limited duration invoke the full transformation prior to permanent death. Circumstances which may temporarily invoke the transformation prior to permanent death are determined exclusively by the Plot/Staff of the local NERO chapter. In situations where the transformation takes place prior to the permanent death, the Transform is no longer dormant, and can be Identified in an appropriate Extended Circle of Power. The invocation of the transformation is generally not for use during situations where PCs are directly pitted against other PCs. The final determination of this is up to the local chapter. </p>
<p>Only one Transform may be in effect on any spirit at any one time. A new Transform formal magic will replace an old one on a target spirit. This includes Local Chapter Only Transform formal magic.</p>
<p>Being an NPC means that the target is completely under the local chapter’s direction. There is certainly no guarantee that the local chapter will even let the NPC ever come into game. If local plot chooses to allow the NPC to come into game, there is also no guarantee that the local chapter will allow the character to pursue the goals from its normal lifetime.</p>
<p>Creation and Summoning</p>
<p>Local Plot must be notified well before the casting of this type of formal magic.</p>
<p>When the creature appears a new card will be supplied, regardless of the statistics of the creature when it originally appeared.</p>
<p>The caster may be required to supply an NPC to play the part of the creature or the local chapter may supply the NPC. This policy varies from chapter to chapter; please</p>
<p>check in advance with the local chapter. The local chapter can always substitute a staff member or other NPC for some or all of the role-playing interaction with the creature. </p>
<p>When this formal magic is performed, the marshal should consult the local guidelines for information on the attitudes and personality of the creature. The NPC playing the creature must abide by the personality requirements and directives given to them by the formal magic marshal. Failure to do so may result in the termination of the role and loss of the creature.</p>
<p>Unintelligent creatures will only follow simple 25 word (or shorter) command phrases with a single condition and a single objective. For example, an acceptable command would be “Follow me and kill anyone who attacks me”, “Attack anyone who enters this room besides these six people”, “Attack anyone who enters the crypt and isn’t wearing this symbol”, or “Follow me and search every creature I kill”. Control of unintelligent creatures can never be passed to someone else. All commands are subject to the approval of the local chapter. NERO International is currently compiling a complete list of acceptable commands; please send all suggestions via email to jvalenti@nerolarp.com with “NERO FORMAL MAGIC SUGGESTION” as the subject.</p>
<p>Intelligent creatures are not automatically controlled. They may be friendly or may simply attack. Negotiations may take place between the caster and the created or summoned intelligent creature.</p>
<p>A creature created or summoned in one NERO chapter might be prohibited from being taken to another chapter. If the creature can be taken to another chapter, the monster card used will be the monster card of the similar creature at the destination chapter. </p>
<p>Approved types of Summonings may be added to at local staff discretion.</p>
<p>Creating Undead</p>
<p>The Create <x> Undead Formal Magic spells cannot create Greater, High, or Master level undead. Undead of Greater, High, or Master level of power that are created via Formal Magic are the result of Transforms and not Create <x> Undead.</p>
<p>Pantherghasts</p>
<p>A Pantherghast will be genocidal against one race. The Pantherghast will focus on the race named by the caster. The Pantherghast may choose to roleplay with the caster before beginning the hunt. Pantherghasts seek to exterminate the hunted race.</p>
<p>Golems</p>
<p>The creation of golems follows the Creation and Summoning rules above in addition to the rules below.</p>
<p>The formal magic will create a golem and place a willing spirit and associated body designated by the caster into the golem. If the caster places a simple animal within the golem then the animal need not be willing at all, and the golem is mindless and under the control of the caster. If an intelligent spirit and body are placed within a golem then that spirit will be able to command the golem from inside and use all of the golem’s full abilities. The golem will always be recognizable as the spirit who inhabits the golem. Note that any attempt to extend the golem through other formal magic casting will fail, consuming the components. The golem will cease functioning 5 days after the first command it executes, regardless of whether or not it has been extended.</p>
<p>In addition to the components, this formal magic requires silver pieces equal to the number of body points divided by ten (round up), which will be incorporated into the body of the golem and is retrievable when the golem is destroyed. On occasion, some or all of the silver will be useless and irretrievable.</p>
<p>A golem will always be unaffected by Life and Death, and will be considered “Dead” as soon as it reaches zero body points or receives a killing blow, even if it can normally be healed. If this occurs, any spirit and body that inhabit a Golem will seek resurrection. </p>
<p>When this formal magic expires, the spirit and body will emerge without the occurrence of a death. The body will retain any battle magics that were cast upon the golem, and exhibit wounds identical to the golem’s (i.e., if the golem had a Shield Magic spell and was down by 15 points, the person has a Shield Magic spell and is down by 15 body). The person will have at least one body point. </p>
<p>If Destroy Celestial Magic is successfully cast on the golem, the spirit and body will emerge without the occurrence of a death in a  similar condition as described above.</p>
<p>Casting Rules</p>
<p>Anyone who possesses the skill Celestial Formal Magic or Earth Formal Magic may cast from formal magic scrolls of the appropriate school.</p>
<p>Formal Magic Scrolls are Indestructible unless a specific Flaw states otherwise. TT The caster(s), Formal Magic Components, Formal Magic Scroll(s), and the target of</p>
<p>the formal magic must be within a specially scribed representation on the ground. This representation must be drawn in the shape of a circle with a V. see Figure 1-1. This is known as a “fishtail,” and is not protective in any way. The representation must also contain sigils, runes, or other symbols, fetishes, implements or</p>
<p>props to indicate that a powerful magic is going to be cast. This representation is often also termed a “Circle.”</p>
<p>No Formal Magic may have a duration of longer than two years with the exception of Transforms.</p>
<p>Durations measured in-game-days are considered to include the current game-day or portion thereof – thus an effect with a duration of one game-day will expire at the beginning of the next game-day, even if that is only one hour away.</p>
<p>Casting Time</p>
<p>The standard time to cast any formal magic is five minutes. However, if a formal magic is directly harmful to a PC the casting time is one hour, though the PC may opt to allow the normal five minute casting time if they inform the marshal at beginning of the formal. This option does not apply to the Obliterate formal magic or formal magic that does not target the PC’s personal items or spirit. The decision to choose this option is wholly out of game and is not subject to any in-game coercion, review, or planning. The hour casting time is automatic upon the desire of anyone in the Circle or the Marshal. ‘Harmful’ includes destroying a ward or circle, placing a formal magic circle around a ward, using a formal magic to escape PC pursuit, etc. If the formal magic is directly harmful to an NPC the casting time is determined by the appropriate representatives of the chapter and may vary between five minutes and one hour.</p>
<p>Game Day</p>
<p>The game day is defined as 6:00 PM to 5:59 PM the following day. Some chapters end the game day at around 3 PM.</p>
<p>Item and Character Transferability</p>
<p>If any LCO components, scrolls, items, or spells are used to create a magic item, the resulting item becomes LCO. LCO stands for Local Chapter Only, which means the item cannot be taken to another NERO Chapter. This includes new spells that are being tested.</p>
<p>A PC is always aware of all formal magic effects on his or her spirit, including school, specific type, and duration as applicable.</p>
<p>A formal magic caster can not cast more than one formal magic spell at any given time.</p>
<p>Target Effect Limits</p>
<p>No target may retain more than 5 different formal magic effects simultaneously. If a target already contains 5 formal magic effects and a sixth casting is attempted, the casting will fail on that target. A single spirit or item can only retain 5 formal magic effects. Any formal spell with the duration of instantaneous is not retained, thus Obliterate, Spirit Forge, etc. do not count toward this 5 effect limit.</p>
<p>In addition, the following lasting effects are exceptions to this rule and do not count toward the five effect limit on a spirit or item: Extend Enchantment, Extend Formal Magic, Greater Extension, Investiture, Render Indestructible, Interplanar Travel, Planar Asylum, Spirit Walk, Whispering Wind, Dreamvision, Create High Horoscope, Transform to Greater Creature, Transform to High Creature, Transform to Master Creature, and Create <x> Golem.</p>
<p>The Spirit Mark and Mark Cantrips do count against the five effect limits.</p>
<p>Fishtail Requirements</p>
<p>All formal magic castings must be performed within an appropriate representation. If two or more formal magic castings are performed in the same representation at the same time they are all cast in Dark Territory.</p>
<p>Success versus Failure</p>
<p>The caster may cast a total number of levels of formal magic they possess in the appropriate school with automatic success in any one game day. A caster may cast an additional number of formal magic levels equal to the total levels of formal magic they possess in the appropriate school of magic in Dark Territory. A caster cannot cast beyond Dark Territory. A caster cannot even attempt to cast from a scroll that is higher level than the number of levels of Formal Magic skill he possesses in the appropriate school. </p>
<p>Multiple Spells Cast on a Target</p>
<p>Casters can choose to pool their formal magic ability to cast multiple Formal Magic spells onto a single target. The total number of Formal Magic they can use cannot exceed double the amount of their total unused formal for the day. This accounts for casting in Dark Territory.</p>
<p>The primary caster of any individual formal magic within a batch must be designated just prior to the start of that formal magic and that caster must be in possession of the scroll at the start of the formal magic for which he is caster.</p>
<p>All casters involved in a batch must be within the Circle for all formal magic cast within that batch. If any caster drops out between formal magic castings in a batch, the total level of formal magic allowed within the batch is recalculated. That caster is no longer required to remain in the Circle. If the total levels of formal magic already equals or exceeds the new limit then the batch terminates. No formal casters may be added to a batch once the batch begins.</p>
<p>Tags</p>
<p>Every formal magic spell in this system has a corresponding tag. Chapters are not permitted to re-issue tags issued from another chapter without National approval. Thus players may not add formal magic effects to items tagged by other chapters, since the local chapter may not re-issue the tag. Chapters may re-issue tags from their own chapter (adding new effects if appropriate), but the Transferability status of an item can never increase. This means that if an Unrestricted transfer item has an LCO Enchant cast it, the tag must be reissued as LCO. If an item has effects of varying durations, the duration of each effect must be marked. Magic item tags cannot be otherwise marked or modified other than to reduce numbers of charges or destroy the tag. Each tag for items generated using the Formal Magic system must be marked as “Indestructible” or “Destructible.”</p>
<p>Schools: A scroll must be marked as one School or the other.</p>
<p>Targets</p>
<p>The target of a formal magic must be declared at the beginning of a formal magic and may not be changed during the casting. If the target has a spirit the target will know immediately that it is the target of the formal magic and what formal magic is being cast. In the case of multiple targets, all such targets must be declared.</p>
<p>Formal magic spells that target a spirit may be refused, with the exception of Investiture/Divestiture, Create Mark / Destroy Mark and Obliterate. The Formal Marshal will inform the target that he is able to refuse this formal magic and the consequences thereof. This can be done anytime up to the end of the formal magic casting, prior to any die roll (if needed). Refusing a formal magic cast upon a spirit will cause the target to die and immediately leave to seek resurrection, regardless of whether the target is conscious.</p>
<p>Pyramids</p>
<p>Casting a pyramid based formal magic upon an item with the same pyramid based formal magic already on it (from another batch) does not increase the original pyramid. In order to increase the size of a pyramid once cast, a new pyramid larger than the first must be cast, in which case the first pyramid immediately expires and the second pyramid takes effect.</p>
<p>Gypsy Curse and Formal Magic</p>
<p>Gypsy curse may in no way affect the casting of formal magic.</p>
<p>Flaw and Backlash Effects</p>
<p>Flaws and Backlashes are identifiable in an extended celestial circle and, in most cases, lingering effects are removable by a Destroy Magic formal magic of the appropriate school. </p>
<p>Pre-Event Formal Magic Use</p>
<p>At the individual chapter’s discretion any character with the appropriate skills can cast formal magic spells at check-in as part of logistics if he wishes. In order to do so, the character turns in the required formal magic components to the production station at check-in and all scrolls that are to be used. The caster will not need to role-play the casting of the formal magic spells that are cast in this way, and he can only cast spells using auto-success. No spells may be cast in Dark Territory at logistics in this way. Special plot related formal magic castings must always be cast in-game and cannot be cast using this method. At the end of logistics, the formal magic caster will have the appropriate number of levels removed from his first day’s ability, and all scrolls that were not used up will be returned with the appropriate modifications to them. If, for any reason, the production staff person cannot complete the caster’s formal magic logistics, all scrolls and components will be returned to the formal caster and he will be forced to cast the desired spells in-game using the standard rules for formal magic casting. Spells that target an unwilling spirit, an item that automatically resists, such as a circle of power or ward, or that are “in-game” unlawful within the local region cannot be cast in this way</p>
<p>Transferability of Characters</p>
<p>Since the spirit of a player character is by default an item of unrestricted transfer, all formal magic upon the spirit of a player character is listed on that character’s card. A Local Chapter Only formal Magic on the spirit is considered in the total limit on formal magic upon a single spirit. The effect of Local Chapter Only formal magic on the spirit will be suppressed when outside the chapter of origin.</p>
<p>During the Time of Casting</p>
<p>When a scroll specifies that an action must be taken during the “time of formal casting”, then it may be done at any time during the casting of the formal magic.</p>
<p>Materials Checklist</p>
<p>Here is a complete list of what is needed to begin a Formal Magic:</p>
<p>•	The Scroll. The caster is responsible for reading and understanding the scroll.</p>
<p>•	The Formal Magic Components.</p>
<p>•	A representation in which to cast.</p>
<p>•	The Caster.</p>
<p>•	The Secondary Casters (if any).</p>
<p>•	The target(s) of the formal magic.</p>
<p>•	Marshal</p>
<p>Marshal Checklist</p>
<p>•	A white headband.</p>
<p>•	These rules, including the individual scroll descriptions.</p>
<p>•	Component Identification charts.</p>
<p>•	Formal Magic Log/Receipt Book.</p>
<p>•	Flaw & Backlash charts.</p>
<p>•	A ten sided die.</p>
<p>Finding a Marshal</p>
<p>The caster is responsible for locating the marshal. Some chapters provide a list of the available marshals at a given event to players who inquire. It is best to arrange a time in advance with a marshal. Many marshals are players too, and there is no guarantee that a request for a marshal can be granted if it is 3:00 AM, especially if arrangements haven’t been made in advance. The marshal must remain out of game for the entire duration of all formal magic castings. The marshal’s character cannot be present in any way, even as a mere onlooker. Many chapters do not allow a marshal to marshal a formal magic in a situation where his or her close friends are involved, especially for in-game associates.</p>
<p>Marshal/Caster Preparation</p>
<p>A. Determine Transferability</p>
<p>Prior to the actual start of the formal magic any players involved should be informed by the marshal if the resulting item will be of any other category besides “Unrestricted” and why. This requires an advanced examination of all materials involved in all of the formal magic castings. Since magic item categories are mostly due to out of game issues, the intent of this rule is to ensure customer satisfaction. In order to have Unrestricted transferability, all components, scrolls, and effects used must be Unrestricted. No effect that alters these rules may be in effect. If these conditions are not met the item or effect created will automatically be Local Chapter Only. </p>
<p>B. Validate Components</p>
<p>Identify the components to make sure they are correctly marked, if necessary. Insufficient components will result in the marshal stating “The Formal Magic does not begin”. If this occurs, the components are not consumed. If the spell is part of a declared batch, the marshal will notify the player that the components are insufficient before the batch begins. (Inform the player later, during step D)</p>
<p>C. Validate Scroll:</p>
<p>Read the Formal Magic Scroll. Make sure that there is a complete understanding of the scroll, and follow any special instructions on the scroll. If the scroll is Unlimited and only usable once each day, verify on the back of the scroll (or the back of the tag) that the scroll hasn’t been used today. If the physical representation of the scroll varies from the current version, then the current version must be used. The only flaws allowed upon a formal magic scroll are “Flaw: this scroll cannot be copied” or “Flaw: this scroll is destructible”.</p>
<p>During the Casting of the Formal Magic </p>
<p>D. Beginning Formal Magic</p>
<p>In order to begin the formal magic, the Caster states “Beginning Formal Magic”. Confidentially ask the Caster if they are waiving auto-success, and casting in Dark Territory. Insufficient components will result in the marshal stating “The Formal Magic does not begin”. If this occurs, the components are not consumed.</p>
<p>E. Declare Targets</p>
<p>The caster must declare the target(s) of the formal magic. The target, if a spirit, must be made aware of this by the marshal.</p>
<p>F. Act out Casting</p>
<p>The Caster(s) must indicate to any casual, secret, or imagined observers that they are performing a formal magic. This must be accomplished through various role-play methods, like constant movement or verbal action or a combination of both. The exact amount of role-play or activity is left up to local plot/rules. The movement can be as simple as constant, circular hand motion or as complicated as broad movements or the hands and/or arms, dancing movements of the entire body, or stylized movements suchas drawing of symbols or lighting candles or incense. Verbal action would include litany speech, question and reply, chanting, or recitation in a “magical language”. The caster may not engage in regular conversation. </p>
<p>Any method chosen by the caster must make use of the components and the scroll.</p>
<p>Poor performance on the role-playing aspect of the formal magic casting will cause the marshal to issue a warning. After receiving two such warnings, the third occurrence of poor performance will result in automatic failure of the formal magic.</p>
<p>G. Monitor for Backlash:</p>
<p>The formal magic automatically backlashes under the following conditions:</p>
<p>•	Any caster is struck with a ranged attack, Disrupted, takes body damage or becomes unconscious.</p>
<p>•	If any caster cannot speak, move their hands, or easily be in a position from which they could see the formal magic scroll even if they are not currently looking at it. </p>
<p>•	If any caster uses any other game skill other than those required by the formal magic scroll, Read/Write,,Wear Extra Armor, or Dexterity Armor.</p>
<p>•	If any caster ceases casting the formal magic, voluntarily or involuntarily. </p>
<p>•	The formal magic components, formal magic scroll, or any target is damaged (Shattered, Destroyed, affected by an Explosive Trap, or numerical damage), destroyed, dies, becomes unusable, or leaves the fishtail.Anything that leaves the circle is always affected by the backlash as if it were still inside the circle.</p>
<p>H. Determine the Outcome</p>
<p>If the formal magic casting is completed, the Caster must roll the die if required to do so see Table 1-1 and allow all casters to see the results. If the caster has chosen Autosuccess then no roll is necessary. Each caster knows the results of the formal magic. The marshal will record the results in the Formal Magic Logbook. If the caster(s) wish(es) to perform more formal magics, then the Marshal should not write any tags until it is convenient. Perform the following additional instructions:</p>
<p>Success: The formal magic completed properly; follow the instructions on the Scroll.</p>
<p>Flaw: The formal magic completed, but with skewed results. Turn to the “Flaw Table” and determine the results. If one of the results indicates that any of the components or the scroll is not consumed, then return the appropriate items and indicate the flaw caused these items to not be consumed in the formal magic log. If the result indicates that the target should receive an additional formal magic effect and the target is at the limit of effects it can hold, the additional effect will fail.</p>
<p>Failure: The formal magic was a complete failure, resulting in no magical effects.</p>
<p>Backlash: The formal magic was a complete failure, and generated a very powerful magical side effect. Turn to the “Backlash Table” and determine the results and apply them as directed.</p>
<p>After Casting the Formal Magic</p>
<p>I. Casting Completes</p>
<p>At this time, the Marshal should: </p>
<p>• Collect all components that were expended in the casting.</p>
<p>• Either mark Limited (times-ever) Scrolls accordingly or collect them on the last use.</p>
<p>• Indicate the casting of this formal magic</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Formal Magic Cantrips</p>
<p>For a player to cast a Cantrip he/she must have the skill earth Formal Magic or celestial Formal Magic.  A player may cast one Cantrip of their school of magic per day for each level of formal magic they possess. The full list of Cantrips, their effects, andcomponents costs is available at www.nerolarp.com.</p>
<p>Cantrip Tome</p>
<p>In order to cast a Cantrip the player must be carrying a Cantrip tome which contains the Cantrip they wish to cast.  Cantrip tomes are in-game objects that must be acquired in-game.  The phys-rep for a Cantrip tome must be at least 6” x 4”.  The tome is governed by the rules defined in th enchant cantrip tome Cantrip. </p>
<p>Cantrip Pages</p>
<p>In addition to Cantrip tomes, there are also Cantrip pages.  Cantrip pages function like Cantrip tomes but are of one use only and will only contain a single Cantrip.  A Cantrip Page must be the same size as a celestial scroll. To cast from a Cantrip Page, the caster must read and touch a packet to the Page.CastingTo cast a Cantrip the player must say the proper incant for the Cantrip and physically break or tear the number of level one components designated for that particular Cantrip (0, 1, or 2) to gain the power for the Cantrip.  When casting a Cantrip with 0 component cost there need not be a “tearing” motion.  Breaking or tearing a single level two component will power a Cantrip which takes 2 components or two Cantrips which take 1 component cast one immediately after another.  Breaking or tearing a level four component will power two Cantrips which take 2 components or four Cantrips which take 1 component cast one immediately after the other.   The components must be broken or torn within 10 seconds of finishing the incant.  The components used for a Cantrip may only be unrestricted NERO components or local to the chapter in which the Cantrip is being cast.  The components must be identifiable by the chapter which they are used in at the time of the casting, and they may not be SR components. Components are to be turned into a marshal after the casting of any Cantrip.  The components will be checked at this time. </p>
<p>Cantrips are cast on the fly for any Cantrip in the carried tome(s).  Cantrips do not require a fishtail to cast.  Cantrips are never thrown at an opponent in the manner of battle magic, but they may allow the caster to throw a packet or series of packets with a defined effect (e.g.10 elemental fire”).  Casting a Cantrip is subject to Spell Disruption.  No other skill or item may be used from the point when the incant is started till the point when the components are snapped or torn or the Cantrip will fail and the components are still consumed.</p>
<p>A Cantrip may never be extended in any manner or placed into an item in the manner of an enchantMent, expanDeD enchantMent, etc.  A Cantrip or the effect of aCantrip may never be spellstored.</p>
<p>The statement “dies and requires a life spell” refers to any time the character is dead whether they receive a life spell or not, resurrect, regenerate, revives through a manner other than a life spell, or is not affectedby life.</p>
<p>There are five types of Cantrip: </p>
<p>1. Personal:  These Cantrips cause an effectupon the caster of the Cantrip.  They may not be placed on another nor may they be transferred.  For the effect of a personalCantrip to remain the PC must retain the skill Formal Magic <school>.  If they lose the skill in any manner the Cantrip will cease functioning.  If they still possess the skill but may not use e.g. are tainted or drained they do not lose any Cantrips upon them.  In addition they must retain the Cantrip Tome with the Cantrip they placed upon themselves.  Losing possession of the Tome even to allow another to cast a Cantrip from the tome will negate any current personal Cantrips. </p>
<p>2. Item:  These Cantrips are only cast on an item with no spirit. </p>
<p>3. Spirit:  These Cantrips are only cast on a recipient with a spirit.  They may not be thrown but must be touch cast in a NERO legal manner by being touched with a packet.  If the target is not willing, the Cantrip fails. </p>
<p>4. Broad:  These Cantrips affect a broadcategory in the estate/military system of NERO and are usually never used in play during an event.  On occasion plot may define specific uses of these Cantrips during actual play such as weakening a building under siege with Weaken Defense but they may NEVER directly affect PCs or NPCs in play. </p>
<p>5. Offensive:  These Cantrips give the caster the ability to directly attack opponents andthus their effect would be stopped by theappropriate normal spell defenses.</p>
<p>Cantrips may have the following durations:</p>
<p>Hour:  One Hour  </p>
<p>Day:   One Day, until the next Standard Reset or game end.  whichever occurs first </p>
<p>Instant:  Immediate and not lasting, the effect on another may last.</p>
<p>Year:  Until removed by in-game methods or 1 year passes.</p>
<p>Concentration:  The caster must maintain concentration to keep this Cantrip going.</p>
<p>Invoked:  When an invoked Cantrip is cast the caster will receive 5 charges of the effectin the appropriate school of formal magic.  Using the effect uses one charge. An effect can be used against a single opponent for a maximum of 5 minutes or line of sight.  All unused charges expire at the next tag reset.  Multiple charges may be used against multiple opponents at the same time.  The caster must state “I Invoke <Cantrip name> against you” to the opponent it is being used against so that the opponent can hear it.  This is an in-game statement and will not work if the Caster is silenced.</p>
<p>2 Year:  Until removed by in-game methods or 2 years passes. Unless otherwise indicated, the effect of any Cantrip with the duration of Day is lost if the target requires a life spell.</p>
<p>