<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Root xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/"><body>
<p>Chapter 8: Atmosphere</p>
<p>Role-Playing</p>
<p>Role-playing requires you to create a new persona.</p>
<p>You should try to think, feel, move and act like your character. (Keep in mind as you read this that you are the player; the persona you adopt is the character.)</p>
<p>It is up to you to decide what your character will say and how your character will act. Imagine yourself actually being the character you have created, and act as your character would. NERO is a fantasy role-playing game, based in a pseudo-medieval era. Your character is living in a world with swords, sorcery, monsters, and magic; act accordingly.</p>
<p>You may design a character that is like yourself or you can be someone totally unlike yourself, and develop a new perspective on the world. You can create a character that does things you would like to do, but can never work up the nerve to try. You can be a fierce warrior, a sneaky thief, or a crafty mage.</p>
<p>Many people are more comfortable creating a character that is more like themselves. Others prefer to play a persona completely opposite. You can do whatever you want (within the rules, of course).</p>
<p>Please remember to be considerate of the other players. Abusing other characters could be going too far, even if it makes sense for your character concept. Remember that even if an action is "in character" you, as the player, bear full responsibility for the effects it has on the other players. After all, you created your character in the first place. Be sure to read "Code of Conduct" on page 100 for more guidelines.</p>
<p>This concept also applies to such things as character insanity (temporary or otherwise) as an excuse for crimes. If you feel your character would snap for some reason, feel free to do so; however, you must be willing to have your character face the consequences or be able to fast-talk your way out of the situation. </p>
<p>The atmosphere of our game depends on the players staying in character. This means talking and thinking only as your character would. Avoid discussions of modern day events and topics. If your character cannot read, then do not read anything. If your character has never seen the local nobility, then you shouldn't recognize them. Do what your character would do. With everyone doing their best to support the atmosphere, you will be surprised at how easy it becomes to stay in your character persona with just a bit of initial effort.</p>
<p>Darkvision and Low-Light vision</p>
<p>There is no such thing as Darkvision or Low-Light vision in the NERO world. Elves, Dwarves, Hoblings and the like do not get any special visual ability.</p>
<p>Whatever you the player can see is what your character can see.</p>
<p>Languages</p>
<p>If you wish to be able to speak another language in character, then you must actually learn it! When you wish to talk in the other language, then you must talk in the other language! This is to prevent someone from overhearing you talk in English pretending that it is another language only to have you say "You didn't understand that; it's in another language."</p>
<p>You do not have to spend any Build Points to learn another language, you just have to find someone who knows the language and then learn it. Keep in mind that in the NERO world, all PC races speak a common language (represented with English) and any other languages associated with those races are dead languages similar to Latin in the modern world.</p>
<p>This concept also applies to such things as character insanity (temporary or otherwise) as an excuse for crimes. If you feel your character would snap for some reason, feel free to do so, but you must be willing to have your character face the consequences or be able to fast-talk your way out of the situation.</p>
<p>The atmosphere of our game depends on the players staying in character. This means talking and thinking only as your character would. Avoid discussions of modern day events and topics. If your character cannot read, then do not read anything. If your character has never seen the local nobility, then you shouldn't recognize them. Do what your character would do. With everyone doing their best to support the atmosphere, you will be surprised at how easy it becomes to stay in your character persona with just a bit of initial effort.</p>
<p>Costumes</p>
<p>A costume is an easy way to help you establish the personality of your character and to stay "in character." Once you look the part, it doesn't take much to become the part. You can create a simple costume for very little money, and can slowly add to it until you have a costume of which you can be proud. </p>
<p>Your costume need not be elaborate. A simple tabard or tunic with a pair of pants (even sweatpants) or a long skirt will be enough to help you play the role. A long shirt belted around the waist works fine. The selection of costume pieces also helps you to define your character's likes and dislikes.</p>
<p>Your costume should be practical as well as adding to the atmosphere. Make sure you can wear it for long periods in the outdoors. If you plan on doing a lot of fighting and running around in the woods, you probably shouldn't wear a silk shirt.</p>
<p>Washable fabrics are best as your costume will see some heavy use. Try to avoid any obvious anachronisms such as zippers, Velcro, jeans, baseball caps, printed t-shirts, watches, and sneakers. Eyeglasses are all right (and have in fact been around since the 13th century).</p>
<p>Minimum Costuming Requirements: You must make at least an attempt at a costume. If other players see you walking around dressed in jeans and a t-shirt, wearing a baseball cap and carrying a sword, they will probably assume you are not in-game and will ignore you. Marshals will warn you and tell you that you are not in-game. Quite often, there are merchants at NERO events who will sell pre-made costumes or custom-make costumes for you. Please do not use crosses, pentacles, and other similar religious symbols. NERO tries not to insult anyone's religious beliefs and we do not wish to do so accidentally. Personal religious symbols are acceptable, but should not be displayed. </p>
<p>Disguises</p>
<p>You are not allowed to disguise your character using any sort of makeup to change your appearance, since makeup is the only way that NERO players can represent another race or physical characteristics</p>
<p>that the players themselves do not have. If you wish to have your character travel incognito, you must use costume and mannerisms.</p>
<p>After all, if the world of Tyrra really existed and there really were Elves and Orcs and Hoblings, you would be able to easily distinguish between a real Dark Elf and someone disguised as a Dark Elf wearing fake ears and face paint.</p>
<p>Certain distinguishing characteristics of a race can never be changed. If you are a Barbarian, you must dress in furs and leathers and talk in a barbaric fashion. If you are a Biata, you can't shave off your eyebrows. If you are a Gypsy, you must speak with a Gypsy accent. </p>
<p>You are allowed to disguise yourself in limited ways, for example, an Elf can wear a hat to hide his ears or a Drae can wear a hood to cover her face. You can wear a mask over your face, provided it is a Zorro-type of mask and not a monster mask.</p>
<p>Even with these changes, if you are asked out-of-game if you look like your character, you must answer yes so that other players will not think that you are playing an NPC.</p>
<p>Taking Damage</p>
<p>When your character is involved in combat, you should role-play the damage you take! React to the axe cut in your thigh. Say "ouch!" when you take a hit. If someone does enough damage to kill you, then fall down and die. This adds greatly to the enjoyment of the game for all. Just standing there saying "Well, I guess I'm dead" is unimaginative and detracts from the feel everyone is trying to generate of life in another place. Don't overact the scene, just grunt and fall. Go ahead and stagger a little to avoid landing on a boulder.</p>
<p>Magical Effects</p>
<p>In fantasy games, magic exists, and can have devastating effects. You should treat the magic in NERO the same way your character should act accordingly. If you get hit with a Lightning Bolt spell, then act as if you have been hit with a bolt of lightning! This adds to the atmosphere of the game.</p>
<p>Playing Fair</p>
<p>The NERO Game System relies on honesty, and as such, a dishonest player will find it a simple matter to cheat. NERO has set out to design a game that can work without constant supervision. This can be a great asset in terms of ease of play and flexibility, but it has a trade-off in potential abuse. If you cheat, other players will find out eventually, and then no one will want to interact with you. If you do not count hits against you, then soon those you face will stop counting your hits against them. </p>
<p>When word of a cheater's actions gets back to NERO, and it will, then we will remove the offending player from the game, pending investigation. If someone seems to have extraordinary powers, or you suspect they are confused about their skills or are cheating then you should calmly approach a marshal with your concerns at a later time.</p>
<p>Marshals</p>
<p>Marshals in our game are identified at the start of each event during Opening Ceremonies. They may also carry identification cards. If you have a rules question, need an official to witness an action, or have any other problem, you may ask one of the Marshals.</p>
<p>. Anachronisms</p>
<p>Some anachronisms cannot be avoided. However, NERO makes every attempt to avoid modern trappings whenever possible. Please, no Snoopy shields, smiley face banners or other silliness (and keep the Monty Python bits to a minimum). Do not use cell phones, and keep your soda cans and candy wrappers in your cabin!</p>
<p>Gadgets</p>
<p>You are not allowed to use modern electronic gadgetry such as infrared seeing devices, electronic listening devices, or any other technological anachronistic mechanism. In effect, by using these things, it's as if you have a powerful magical item and it would hardly be fair to the rest of the players.</p>
<p>Justifying Anachronisms</p>
<p>In order for the NERO world of Tyrra to function more smoothly, we have allowed certain anachronisms to exist in our medieval society.</p>
<p>Eyeglasses</p>
<p>Although eyeglasses did exist in medieval times, they were not available to most people and were bulky and easily broken. On Tyrra, many people wear glasses. For safety reasons you are never allowed to remove a player's glasses in order to handicap that person.</p>
<p>Matches</p>
<p>Matches exist in the world of NERO so that you do not have to bring flint and tinder with you everywhere. (If you wish to bring flint and tinder with you to add to the atmosphere of the game, then we will be very happy.) Try to avoid using lighters, but if nothing else is available, they can be used to represent flint and steel.</p>
<p>Bathrooms</p>
<p>The showers and toilets are out of game for safety and privacy purposes, but characters can make references to them as they actually exist, after all, the ancient Romans had indoor plumbing long before the middle ages began. In the world of NERO, only the very richest homes and inns have indoor plumbing. One nice thing about Tyrra as opposed to medieval Earth is that people on Tyrra bathe more often.</p>
<p>Clocks and Watches</p>
<p>Clocks exist in our game but they are very expensive! Perhaps there is one clock per town, probably placed in a high tower. Clocks operate through a series of levers and springs, no electricity of course.</p>
<p>Timepieces include all clocks, watches and small winding pocket watches as well.</p>
<p>Timepieces, if brought by a player, can be used when on a timed module.</p>
<p>Time</p>
<p>In the world of NERO, time passes in-game at the same rate as it does out-of-game. If a month has passed between NERO events, then a month has passed in the world of Tyrra.</p>
<p>To figure out the NERO year, simply remove the first two digits of the current mundane year and replace them with a "6" so that 2005 becomes 605. This in no way is meant to imply that our games take place in a world similar to Earth's seventh century.</p>
<p>Discrimination</p>
<p>What NERO is attempting to do is create the days of legend as we would have liked them to be, not as they really were. That means our culture is considerably more egalitarian than a real medieval society. No discrimination is allowed against players in a NERO game. You cannot be denied a position as a noble, a member of the army or any other NERO-sponsored group on the basis of race, religion, gender, age, sexual orientation, or country of origin. However, this does not mean that the world of NERO is an egalitarian paradise. There are countries and people who do discriminate in-game. </p>
<p>Although you the player are not allowed to discriminate, your character can discriminate on the in-game basis of matters of players' choice.</p>
<p>For example, Kildor the fighter hates all dwarves. He thinks they are the lowest form of life (no pun intended) and he kills them whenever he gets the chance. Players who have dwarven characters that are killed by him cannot claim that they are being discriminated against because they chose to play dwarf characters. </p>
<p>It is very important that all players try to distinguish between in-game prejudices and out-of-game prejudices. It is better to steer clear of the issue altogether if possible.</p>
<p>Science</p>
<p>How advanced is science in NERO? Well, scholars are aware that the planet Tyrra is not the center of the solar system and that the world is not flat. They are also aware of the existence of real elements (as opposed to the 'traditional' magical elements of Earth, Air, Water and Fire) and there is even a Periodic Table of the Elements which lists all twelve elements known. Lenses for glasses and telescopes are in existence but are generally of poor quality. There are compasses and navigational materials for traveling but PC's aren't allowed to bring and use them.</p>
<p>Scientific evolution on Tyrra has been stunted by the prevalence of magic. Tyrran science is right at the verge of the Renaissance, on the tail end of the Dark Ages, where astrology and magic are considered scientific facts.</p>
<p>Consider NERO's science to be right at the verge of the renaissance, on the tail end of the Dark Ages.</p>
<p>Magic</p>
<p>Although magicians, can perform all sorts of amazing feats, we have to limit them because of real world difficulties. For example, we do not have an invisibility spell because it is almost impossible to pretend you "don't see" someone. We also have no flying spells, growing spells, polymorph spells or any other unusual spells that cannot be performed or easily imagined out-of-game. </p>
<p>We once had a Scry spell (now available in very limited quantities as an Interplanar Conduit formal magic) which was removed for its unplayability, we could not answer questions that the spell would have been able to answer ("Where did I put my hat?" "Where will the Baron be tomorrow at 2 p.m.?" "Who in town is thinking about killing me?")</p>
<p>A Truth spell was also removed for much the same reason, how can we force players (not characters) to tell the truth? And (metaphysically speaking) what is truth, anyway? No effect can force a PC to tell the truth.</p>
<p>Healing</p>
<p>Why need anyone ever suffer if there are healing spells? Well, the answer is that healing spells cannot do everything. If you are damaged (or dead) and you are then magically healed to your maximum (or resurrected), then you are returned to the state your body was in before the damage was taken. If you had a limp before you were healed, you still have a limp. If you were dying of old age, then you are still dying of old age. How do we explain limps, handicaps, and scars? One explanation is that it's all psychological.</p>
<p>If you were injured long ago and healed naturally, gaining a scar, then you are psychologically aware of the scar and when resurrected, it will still be there because your mind accepts you that way.</p>
<p>Another explanation is that the spells or resurrection heals you up to the state you were in last before you took any recent damage.</p>
<p>In other words, if your body healed normally after a battle and you ended up with scars, any future healing would not correct that old injury. You can decide which of these two in-game explanations works for you.</p>
<p>A Cure Disease spell will only cure magically caused diseases. It will not cure cancer, get rid of athlete's feet, or hide your bald spot.</p>
<p>This gives some players fun at role-playing frustrations of being sick: "You mean they can bring me back to life after dying but they can't cure the common cold?!!"</p>
<p>Religion</p>
<p>Although religion played a very large part in medieval society, we do not allow it in-game because we do not wish to accidentally insult anyone's beliefs. Please do not prominently display any religious symbols or use them in your costume design nor use any religious title in your character's name. Always avoid references to gods or demons or religious rituals.</p>
<p>Words and Language</p>
<p>Although technically the characters in the world of NERO are speaking some unusual fantasy language, we have thoughtfully translated these words into English for you.</p>
<p>Although it would be fun to have fantasy names for the months, days of the week, planets and other common things, it would be very confusing to play the game that way, especially for players who only attend an event or two a year. Therefore, we stick with the traditional words used in modern English.</p>
<p>We do not use the old English "thee" or "thou" or other Shakespearian era vocabulary. In game, we state that we once used terminology like that but language has evolved. You may note that certain old documents such as the Code of Chivalry may still be written in that style. There may also be some countries or cultures where it is still used.</p>
<p>Foreign and racial in-game languages exist in NERO but you must actually learn them. See the section on "Languages" in the chapter on Miscellaneous Rules for more information.</p>
<p>The Society of NERO</p>
<p>NERO games take place on the planet known as "Tyrra" in most languages. Coincidentally, it is a planet not unlike Earth in climate and topography! NERO is trying to create and represent a fantasy world, based primarily on medieval Europe. This is not to say that your character should be limited by this; you may choose to play a character based on medieval China or ancient Egypt. </p>
<p>Government</p>
<p>Our present-day concept of democracy is a very foreign idea to Tyrrans. There may be some countries that have a very limited form of democracy, for example, all the nobles can vote on certain issues but that is the extent of it. Even peasants who revolt against unfair kings never think to replace the kingdom with democracy, but only with a fairer monarch or other ruling elite. Here's how it works:</p>
<p>The kingdom functions as a feudal society. This means that there is a strongly observed hierarchy. It is not a system of equality of all people. It is a system of duty to one's superior in return for protection and support.</p>
<p>The king owns all of the lands and properties within the kingdom. The king chooses people to administer the majority of these holdings in his name. These people are vassals of the king. Each of these people administer the land as if they were their own and in return they swear that they will support the king, provide troops in time of war, collect taxes, and meet any other duties the king expects of them. These vassals are called dukes. In turn each of these people appoints vassals of their own, called counts and barons. Again, Oaths of Fealty bind the duke with his vassals. Further, counts and barons may assign areas of land to vassals of their own, called knights and lords.</p>
<p>Every person in the preceding group is collectively known as a "noble." Any person who is not a noble is a commoner. They are the fiber of society, performing the day to day work. They are the farmers, craftsman, healers, soldiers, fisherman, and etcetera. Just because they are commoners does not mean that they are cattle to be controlled by nobles. Somewhere between the nobles and the commoners are the adventurers. Adventurers get respect because of their deeds and the fact that they usually have a bit of money. Since NERO is an epic fantasy game, most of our players are nobles or adventurers, not commoners. Although a real medieval society would have many commoners tending fields, cleaning stables, and doing the other day to day menial tasks that must be performed, no player wants to play such a role. For game purposes, assume they are out there somewhere. Every once in a while you might meet a few NPCs playing these parts who have information for you.</p>
<p>Each noble owes certain responsibilities to commoners upon their lands. In return for part of the profits of the commoners' labors, the noble who governs the land is expected to protect them from crime, invasion, and help them when they need it. The noble is expected to provide leadership, an example of proper behavior, and to improve the lot of his or her peasants over time.</p>
<p>The commoners' responsibility is to be willing to pay fair taxes, join the militia in time of need, help their lord administer justice by reporting crimes and providing testimony, defend their lord's name, and address and treat nobles with the respect they are due.</p>
<p>Societal Conventions</p>
<p>These "laws" form the basic customs of the people and are followed by all members of the society, from the highest noble to the lowest peasant. These laws are so ingrained in the society that they are rarely challenged. Anyone found to have violated these laws should be shunned by all as a villain and an untrustworthy social deviant.</p>
<p>Hospitality: Any person who is invited into your home or holdings and accepts your hospitality will be treated as a guest with the respect due a person of their class and station. This person will be protected from all harm by you and all members of your household. By accepting your hospitality, the guest also agrees to give respect where it is due and not take advantage of your goodwill.</p>
<p>Loyalty: Any person who swears fealty to you as their liege will obey you and be loyal to you and in turn you will support them give them your protection.</p>
<p>Kinship: Any member of your family must be loyal to you and you must be loyal to them. Because they are family they are worthy of your trust.</p>
<p>Honor: Each individual is considered to be able to defend their honor by the honorable use of arms or magic. This type of activity is governed by a set of rules that differs substantially between commoners and nobles.</p>
<p>The hierarchy of a medieval society is based upon title and rank within that society. The higher your rank, the more authority and respect you command.</p>
<p>In the NERO world, noble title is sometimes inherited and sometimes earned. Depending on circumstance, then, either the King or Queen could be the power. The husband or wife of the noble in power either has a decision making power equal to or just under that of the noble themselves (providing that person grants that power), or has little to do with governing at all, being just a figurehead.</p>
<p>Titles and Rankings</p>
<p>King/Queen</p>
<p>Theirs is the final word on all matters and is literally the law. Once the Royal mind is made up, it goes without question. They would be addressed as Your Majesty or Your Royal Majesty.</p>
<p>Crown Prince/Crown Princess</p>
<p>This is the eldest child of the monarch who will inherit the crown upon the death of the parent or whoever has been designated as heir apparent to the throne by the sovereign ruler. They are addressed as Your Royal Highness.</p>
<p>Prince/Princess</p>
<p>These are the children of the King and Queen who are not designated heirs (usually all but the first born). They are addressed as Your Highness.</p>
<p>Duke/Duchess</p>
<p>This is a title of nobility inherited or granted by the King that earns respect and sovereignty over a portion of the King's lands (which can then be divided among Counts and/or Barons). They are addressed as Your Grace. </p>
<p>Count/Countess</p>
<p>This title is inherited or granted by a Duke or King and earns respect from Barons, Knights, guards, Lords and commoners. They have sovereignty over a portion of the King's lands which can then be divided among Barons. They are addressed as My Lord Count or My Lady Countess.</p>
<p>Viscount/Viscountess</p>
<p>This title is usually a title of honor given to a nobleperson. It does not carry any lands. They are addressed as Your Excellency.</p>
<p>Baron/Baroness</p>
<p>This title is inherited or granted by a Count, Duke, or King. It commands respect from commoners, guards, Knights, Lords, and has sovereignty over a portion of a Count's (or Duke's) lands. They are addressed as My Lord Baron or My Lady Baroness, or in some places as Good Sir Baron or Good Dame Baroness.</p>
<p>Seneschal</p>
<p>This is a title of someone who functions as the secretary to the holder of a noble title. He or she may perform justice or execute decisions in the name of their liege. In the absence of the liege, they have the power of the liege. They are granted estates, though often they reside on a portion of their liege's estate. They are addressed as My Lord Seneschal or My Lady Seneschal.</p>
<p>Knight</p>
<p>A Knight is a person granted the right to bear arms and distribute justice in the name of a liege or to carry the standard of their liege, and to own an estate. A Knight commands respect from other Knights, Lords/Ladies, guards, and commoners. Some knights are Paladins. These are the knights whose dedication to the Code of Chivalry is so great that their liege has given them this honorary title. Paladins have no special powers except when conducting trials of nobility. They are addressed as Good Sir Knight or Good Dame Knight.</p>
<p>Lord/Lady</p>
<p>A Lord or Lady is usually the spouse or child of a noble. They deserve respect as a noble but cannot perform any noble duties nor own an estate. In some places, a Lord or Lady is equivalent to a knight and can hold all of the same powers as a knight. They are addressed as Your Lordship or Your Ladyship.</p>
<p>Magistrate</p>
<p>Magistrates are granted the right to try commoners and dispense justice in the lands of their liege. They do not have the power to make laws nor do they have any power outside of their liege's lands. Their decisions can be overruled by any noble of their liege's land, but such an act is usually extreme in nature and is subject to review. Although probably not noble, they are treated with respect due a noble and are addressed as My Lord Magistrate or My Lady Magistrate.</p>
<p>Guildmaster/Guildmistress</p>
<p>Though not a noble title, the head of a chartered Healers' Guild or Mages' Guild is often accorded the same respect as a knight. They are addressed as Guildmaster or Guildmistress.</p>
<p>Squire</p>
<p>A squire is a knight in training. Although they hold no power and are not considered nobility, they are treated with respect by guards and commoners. They are addressed as Squire.</p>
<p>Sheriff</p>
<p>The Sheriff is appointed by the Magistrate and is responsible for appointing and maintaining the Town Guard. They are addressed as M'Lord M'Lady, or Sheriff.</p>
<p>Guard</p>
<p>A guard is a person granted the right to uphold the laws and distribute settlements to minor disputes within the lands and laws of their immediate liege only. They would command respect from commoners. They are addressed as M'Lord, M'Lady, or Guard. </p>
<p>Merchant</p>
<p>A merchant is an upper class or wealthy commoner who may or may not be respected or paid attention to by the lower ranking nobles and Knights, but who would command the respect of the other commoners. Often they can be minor land owners if this is granted by their liege. They are addressed as Good Merchant, or M'Lord or M'Lady. </p>
<p>Common Townsfolk</p>
<p>These are people who live within a town, anyone from a tradesman to a clerk. They do not own land. They are addressed as Goodman or Goodwife.</p>
<p>Special Cases</p>
<p>Adventurer</p>
<p>While not quite the same status as common townsfolk, adventurers are nonetheless also not of rank equal to nobility. They are rarely land owners. They owe respect to anyone with the rank of guard or higher.</p>
<p>Mage</p>
<p>The mage is generally considered the same as a merchant (although his or her apprentice may not be), but unless they are appointed to or inherit a title, they are not nobility. If not in anyone's service, yet a member of a recognized guild, they should be accorded the same respect as a merchant. If acting on their own, they should be treated properly as any other commoner would be for the situation. For example, if this is reputed to be a powerful independent mage, "Begone wretch" may not be entirely appropriate.</p>
<p>Healer</p>
<p>Healers are treated like mages with appropriate respect due a member of the healing profession (in case you ever expect to be injured).</p>
<p>Thieves</p>
<p>Thieves are commoners unless someone has granted them a title of some sort. (We're sure the thieves out there will find plenty of ways to exact revenge for this obviously gross injustice. . .)</p>
<p>Noble Powers</p>
<p>Nobility carries with it power and responsibility. Beside showing respect to those who are above you in the feudal hierarchy, you must also obey them. Commoners owe respect to nobles because nobles protect them from marauding monsters, ensure that there is a flowing economy, strengthen the land's ties with the throne, and generally maintain a status quo which keeps the citizenry a few steps away</p>
<p>from anarchy. Because of all this hard work, if a noble gives a commoner an order, that person is obligated to obey it. Although there is no Oath of Fealty, the relation is implied because of what the noble does for the commoner.</p>
<p>Does that mean that the nobles have free reign over the commoners? Of course not. A noble who orders commoners to perform manual labor or pushes them about for no reason places himself or herself at risk of losing his or her title. The noble's lieges are obligated to investigate any charges of wrongdoing by the nobility even if reported to them by a commoner. </p>
<p>In some ways, squires fit into the same category as commoners except that they have sworn an Oath of Fealty to a noble. That squire's oath is also sworn to any person the noble has an oath to as well. Therefore, if Squire Michael swears an oath to Dame Linda, he has implied oaths to Linda's liege, Baroness Jora, and to her liege, Duke Padsworth. And of course, all oaths are sworn to the King or Queen. </p>
<p>If someone higher than you on the chain of command gives you an order, you are required to obey it, provided that the order is not contradictory to orders already issued you by your liege. Suppose Michael becomes a knight in Baroness Jora's court. </p>
<p>If Baron Higgin comes along and gives Michael an order, does he have to obey it? Yes, but only if it is not contradictory to a previous order given by his liege Baroness Jora. This can be somewhat confusing and does present the same problems posed by nobles ordering commoners around, but it is also self-correcting in the same fashion. </p>
<p>If Baron Higgin orders Sir Michael to accompany him on a rescue mission, Michael must obey. If Baroness Jora had previously ordered him to await the arrival of a visiting dignitary then he could refuse to follow Baron Higgin's orders explaining, of course, that his liege had already given him an important task. If Baroness Jora had given him no specific task, then he would have to obey.</p>
<p>If Baron Higgin had ordered Sir Michael to kill a commoner standing nearby, he would also have to obey. Although no explanation was given, and this seems like a heinous crime, the knight would be required to follow the command. </p>
<p>Suppose the commoner was really an evil doppelganger. Baron Higgin's quick thinking would have saved the day. Had the knight argued with the Baron, the villain might have been able to escape.</p>
<p>By ordering someone to do something, a noble takes a great risk. If a noble gives an order, then that noble takes full responsibility for the results of that order.</p>
<p>In the example above, if the commoner proved to be nothing more than an ordinary citizen, Baron Higgin would be guilty of murder even though he himself did not perform the action, and Sir Michael would be found innocent. Baron Higgin would certainly lose his title and be subjected to the laws of the region as well. </p>
<p>Nobles understand that the power to command others must be used very carefully. Much thought must be given before issuing an order. This is why most nobles will not issue orders to those outside of their immediate court. </p>
<p>A good example of this chain of command can be found in the modern day army of nearly any country in the world. A private who is a member of Company D must still obey orders given to him or her from a sergeant from Company B. It is assumed that this power will not be abused or misused. While it's true that noble courts are not military organizations, they operate using a chain of command structure upon which modern day conventions are based. </p>
<p>This also applies to dispensing justice. Not every nobleperson can act as judge and jury in every instance. Generally speaking, you may only dispense justice upon those who are under you in the chain of command. A knight can only decide cases that result from actions taken on his or her lands. Visiting nobles should always defer to the owner or administrator of the local lands. This overlaps a bit of course: a knight's lands are also the lands of all of the knight's lieges.</p>
<p>Any person of any rank giving orders or dispensing justice among the commoners must be certain beforehand that their superiors would agree with both their reasoning and the severity of the punishment. If they indiscriminately or falsely submit a commoner to punishment then their superiors should see to it that they receive punishment equal to that enacted against the person in question.</p>
<p>There are consequences for every action. </p>
<p>To summarize, all commoners must obey nobles of any rank. </p>
<p>Nobles must obey the orders of nobles of a higher rank than themselves provided those orders are not contradictory to the ones given them by their liege lord. It is incumbent on nobles to watch those under them to make sure this is not abused. In addition, nobles may dispense justice for crimes committed on their lands only.</p>
<p>General Courtesy</p>
<p>For the most part, showing respect for someone of a higher rank than yourself is very similar to showing respect for persons of importance in modern society. The average person on the street would not be able to walk in and start chatting with the President any more than your character should be able to chat with the King. Just like in modern society, in order to speak with any important person, you have to run through a lot of red tape. </p>
<p>For example: Say Amilio the Stout wanted an audience with the King because he thought the monsters just outside of his town were killing more than their fair share of townsfolk every Saturday night. </p>
<p>He would, if following proper channels, take the case to a local Baronial guard or to the Baronial Seneschal if one was available. If neither of these were available to listen to the problem, he could even try approaching one of the Baronial knights who may be willing to listen. Should our hero's pleas still go ignored or his request to speak to the King not considered important, he might consider taking his case to the local mage or healers' guild representative to plea his case for him. They might command more attention. That person would approach the Baron and request the Baron to listen to Amilio's problem. If the Baron listens, he may then elect to </p>
<p>(1) solve the problem himself;</p>
<p>(2) offer to take the problem to the Duke himself;</p>
<p>(3) decide that the problem is better left alone for now and thank</p>
<p>Amilio for his concern; or</p>
<p>(4) petition for an audience with his liege (probably a Count or Duke) on behalf of Amilio.</p>
<p>If Amilio is the reasonable sort who speaks politely (and nicely), the Baron may recommend that Amilio present his case himself. At this point, Amilio may find himself talking to his Count (who may go through the same decision process) or may find himself with an audience with the Duke himself.</p>
<p>For the most part, no commoner will generally find themselves in an audience with the King unless the King is feeling generous. Adventurers and members of important guilds will be treated with slightly more respect than the average commoner in these situations.</p>
<p>As far as everyday courtesy goes, when a person of noble ranking passes you on the street and their rank is higher on the food chain than yours, you should bow slightly. If a contingent of guards or knights is coming down the road, you give them the right of way.</p>
<p>When addressing another person, and you are uncertain of their station or rank, you should address them as "M'Lord or M'Lady." This ensures that everyone receives at least common respect. More importantly, it adds to the atmosphere of the game as a whole.</p>
<p>Noble Etiquette</p>
<p>Among the nobility, many ranks give your character the right to dispense justice in accordance to the laws of the kingdom. This functions much like modern society where people of powerful political or business ranking are entitled to a show of decorum and some preference from society (although it certainly has never demanded that everyone like or never poke fun at these figures).</p>
<p>Noble ranking also requires from the noble people a certain amount of responsibility and adherence to the kingdom's laws themselves from the noble. Each noble in turn is expected to answer to those to whom their station would require they pay deference.</p>
<p>A cruel and unjust baroness who consistently imposes petty and unfair disciplines upon the commoners may eventually be subject to punishment by the same laws she used to abuse her people.</p>
<p>Now back to our friend Amilio. Amilio has been trying to get an audience with the Duke. He has been going through the proper channels and has been getting nowhere, mainly because Baron Wasteland (on whose lands Amilio lives) is a real creep. Amilio, in a fit of frustration, finally decides to take his case directly to Count Chermoney, Baron Wasteland's liege. Amilio pleads his case to the</p>
<p>Count's seneschal or to one of the Count's guards. He will then get an audience with the Count and may tell him of the unreasonable attitude of Baron Wasteland. After dealing with Amilio's problem,</p>
<p>Count Chermoney will then be responsible for dealing with the negligent and abusive attitudes of Baron Wasteland.</p>
<p>Should the Baron be found to have repeatedly treated his people in this manner and should continue to disobey the wishes of his liege, then the Baron faces the very real threat of being stripped of his lands and title and finding himself broke and in jail.</p>
<p>Becoming a Noble</p>
<p>Becoming a noble is a goal for many players in NERO. Nobility offers many in-game benefits: besides being in the middle of many important in-game events, you get real in-game power and in some chapters, an automatic income from your estates.</p>
<p>Because the position offers such benefits, it is not easy to obtain. To become a knight, you have to prove your worth through a series of tests and challenges. Take this point seriously! Simply showing up every event will not be enough; the position will not be granted for longevity.</p>
<p>Becoming a knight requires work. Put a lot of effort into your costume. Constantly be in character. Always be the "good guy" (at least in public). Earning a knighthood is a reward. It's a quest. It's not a right. NERO wants its players to respect you (the player) for all the hard work you have done to achieve that position even if they don't respect your character.</p>
<p>Bloodlines</p>
<p>Many societies and cultures in the NERO world care a great deal about bloodlines and lineage. In particular, many of the races of the world are concerned about interbreeding. However, with a millennia of interaction among the races, no PC member of a race can absolutely verify, through magical means or otherwise, the complete "purity" of their bloodline.</p>
</body></Root>