<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Root xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/"><body>
<h1>Chapter 3 The Skill System</h1>
<p>NERO characters advance by purchasing skills.</p>
<p>Each skill you learn allows you to perform a particular task or group of tasks. Many can only be used a limited number of times per day. Some skills allow you to improve your abilities when the skill is bought multiple times. Be sure to carefully read the skill descriptions.</p>
<h3>Standard Reset</h3>
<p>In any case where a skill can be used only a certain number of times per day (such as Critical Slays or spells), the used skills will not return to you until the next day at 6 PM. This is known as a reset. On adventure days the reset happens before each module or adventure.</p>
<h3>Limited Reset</h3>
<p>Some chapters offer an additional reset of times-per-day skills at 6 AM. These are called limited resets and do not refresh craft and production skills, formal magic skills, Cantrips, or magic items. Information on whether or not your local NERO Chapter is using the Limited Reset rule will be available on their web site, at the event, and often announced at the Opening Ceremonies of the event.</p> 
<h2>The Skill System</h2>
<p>NERO is a fantasy game. By that, we mean that it is a compilation of rules and customs by which we allow people to simulate doing things that they cannot really do. The most obvious of these things is magic.</p>
<p>You should not be fooled into thinking that your personal skill equates to the character skill it represents. For instance, we have weapon skills. You must have the</p>
<p>One Handed Edged weapon skill before you are allowed to use a long sword. Many people have asked if they can at least pick up a sword and block blows with it, after all, anyone could make the attempt, could they not? The answer is no, in our game they cannot.</p>
<p>The level of ability represented by the skill bought can be considerably different from that of your average player. It represents a skill that has required hours of practice a day for months to gain. When such an individual is faced with a person totally unskilled in weapon use, they would strike the person down with ease. The player's skill may be somewhat less than that of the character, however, so the restrictions are used to simulate the skills.</p>
<p>Similarly, the proficiency system represents a level of skill that the player might never obtain. We use it as a way to artificially give a player's character, no matter what his or her real world skill, an advantage over another whose character is not as skilled. It allows a player of indifferent skill to defeat or hold their own against a player of much greater skill. </p>
<p>This is, after all, a fantasy. A person should be able to acquire skills that allow their character to do things that they themselves could not do in real life.</p>
</body></Root>