<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Root xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/"><body><p>Chapter 4 Magic</p>
<p>Spell Aura</p>
<p>There are two types of physical representations for spell aura; the manufactured spell orb and the traditional spell packets. Check with your local chapter so see which aura types you can use as some venues restrict one type or the other.</p>
<p>The spell orb is a manufactured product made of soft foam and can be no bigger than the size of a tennis ball. Soft foam balls can be purchased at most sporting good stores and toy stores. Foam balls are made by companies such as Wilson (called the Foam Flight Practice Ball) and Nerf makes a soft foam tennis ball.</p>
<p>Spell packets are constructed with bird seed and fabric. The bird seed should be the small variety, with no sunflower seeds or other heavy or sharp items that could hurt.</p>
<p>Do not use replacements! Rice can get wet and turn into a hardened ball. Rubber balls or tightly packed rubber bands will be too hard. If you are caught using something other than bird seed, you will have your packets and spell tags, if tags are used, confiscated and will lose your spells for the rest of the day.</p>
<p>To make a spell packet, the birdseed is placed in the center of the fabric, and the fabric is gathered around it and a small rubber band is used to bind the fabric or it can be sewn shut. Packets should be loosely packed, tight balls of birdseed can hurt!</p>
<p>The packet may be of any color except orange or yellow. Orange packets are used to represent alchemical gas globes, and yellow packets are used for arrows.</p>
<p>A good size for your fabric is 6" by 6", and a good amount of birdseed is 3/4 tbsps. You can use different amounts but, you should never use so much material that the resulting packet cannot fit into a 35mm film canister. Packets that are larger than that will be confiscated by a marshal. You may want to personalize your spell packets in some way by using a distinctive cloth or writing on the packets. This is a good way to make sure you can get your packets back after a battle without arguing with other spell casters about whose packets are whose.</p>
<p>Spell packets are visible as an opaque colored aura of energy only when held in the hand. In game they are visible but they do not produce any light. They are not in-game items and cannot be stolen, fumbled or removed.</p>
<p>You should not carry in your hand more spell packets than you can actually cast (although you can have plenty of extras in your pouches or pockets). If you only have 3 spells, you cannot have 42 spell packets between your fingers. You may also carry packets to represent scrolls or magic items that require a thrown packet to be thrown but those items must be readily available and not stashed away in a backpack.</p>
<p>Casting Spells</p>
<p>To cast a spell, the caster must have a spell packet in hand. The hand and arm with the spell packet in it must be "free" (Hands that are holding something else, or are tied or bound either physically or with a binding spell are not "free"). The caster must then correctly recite the verbal for the spell in a voice loud enough to be heard by a person standing next to you even if there is no one standing next to you. Within three seconds after finishing the verbal, the caster must then throw the packet at the target. The short phrase or "incantation" of the spell is spoken in plain English so the victim will know what spell has been cast. In game, these words are understood by anyone, but have a "magical effect" associated with them that makes them different from normal speech. Even though you can speak the language, you cannot "fake" a spell incantation or otherwise bluff the casting of a spell. You also cannot bluff the start of a spell incantation. If you start the incantation, the spell is used. Spellcasters expend the power to cast a spell as soon as the incantation has begun. You cannot start the incantation for a spell, change your mind, and then still have that spell. You must wait until the next reset to restudy and to cast the spell again.</p>
<p>Touch-Casting</p>
<p>Touch-casting is performed by holding a packet and placing it against the target you wish to affect. The obvious advantage to this is that there is no chance of missing and wasting the effect. In such a case, the effect recipient may choose to "accept" the effect, thus letting it past their Spell Defenses such as Shield Magic or Elemental Shield. The recipient must be conscious to "accept" an effect without triggering the Spell Defences. You may never "accept" a thrown effect. The decision to accept an effect through touch-casting is made immediately after the effect is cast. This is to prevent a caster from tricking an unsuspecting victim. </p>
<p>The recipient of a touch-cast effect can always refuse the effect by saying "refused." This will use up the effect, but have no effect whatsoever on the recipient. Whenever attempting to touch-cast, you must abide by all NERO safe conduct rules.</p>
<p>Meditation</p>
<p>Any character may Meditate to regain use of "times per day" or "expendable" skills that were blocked by the Return type monster ability. To Meditate, the player must role-play deep concentration for 60 seconds, during which time they may perform no other actions including speaking, moving, or the use of any in-game skills, items or abilities. At the end of the meditation the character regains any skills or abilities lost to the effect Return <type>. Only character skills and abilities may be regained by Meditating. (not Magic Items, Scrolls, Alchemy, etc.) A spell-casting character may also Meditate to regain spells that missed a legal target. At the end of the meditation, the character regains the use of any thrown spells that failed to hit a valid target, as well as all spells, skills and abilities lost to the Return <type> effect. Spell casters should not use the Meditate ability to intentionally miss their targets in an attempt to cause confusion for the NPCs. "Decoy" spells that are intentionally thrown away from the target should not be regained by Meditate. In effect, you can only get your spells back from Meditate if you were actually attempting to hit your target and missed. Spells negated by defenses (ex. Dodge, Phase, and Resist) cannot be meditated back.</p>
<p>Schools of Magic</p>
<p>Whenever your character begins learning magic, either celestial or earth, you must select which of the two is your primary school of magic. The other will be the secondary, costing more build to buy. There is nothing preventing you from learning both earth and celestial magic but a separate spell pyramid must be built for each school.</p>
<p>Stacked Effects</p>
<p>Identical spells may not be stacked. No person may have a second copy of the same spell actively affecting him or her unless the spell description states otherwise. If</p>
<p>you are hit with a second effect that isn't stackable, the call is "got it". Calling "No effect" in this situation is incorrect. This definition is extended to include all identically named NERO game effects, not just spells. Identical effects are not stackable, unless noted in the effect's description.</p>
<p>The following spell types have special rules regarding spell stacking.</p>
<p>Blade Effects</p>
<p>These effects change the damage call of a weapon. You may have no more than three blade effects active on you at any time. The following spells are blade effects Endow, Delayed Endow, Elemental Blade, Enchanted Blade, and Silver Aura. While blade effects can affect the same target, they only work one at a time.</p>
<p>Charm Effects</p>
<p>You can only be affected by one charm effect at a time. If a creature is under a Charm effect and is hit with another, the most recent one will replace the previously administered effect as long as the new effect is of equal or higher value to the previous effect. See Table 5-6 on page 64.</p>
<p>Ex. Durk the adventurer is Charmed by a Siren his friend Sloan casts a charm spell at him, since Charm is of equal value to the Charm on Durk, the Siren's charm effect is negated and Durk is now only charmed to Sloan.</p>
<p>However, if the second effect is of lower value on the chart (1 being the lowest) the first charm effect remains.</p>
<p>Ex. Durk the Adventurer is Charmed by a Siren, the Siren's minion casts Shun on Durk. Since Shun is a lower value than Charm, Durk calls "Got it" and take no effect to the Shun. Durk would remain Charmed to the Siren.</p>
<p>Target Specific</p>
<p>Some effects like Wither Limb or Shatter have a sub-target as part of the call. This is required for spells and optional for other delivery methods such as carrier attacks or potions. If the sub-target is not specified then it is the target's choice as to which sub-target that is un-withered(Wither Limb ) or unrendered (Shatter, Destroy) will be affected. If no target matching the description exists, the call is "Got it". Calling "No effect" in this situation is incorrect.</p>
<p>Spell defenses</p>
<p>Spell defenses carry over from adventure to adventure. A fighter who still has a Shield spell on him at the end of a NERO adventure weekend will still have that spell at the beginning of the next weekend or module. This rule applies only to spells that are "indefinite" in duration. There can be no Wards when the game starts.</p>
<p>In-game, Spell Defenses are visible when they go off. It is obvious to anyone looking at you that you were protected from an attacking spell and what defense was used to negate it. You must state what the defense is at the time by saying "Reflect Magic" or "Shield Magic" for example, thus informing all observers that the spell was unsuccessful. Saying "flash" or "no effect" is not allowed. If you do not call a spell defense within three seconds of being hit, you take the effect and the defense is lost.</p>
<p>A spellcaster is not immune to his or her own spells, nor can they automatically dispel or deactivate their own spells, unless specifically noted in a spell's description. Spells such as Bless and Shield which merely add hit points do not have to be so announced.</p>
<p>Visible Effects</p>
<p>Berserk, Bind, Confine, Disease, Feeblemind, Hallucinoid, Imprison, Nausea, Paralyze, Pin, Silence, Sleep, Taint Blood, Vertigo, and Web, are all visible to any viewer while they are in effect, so long as they take the time to observe them (they must ask the affected player). The spells Ward and Circle of Power are also visible, provided that the physical representation (rope, building or otherwise) can be seen and the viewer takes the time to observe them. You cannot call a Hold to determine whether any visible effects are present. The amount of time it takes to ask if your character sees the effect is the amount of time it took your character to notice the effect, and you should only ask for visible effects from a short distance away at a conversational volume.</p>
<p>Eldritch Power</p>
<p>Many of the spells call upon an energy called eldritch power. This is a type of energy that only affects beings that are alive or animated. If you cast a Flame Bolt spell</p>
<p>at someone and miss and hit a tree, the tree will not catch on fire. Nor can you use an Ice Bolt spell to keep your ice cream cold. These spells can only affect creatures that are alive or animated.</p>
<p>Reversible Spells</p>
<p>Many earth magic spells are reversible (for example, Cure Disease and Cause Disease). These spells do not have to be learned or "memorized" separately. In fact, there is no way to separate the two spells. If you know the spell Cure Wounds, you automatically also know Cause Wounds. You cannot "forget" how to cast necromantic spells or otherwise claim to only know one side of a reversible spell. You can decide at the moment of casting which spell effect you will use (With proper incantation, of course). The reverse of many healing spells are necromantic, identifiable by the word "Chaos" in their incant. Beware however, that in- many in game places laws exist against necromantic spells such as Create Undead, so you'd better be ready to face the in-game consequences.</p>
<p>Spell Disruption</p>
<p>If a person takes body damage while casting a spell, the spell is disrupted. It does not work and is lost from memory. A spell can be disrupted by anything that deals body damage, including weapons, traps, or other spells. This is known as Disruption or Spell Disruption and is sometimes applicable to other types of attacks as noted in their descriptions.</p>
<p>Necromancy</p>
<p>Is necromancy evil? Not every person on Tyrra thinks so, in fact, it is accepted and even promoted by some races and cultures. However, necromancy is illegal in most parts of the world because many people believe it draws upon the decaying and dying aspects of the earth and thus prevents the earth from acting "naturally." The most accepted in-game explanation is this: Imagine the planet going through its seasons normally from year to year. Healing spells "go with the flow" of this cycle and do not disrupt the orderly process of living and dying that are part of this orderly system. Necromancy "goes against the flow" of this cycle by tapping into the chaotic forces that are not part of this system. Creating undead, for example, requires that a spirit behave in ways that are contrary to the orderly flow of the cycle. This in-game "theory" has been used in the past to explain large numbers of undead randomly appearing ("The chaos in this area is so strong that the cycle is being completely disrupted!") as well as aberrant weather ("This cold wave this time of year can only be explained by too much necromancy being cast in the area!"). Of course, there are many scholars who believe that this theory is a load of goblin dung and that bad weather and undead rising are all part of the normal cycle. It is up to you to decide as your character how you feel about the issue. Assume for game purposes that there are many learned treatises on both sides and that people have been arguing the point for many hundreds of years.</p>
<p>Elemental Planes</p>
<p>There are twelve main elemental planes which exist across powerful dimensional boundaries. The world of Tyrra is made up of the combination of these elements and their intersections. Please see the Tyrran Cosmology document at NeroLarp.com for more information, but it is important to note here that each of the twelve elemental planes has an associated damage type: a power it uses to harm opponents. These planes and their associated damage types are as follows:</p>
<p>Planes  Life, Death, Order, Chaos, Dream, Reason, Light, Darkness, Earth, Air, Fire, and Water. </p>
<p>Damage Types, in order  Essence, Destruction, Order, Chaos, Dream, Reason, Light, Darkness, Stone, Lightning, Fire, and Ice.</p>
<p>Illegal Skills and Powers</p>
<p>No character can ever use a plot given power to gain information about a PC's actions after the fact. This includes approved spells and skills such as Dreamvision as well as other abilities such as clairvoyance, clairaudience, tracking or scrying of any manner.</p>
<p>If a character wants to know what was said or done by a PC first hand, he must actually be present at the time of the action. Plot will never provide this information via one of the listed abilities, or through any similar means, and a PC can never claim to have known it due to ESP or other special abilities after the fact.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Chapter 5 : Spells</p>
<p>Every Spell listed here is available at every NERO Chapter.</p>
<p>The information after the spell's in game name includes the spell's level, whether it is Celestial or Earth, whether it can be made into a Potion or Scroll, whether it can be Manifolded, and its duration.</p>
<p>Spell Defenses</p>
<p>There are a few spells and effects that will defend the recipient from incoming spells or attacks. Each can protect against one spell or effect only. They are cast upon the recipient in advance and stay with the recipient until "activated" by the effect they are meant to prevent. The Spell Defenses are Displacement, Elemental Shield, Guardian of the Four, Magic Armor, Poison Shield, Reflect Magic, and Shield Magic.</p>
<p>In-game, you are always aware of what Spell Defenses are active on you. Once a Spell Defense is active, then it will affect the next applicable incoming effect, regardless of whether or not you would have been affected. It will then be used up.</p>
<p>All Spell Defenses must be called correctly, for example "Reflect Magic" or "Phase", to be effective and must be called within three seconds or are lost or not used respectively.</p>
<p>Spell Durations</p>
<p>Concentration</p>
<p>This spell lasts as long as the caster maintains concentration. While concentrating, the caster cannot run or use any game skills.</p>
<p>Continuous</p>
<p>Continuous is a specific form of concentration which requires the caster to continually chant a litany, recite a verse, or sing a song with the limits listed under manifold page 39 except you do not need the Manifold skill or a Hearth. At the end of each repetition the caster may state the incant for the spell and deliver the effect as specified in the description of the spell. As long as the caster continues to repeat the verse they may continue to recast the spell using only one spell slot. Each spell with this duration may impose other limits upon the caster to continue the spell. The caster may not speak outside the words of the verse or incant and may not use other skills while continuing a spell and may not pause longer than 5 seconds. The limitations of Concentration also apply. If a continuous spell is used once the caster may simply state the incant.</p>
<p>Timed</p>
<p>Some spells last for a specific amount of time, either 5 seconds, 1, 5, or 10 minutes, 1 hour, or 5 days.</p>
<p>Instant</p>
<p>The duration of this spell is instantaneous, but its effects may be permanent. (Thus, any damage taken from these spells is permanent until cured.)</p>
<p>Indefinite</p>
<p>The effects of this spell are permanent unless the victim receives the proper counter spell or the spell's effect is used up (or the victim dies). The counter spell will be listed in the spell description.</p>
<p>Line of Sight</p>
<p>This spell lasts as long as the caster could see the victim from wherever the caster is located. It also lasts if the victim could see the caster.</p>
<p>Basically, if you can draw a straight line between the caster and the victim without the line being obscured by any large, immovable obstacles, then the Line of Sight is still in effect. The caster closing their eyes or hiding behind someone else does not break Line of Sight.</p>
<p>If the caster breaks Line of Sight by imposing a very large object such as a building or large tree between the caster and the victim for longer than 10 seconds, the spell is broken. If view of the character is resumed before the 10 seconds is up, then the spell continues. These spells will cease immediately if the caster falls unconscious line of sight lasts for a maximum of 5 days.</p>
<p>Awaken</p>
<p>I command you to awaken.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:YesPotion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell awakens the recipient from a Waylay, any sleep effect, and the charm effects Calm, Calm animal, Calm, Calm Animal, Shun, shun Animal, Silence, Fear, and Vampire Charm. It does not in any way affect Enslavement.</p>
<p>Banish</p>
<p>With eldrich force I banish you.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:YesPotion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell sends any extraplanar creature from Tyrra to its plane of origin and will keep the creature on its own home plane for 24 Tyrran hours. All items carried by the creature will be left behind unless Spirit Linked. This spell cannot be used to return to Tyrra from another plane.</p>
<p>Bind</p>
<p>With mystic force I bind you.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: line of sight</p>
<p>This spell snares the victim's arms, binding them straight to its sides. The victim may talk freely, but may not use any game skills requiring use of the arms, including using a weapon or shield, casting a spell, or activating a gas globe. The victim may walk, run, or leave the combat area as desired. This spell does not prevent the victim from being searched or being given a Killing Blow, although a moving victim is unlikely to allow either action.</p>
<p>Bless</p>
<p>I grant you the power of a bless.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell gives the recipient five extra Body Points. These points are the first Body Points lost to damage. This spell cannot be used to revive an unconscious person or harm an undead.</p>
<p>Calm</p>
<p>I command you to be calm.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>By means of this spell the caster can calm one target. This makes the target docile and non-aggressive for the duration of five minutes. The target might wander off, head for the tavern for a drink, or simply sit down and rest for a while. They cannot take any aggressive actions while under the effect of this spell, they will not participate in combat nor will they attempt to remove the spell. This is a form of charm and will over-ride any normal behavior so long as it is effective it can be stopped by the ability Resist Charm. If anyone attacks the target in any way this effect will immediately be dispelled. An Awaken or Dispel Magic will also work to remove this effect.</p>
<p>Calm Animal</p>
<p>I command this animal to be calm.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>By means of this spell the caster can calm one creature that is designated as an animal. This calm makes the creature docile and non-aggressive for the duration of five minutes. They cannot take any aggressive actions such as participating in combat nor will they attempt to remove the spell. The animal might wander off or simply sit down and rest for a while. This is a form of charm and will over-ride any normal behavior so long as it is effective it can be stopped by the ability Resist Charm. If anyone attacks the creature in any way this effect will  mmediately be dispelled. An Aw aken or Dispel Magic will also work to remove this effect. This will not affect magical animals, hybrid animals, animal men, only ordinary animals, fish, and birds. For example an eagle would be affected but it would not affect a gryphon, a phoenix, or a biata. A bull would be affected but it would not affect a minotaur or a bull scavenger. A horse would be affected but a unicorn would not. This spell has no effect on any being which is not designated as an ordinary animal though it will still trigger a Shield Magic or similar protective.</p>
<p>Cause Critical Wounds</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to cause critical wounds 30.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will deal 30 points of body damage to the target. It does not affect armor. It will cure 30 Body Points to an undead creature.</p>
<p>Cause Disease</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to cause disease.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell will infect the recipient with a debilitating disease. The infection is not contagious, but makes the target unable to run. The spell Purify Blood will not cure someone under the effects of this spell. This spell might not be effective against creatures with no metabolism.</p>
<p>Cause Light Wounds</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to cause light wounds 5.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will deal 5 points of body damage to the target. It does not affect armor. It will cure 5 Body Points of damage on an undead creature.</p>
<p>Cause Mortal Wounds</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to cause mortal wounds 40.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will deal 40 points of body damage to the target. It does not affect armor. It will cure 40 Body Points to an undead creature.</p>
<p>Cause Serious Wounds</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to cause serious wounds 20.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will deal 20 points of body damage to the target. It does not affect armor. It will cure 20 Body Points to an undead creature.</p>
<p>Cause Wounds</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to cause wounds 10</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will deal 10 points of body damage to the target. It does not affect armor. It will cure 10 Body Points to an undead creature.</p>
<p>Charm</p>
<p>I command you to be charmed.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>This spell makes the victim view the caster as his or her best friend in the whole world. While this spell is in effect, no amount of logic or role-playing will convince the victim that he or she has been Charmed, and the victim will not remember the casting of the spell until after it has worn off or been cured. An attack on the victim by the caster's party will not immediately break the spell, but if the caster cannot come up with a good reason why he or she is not helping to defend the victim, then that will. If the caster attacks the victim, then the spell is broken immediately. A victim of this spell will not do anything completely against his or her own nature (such as attack his or her own party) unless a very good reason can be given by the caster. The spell does not turn the victim into a mindless robot blindly following orders, but it does require the victim to stay by the side of the new "friend" and listen to his or her suggestions. (Note that this assumes that they both speak the same language. You cannot obey a "suggestion" that you don't understand.) This spell only works on creatures that have a mind as defined by the game. Several creatures (such as lesser undead, golems, or some giant insects) do not have a mind that can be affected by this spell. After the spell's duration expires, the victim remembers everything that happened except the actual casting of the Charm spell. Depending upon the circumstances,the victim might sometimes realize that he or she had been charmed. Note that this spell is not strong enough to override Control Undead, Fear, Enslavement or Vampire Charm Table 5-6 on page 64.</p>
<p>Circle of Harmony</p>
<p>With eldrich force I build a circle of harmony</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 1 Hour</p>
<p>This spell allows the caster to charm a single creature which must be an animal. This spell duplicates the Charm spell, except that it may only be cast on ordinary animals. Since the Animal will not understand the common tongue this in general only keeps the caster safe from the animal attacking him. If the caster is attacked the animal will generally attempt to defend him and if the caster interposes himself between the animal and another target the animal will understand that it shouldn't attack the target. If the animal has been trained to follow commands it will listen to the caster as if he were the one who normally gives the commands and will perform any commands he is trained to at the request of the caster, this does not mean the animal will do anything they are not specifically trained to do. This spell is a type of charm and can be resisted with the ability Resist Charm, and it can be cured with an Aw aken spell or Dispel Magic spell. Stronger charms such as Vampire Charm or Enslavement will override its effects Table 5-6 on page 64. This will not affect magical animals, hybrid animals, nimal men, only ordinary animals, fish, and birds. For example an eagle would be affected but it would not affect a gryphon, a phoenix, or a biata. A bull would be affected but it would not affect a minotaur or a bull scavenger. A horse would be affected but a unicorn would not. This spell has no effect on any being which is not designated as an ordinary animal though it will still trigger a shield magic or similar protective.</p>
<p>Circle of Power</p>
<p>With eldrich force I build a circle of power.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 10 Minutes</p>
<p>The caster may draw out or construct an intricate circle which acts as a prepared hearth, for the school of magic from which this spell was cast, without the need to be indoors. The circle  ust consist of a circle within a circle to form a circular  band. Between the two circles their must be no less than eight symbols or glyphs. The circle must be fully prepared before the spell  s cast. The maximum radius of the outer circle is six feet, and the inner circle must be at least six inches smaller in radius. The area within the outer circle represents the area of effect. The  spell lasts for one hour or until the circle is in part or whole erased, pulled apart, destroyed, or a dispel magic is cast upon the phys-rep. The caster must place an individually recognizable  styled "H" in the center of the circle as if it were a hearth indicating it is active, the "H" is OOG the way a "W" is for a ward. The circle remains active even if the caster leaves it but if dispelled or otherwise disrupted the "H" must be removed. A player must confirm their "H" is still present before using a Circle of Harmony. A player may cast this spell from both schools of magic in order to have the effect of the hearth for both schools. If they do this the "H" must reflect this to them. Multiple characters can have this effect active on the same area, but each Circle of Harmony must have its own "H" which must be recognizable by the player who cast it and distinct  rom any others.</p>
<p>Confine</p>
<p>With mystic force I confine you.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Line of Sight</p>
<p>This spell snares the arms of its victim, binding them straight to its sides, and immobilizes the victim completely from the neck down making them helpless. The victim may talk freely, but  may not use any game skills requiring use of the arms, including using a weapon or shield, casting a spell, or activating a gas globe. The victim may not walk, run, or be moved in any way  Any item the victim is holding cannot be dropped. However, since the effect allows the victim to be searched, anyone else can choose to physically remove a hand-held item from the  victim by simply "searching" them. Even a victim with Superhuman Strength cannot prevent himself from being "searched" in this manner. This spell does not prevent the victim from being given a Killing Blow.</p>
<p>Control Undead</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to control undead.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>This spell allows the caster to control one lesser undead for 5 minutes. Tasks may not involve any sentient thought higher than an animal: "Guard this" is fine, but "Count all the leaves on that tree" requires sentience and will not work. The most recent Control Undead effect takes precedent, if there is a conflict. This spell will not affect a living target, although it will remove a living person's Shield Magic or Reflect Magic. This effect is stronger than calm, Calm animal, Charm, Charm Animal, Shun, Shun Animal or Fear. The most recent Control Undead, Vampire Charm or Enslavement effect will take precedent if there is a conflict Table 5-6 on page 64.</p>
<p>Corruption</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to corrupt you.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 1 Minute</p>
<p>This spell restores an undead target or other target healed by necromancy or chaos to his or her full body points. Once the spell is successfully cast, the target will begin to regenerate as per the rules of the special ability Regeneration. Corruption requires that the character stand or sit in one place for one minute and concentrate. If this process is interrupted before its  completion, the spell is lost for no effect. The target may not be restored to a total of body higher than is appropriate for his race and level via this spell. This spell may not be used to aid a living character in any way. This spell only affects targets which are healed by necromancy or chaos. This spell does not remove any other negative effects. This spell is the reverse of Regeneration.</p>
<p>Create Undead</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to create undead.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>This spell only works on a corpse that has not previously been animated  and will pull the character's spirit back to reanimate its former body.  The resulting zombie will then follow the caster's commands as if a control undead spell had been cast upon it.  Note that this spell must be cast within the fie minute period between a character's death and the point where the spirit heads to the Earth Circle for resurrection. This spell transforms the individual into a mindless berserker who will fight at their normal speed until reduced to no hit points or until ordered to stop by the caster.  The creature's visual appearance does not change.  While Created as an undead the fie minute count until resurrection is suspended. If the zombie is reduced to zero Body Points or takes effect from a Dispel Magic  then the spell ends and the resurrection count resumes where it left off.  The spirit will remember nothing of the time spent as a zombie. The zombie created will have the maximum body points the victim had in life.</p>
<p>Cure Critical Wounds</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to cure crtical wounds 30.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will restore up to 30 points of body damage but never more than a character's maximum.  It will restore an unconscious or dying character but will not resurrect a dead one.  Against undead  this spell will deal 30 points of body damage.</p>
<p>Cure Disease</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to cure diease.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will cure a character infected with a disease.</p>
<p>Cure Light Wounds</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to cure light wounds 5.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will restore up to 5 points of body damage but never more than a character's maximum. It will restore an unconscious character but will not resurrect a dead one. Against undead, this spell will do 5 points of body damage.</p>
<p>Cure Mortal Wounds</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to cure mortal wounds 40.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will restore up to 40 points of body damage but never more than a character's maximum. It will restore an unconscious character but will not resurrect a dead one. Against undead, this spell will do 40 points of body damage.</p>
<p>Cure Serious Wounds</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to cure serious wounds 20</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will restore up to 20 points of body damage but never more than a character's maximum. It will restore an unconscious character but will not resurrect a dead one. Against undead, this spell will do 20 points of body damage.</p>
<p>Cure Wounds</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to cure wounds 10.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will restore up to 10 points of body damage but never more than a character's maximum. It will restore an unconscious character but will not resurrect a dead one. Against  undead, this spell will do 10 points of body damage.</p>
<p>Curse</p>
<p>I curse you with destruction.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell will cause the victim to take double damage from all attacks that would affect them. It can be removed by a Remove Curse or a Dispel Magic. The damage taken is doubled before any Spell Defenses are applied. The Curse effect does not lower a creature's Threshold, nor does it make the creature affected by additional attacks that would not normally affect it.</p>
<p>Death</p>
<p>I grant you the gift of death.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell causes the victim's spirit to flee its body, if it has a metabolism. Any armor the character was wearing is still intact, but any spells active on the victim will disappear. This spell brings a character to death, and the only thing that will save the victim is a Life spell.</p>
<p>Delayed Endow</p>
<p>I grant you the power of a delayed endow.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell endows the recipient with the ability to do two extra points of damage for one swing if it hits the target.  The total damage must be announced while swinging.  Once called  the spell is used up whether the blow was successful or not.  Unlike a normal Endow  the recipient may choose when to use a Delayed Endow. The recipient may also expend this spell to rip form Pin as per the monster ability. Delayed endow ill not benefit creatures that have Superhuman Strenght greater than +1  and will only add +1 to a creature with +1 strength. The spell may be stacked iwth other Blade Effects(maximum three spells total)</p>
<p>Desecrate</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to desecrate you.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>The recipient is protected against all non-ranged atacks from living creatures. ranged attacks (such as spells  missle weapons  and gas globes) can affect the recipient. this spell will remain in effect as long as the subject's hands are crossed on their chest and they do not recieve any body damage. I f you are unsure if an attacker is living or not  you will affected by them. YTou may not call a Hold or otherwise go out of game to asertain their status. the cahracter with a Desecrate active may use no game abilities ecept touchcasting on themselves. Attempting to pick up an item will distrupt the spell.</p>
<p>Destroy</p>
<p>I summon a force to destroy your <item>.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will render any tagged object up to the size of a normal door, useless. It can not be used to create a door-sized hole in an object larger than a door. It can target a suit of armor, although the Shield spell, and Dexterity Armor will be unaffected. Armor successfully destroyed will require the tag to be discarded as useless. This spell will not work on an item that has been Rendered Indestructible. It may also be cast at a creature to affect such an item, or to target the creature directly as some creatures may be harmed by this spell. If the caster does not specify an item or if the spell is received from a carrier attack, then it is the target's choice as to which currently non-rendered item matching the description becomes Destroyed. If no item exists call "got it" see stacking spells "Stacked Effects" on page 47. Destroying an item that has other items within, hanging from, or fastened to it will destroy all of the items. This spell will destroy not only a shield but also any scrolls , or Gas globes, etc. attached to the back. Destroying a trapped door or item will set off and destroy the trap as well. After the item is destroyed the prop for the item remains, but is unusable.</p>
<p>Destroy Undead</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to destroy undead 70.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will destroy any one lesser undead creature. Greater undead will take 70 points of body damage. this spell will not affect a living target  although like all spells it will remove a living person's shield magic or reflect magic.</p>
<p>Detect Magic</p>
<p>I call fourth mystic power to detect magic.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>Casting this spell on an object or person will reveal to the caster and only the caster if any magic is present. Any visible items worn or carried by the target will be revealed, but items hidden under clothing or in bags or boxes will not be. This spell will cover up to a door sized area. The subject must tell the caster which (if any) magic items are visible, and which schools of magic are present on all of the detected items (Earth, Celestial, Both or Other.) If the subject has any spell defenses currently active (such as Endow or Magic Armor), then the subject will detect as magical to the caster. This does not overshadow any items on the person. In other words, the fact that a subject has a Shield spell upon him or her does not cover the fact that a magic item is worn. If cast upon a Circle of Power or Ward, this spell will not only detect the target's school, but also whether the target's duration is ten minutes, one hour, one year or two years.</p>
<p>Dispel Magic</p>
<p>I call fourth mystic power to dispel magic.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will dispel all active non-formal magical effects on a given creature or object unless specifically noted by the spell description. A Shield Magic or Reflect Magic will protect all   ther spells on a person from a Dispel Magic, but will be used up in the process. A Dispel Magic potion isn't stopped by a Shield Magic or a Reflect Magic, and will dispel those spells and all others spells active upon the drinker.</p>
<p>Displacement</p>
<p>I grant you the power of a displacement.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell grants the caster, and only the caster, a shield against the first effect that hits them. It may not be cast upon another target. This will always be the first protective spell lost if it is appropriate to defend against an attack and will be used before a Shield Magic, Elemental Shield, Magic Armor or any other automatic protective effect, though a Formal Magic Cloak or Bane can be used before a Displacement. The caster may choose to accept a touch cast effect under the protection of this spell. When struck by an appropriate attack the defense is automatically triggered. Displacement cannot be Imbued via Formal Magic Cantrip, placed into a Magic Item of any kind (including a Spell Store item), or by any other means transferred to someone else to cast. The proper call for this defense is "Phase."</p>
<p>Dragon's Breath</p>
<p>I call fourth a dragon's breath 40.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell allows the caster to cast a bolt of magical fire, dealing 40 hit points of eldritch fire damage to the target. The fire is eldritch in origin and will not otherwise set anything alight.</p>
<p>Eldrich Blast</p>
<p>I call fourth a  <flame ice lightning or stone>  blast 45.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell allows the caster to affect a target with a bolt of magical fire, ice, lightning or stone dealing 45 hit points of eldritch damage. The caster may choose which type of damage to throw at the time of the casting, signifying such through the verbal. The damage will not otherwise set anything alight or freeze anything. This spell may also be called (Fire, Ice, Lightning or Stone) Blast for the purposes of magic deliverance, monster abilities, magic items, and similar situations.</p>
<p>Elemental Blade</p>
<p>I grant you the power of an elemental blade.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell allows the recipient to do five extra points of damage for one swing if the blow is successful. The spell is used up whether the blow is successful or not. Unlike an Endow, the recipient may choose when to use an Elemental Blade. The recipient must announce the total damage while swinging. This damage will not set anything alight, freeze it, turn it to stone, etc. The extra damage comes from the spell's eldritch effect, and its bonus can added fully to damage done by creatures with Superhuman Strength. The spell may be stacked with two other Blade Effects see Table 5-6 on page 64, but the spells will only work one at a time. It does not allow you to hurt a  monster that can only be damaged by magical weapons. When using this spell, you may call out "Fire, Ice, Lightning or Stone" as a damage type. The user of the spell chooses the type of damage done. The damage type is chosen when the damage is added to the weapon blow.</p>
<p>Elemental Shield</p>
<p>I grant you the power of an elemental shield.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell protects the recipient from the next effect with the word "elemental" in the verbal. It is then immediately used up. When used, the call is "Elemental Shield."</p>
<p>Empathic Healing</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to transfer <effect>.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell allows the caster to transfer one detrimental effect from the target to the caster. The effects this spell may transfer to the caster are Disease, Curse, Paralyze, Silence, Sleep, Taint Blood, Weakness, Wither Limb, Drain, Drain Life, Feeblemind, Hallucinoid, Intoxicant, Nausea, Paralyze, and Vertigo. No effect not on this list may be transferred using Empathic Healing. The caster cannot use spell protectives or combat abilities like Dodg e or Phase to negate the effect upon them. If the effect is not inflicted upon the caster because of immunity to the effect, a formal magic defense, or a magical item, then the spell fails. The caster must take the effect or use a racial resist for the spell to succeed. The caster must begin the duration of the negative effect they take upon themselves from the point they take the effect not when it was originally cast on the one they removed it from.</p>
<p>Enchanted Blade</p>
<p>I grant you the power of an enchanted blade.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell allows the recipient to use the "Magic weapon type against one opponent for the one battle, in the manner of a Critical Attack page 35 The recipient may choose when to use the Enchanted Blade, and must announce the total damage of the swing while saying "Magic" instead of "Normal" or "Silver." The spell may be stacked with other Endow/Blade spells (maximum three spells total), but the spells will only work one at a time. Enchanted Blade will have no effect with a Damage Aura or Magic Aura.</p>
<p>Endow</p>
<p>I grant you the power of an endow.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell endows the recipient with the ability to do three extra points of damage on the next swing, if it hits the target. The total damage must be announced while swinging. Once called, the spell is used up whether the blow was successful or not. The spell may be stacked with two other Blade Effects see Table 5-6 on page 64 , but the spells will only work one at a time. It does not allow you to hurt a monster that can only be damaged by magical weapons. Endow will not benefit creatures that have Superhuman Strength greater than +1, and will only add one to a creature with +1 strength.</p>
<p>Enflame</p>
<p>I summon a force to enflame your <item> 20.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell causes any hand-held itemto burst into fire for 5 seconds, dealing 20 points of eldritch fire damage to the person or creature carrying the item as if they were struck by a Flame Bolt. It will also act as a Fumble spell towards that item if the creature was affected by the fire. A defense against Fire will negate this spell.</p>
<p>Extended Hearth</p>
<p>With eldrich force I build an extended hearth.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>When this spell is cast on an existing circle of power or ward it will allow the circle or ward to act as a prepared hearth for the caster for the school this spell was cast from. The prepared hearth will last as long as the circle or ward if they are not already extended through formal magic. If they are already extended through formal magic this spell will last for five days. The extended hearth is only dispelled if the circle or ward is destroyed, a Dispel Magic will not suffice. When cast the caster must place an individually recognizable stylized "H" up on the door or wall or within the center of the circle obviously indicating that a hearth is in affect, the "H" is OOG the way a "W" is for a ward. If the effect is dispelled the "H" must be removed. A player must confirm their "H" is still present before using an extended hearth. A player may cast this spell from both schools of magic in order to have the effect of the hearth for both schools. If they do this the "H" must reflect this to them. Multiple characters can have this effect active on the same area, but each Extended Hearth must have its own "H" which must be recognizable by the player who cast it and distinct from any others. This spell cannot be thrown.</p>
<p>Flame Bolt</p>
<p>I call fourth a flame Bolt  20.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell deals 20 points of eldritch fire damage to the victim.</p>
<p>Free Undead</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to free undead.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell free an undead creature from the effects of a Trap Undead spell. This spell will not affect a living target, although it will remove a living person's  Shield Magic or Reflect Magic.</p>
<p>Fumble</p>
<p>I summon a force to fumble your  <item>.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell causes the target to be unable to use a specific hand-held item. Only the item named may be fumbled in this manner. Saying a general description like "weapon" is fine, although if the target is holding two items which match the description, then it is the target's choice as to which they cannot use. A shield is not considered a "weapon" for purposes of this spell. Spell packets cannot be affected, while orange gas globes can be affected.</p>
<p>Guardian of the Four</p>
<p>I grant you the power of a <fire, ide, lightning or stone> shield.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell grants a shield to fire, ice, lightning, or stone as determined by the caster at the time of casting. This will nearly always be the first protective spell lost if it is appropriate to defend against an attack and will be used before a Shield Magic, Elemental Shield, Magic Armor or any other automatic protective effect other than Displacement which still comes before this spell. This spell will defend against packet delivered attacks and weapon delivered attacks as long as the damage or effect type is appropriate. For combined effects such as Enflame where the spell is both a fire attack and another effect this spell will protect against both. A player may have only a single casting of this spell upon them if another casting is placed upon them it will replace the prior one. When struck by an appropriate attack the spell automatically goes off the target may not choose to accept the spell and save this protection for later. This protective will be set off prior to any more general protective such as a Shield Magic. The caster may choose to accept a touch cast effect under the protection of this spell. When used, the call is "(fire, ice, lightning, stone) Shield."</p>
<p>Harm Undead</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to harm undead</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will deal 30 points of body damage to an undead creature. This spell will not affect a living target, although like all spells it will remove a living person's Shield Magic or Reflect Magic.</p>
<p>Help Undead</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to help undead.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will heal an undead creature for 30 points of body damage. This spell will not affect a living target although like all spells it will remove a living person's Shield Magic or Reflect Magic.</p>
<p>Ice Bolt</p>
<p>I call fourth an ice bolt  15.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell does 15 points of eldritch ice damage to the victim.</p>
<p>Ice Storm</p>
<p>I call fourth an ice storm 35.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell does 35 points of eldritch ice damage to the victim.</p>
<p>Illumination</p>
<p>I grant you the power of illumination.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Days</p>
<p>This spell produces a glowing light and allows the caster to kindle a light wand. The light can then be used by anyone. It will not work without a phys-rep. You cannot cast a Illumination spell at a person or tree and have the person or tree glow. There must be a properly dimmed flashlight or other out-of-game light source provided. The spell lasts until it is dispelled. If using a flashlight for this spell, the lens of the flashlight must be covered by a cloth, tissue paper or a gel to diffuse the light. Do not shine the light in anyone's face. This spell can not be thrown.</p>
<p>Imprision</p>
<p>With eldrich force I build a prison.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 10 Minutes</p>
<p>This spell seals the victim into a rigid, form-fitting and unbreakable barrier, trapping them within. The victim cannot move, speak, touch-cast, Gypsy Curse, or perform any game skills requiring movement. The spell lasts for ten minutes, but may be dropped by the caster at any time if he or she touches the victim and states "Imprison down." This statement is out of-game, and can be used even if the caster is Silenced or inside the Imprison. Any observers who hear the statement are aware that the Imprison was dropped, and they might know who dropped it. A Dispel Magic will bring down the Imprison, but will not dispel any other spell effects on the creature inside. Any creature sealed within an Imprison spell cannot be affected by any effect or damage, nor can they be moved. A victim of the Imprison is completely aware of his or her surroundings and unless unconscious or otherwise impaired will remember all that occurred while Imprisoned. This spell will prevent the victim from being searched and only the caster may deliver a Killing Blow to the recipient with the phrase "Imprison Down" after the three count. If the Killing Blow fails (for example, if the creature inside is immune to the caster's attack), then the Imprison will drop as soon as the Killing Blow is completed and the creature may then defend itself.</p>
<p>Improved Hearth</p>
<p>With eldrich force I build an improved hearth.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 1 Hour</p>
<p>This spell must be cast on an area already prepared as a hearth using the skill Prepare Hearth. Once cast by the character who prepared the hearth the duration of the hearth is extended to 1 hour but only works for the school of magic from which it was cast. The hearth no longer ends if the caster leaves it, is targeted with a Dispel Magic, or dies but it will end if the room is targeted with a Dispel Magic. When cast the caster must place an individually recognizable stylized "H" up on the door or wall obviously indicating that a hearth is in affect, the "H" is OOG the way a "W" is for a ward. If the room is dispelled the "H" must be removed. A player must confirm their "H" is still present before using an improved hearth. A player may cast this spell from both schools of magic in order to have the effect of the hearth for both schools. If they do this the "H" must reflect this to them. Multiple characters can have this effect active on the same area, but each Improved Hearth must have its own "H" which must be recognizable by the player who cast it and distinct from any others. This spell can not be thrown.</p>
<p>Inspiration</p>
<p>I grant you the gift of inspiration.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>The recipient chooses one daily use skill that they have purchased with build points and that they have already used that day to be refreshed. This spell will restore only normal times per day skills including a single spell slot. It will not renew powers from items or production skills or special abilities of any kind, only skills conforming to the current edition of the NERO rules. It will renew a single level of formal magic if the target so chooses but only for use in casting a Cantrip not for casting of formal magic. If used to renew a Critical Slay or Assassinate it will renew only the 100 slay or assassinate it will not renew a 200 slay or assassinate selectively unless all other slays or assassinates have been renewed through some other means first. A single target may only be affected by one inspiration for each time they can study to reset their skills (This means once per reset) and spells and casting the spell on them again will have no effect until after the next reset point.</p>
<p>Lesser Divestiture</p>
<p>With eldrich force I remove your investiture.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will Divest a person from a Ward or Mystic Lock. The caster of this spell must already be Invested. If Divesting from a Ward, the caster and the subject must both  be within the Ward at the time of casting. If Divesting from a Mystic Lock, the caster and subject must both be touching the Mystic Locked chest at the time of casting. The subject's name must then be removed from the appropriate marshal notes. A person Divested is no longer Invested in the Ward or Mystic Lock. This spell can not be thrown.</p>
<p>Lesser Investiture</p>
<p>With eldrich force I grant you investiture.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 days</p>
<p>This spell will Invest a person into a Ward or Mystic Lock. The caster of this spell must already be Invested. If Investing into a Ward, the caster and the subject must both be within the Ward at the time of casting. If Investing into a Mystic Lock, the caster and subject must both be touching the Mystic Locked chest at the time of casting. The subject's name must then be added to the appropriate marshal notes. This spell can not be thrown.</p>
<p>Life</p>
<p>I grant you the gift of life.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell must be cast within five minutes of a creature's death. It restores the creature to one Body Point and the creature is not forced to resurrect. This spell is the only thing that can save someone who has been given a killing blow or hit by a Death effect. This spell will not normally affect a living target or an undead creature, although it will remove a living person or ndead creature's Shield Magic or Reflect Magic.</p>
<p>Lightning Bolt</p>
<p>I call fourth a lightning bolt  10.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell does 10 points of eldritch lightning damage to the victim.</p>
<p>Lightning Storm</p>
<p>I call fourth a lightning storm 30</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell does 30 points of eldritch lightning damage to the victim.</p>
<p>Magic Armor</p>
<p>I grant you the power of a magic armor.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>A Magic Armor spell will protect the recipient from the next single strike by a NERO-safe weapon or any attack with the word "physical" in the verbal. The recipient must state "Magic Armor." The attack and the Magic Armor will then be expended. This does not protect against a Killing Blow or a fall, nor does it work against any traps other than weapon traps. A Magic Armor will be blown even if the amount of damage called is "zero."</p>
<p>Magic Missle</p>
<p>I call fourth a magic  missle 5.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell does 5 points of eldritch damage to the victim.</p>
<p>Magic Storm</p>
<p>I call fourth a magic storm 5.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Concentration</p>
<p>This spell allows the caster to continuously channel eldritch energy so long as their feet remain planted. At the time of casting, the caster must plant both feet. As long as both feet remain planted and Concentration is maintained, the caster may throw a packet after completing the incant "Magic Storm 5" While the spell is in effect, the caster can perform no other skill  nor cast any other spell, nor activate magical items, but can speak. Each packet thrown acts as a separate spell which causes 5 points of eldritch damage to the target.</p>
<p>Mystic Lock</p>
<p>With eldrich force I build a mystic lock.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Days</p>
<p>This spell magically seals a single box or chest which becomes immobile once the spell is cast. It will not work on a container that already has magical properties. The size of the box is limited to a rectangular solid 3ft x 3ft x 6ft and no larger. No effect, person or object may pass through the Mystic Lock unless as described below. Anyone touching the Mystic Lock during the casting of the spell will receive an Investiture to the Mystic Lock. The names of the people Invested must be written in the room's marshal notes. Investiture in a Mystic Lock allows you to place and retrieve items within the chest, however no people or dead bodies may ever be placed inside a Mystic Lock. Mystic Lock is not affected by Dispel Magic. The chest must be visibly marked to indicate the presence of the Mystic Lock by attaching a large clearly visible "W". You may not Mystic Lock a box in order to obstruct or hinder movement. This spell cannot be thrown.</p>
<p>Paralyze</p>
<p>I curse you with paralysis.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>This spell completely immobilizes the victim. The target may not move any part of their body and may be given a Killing Blow while thus trapped. If the victim is rendered unconscious or someone  attempts to pose them, they will collapse to the ground but will remain Paralyzed. An Unparalyze spell or a Dispel Magic will release a victim from the Paralyze. A Release spell will not work. This spell only works on creatures that have a metabolism. Some creatures such as undead, golems or some elementals are not affected by this spell.</p>
<p>Pin</p>
<p>With mystic force I pin you.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Line of Sight</p>
<p>This spell will root the target's right foot in place. The target may pivot their body 360 degrees but may not move their right foot. The Pin can be removed with a Release spell or a Dispel Magic.</p>
<p>Poison Shield</p>
<p>I grant you the power of a poison shield.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell protects the recipient from the next attack with the word "poison" in the verbal. It is then immediately used up. It will not protect against ingested elixirs. When used, the call is "Poison Shield."</p>
<p>Purify Blood</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to purify your blood</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will cleanse the recipient's blood, removing any and all alchemical effects or monster effects with the word "poison" in the verbal that are currently active on the character,  even beneficial ones. It will also remove the effects Berserk, Feeblemind, Forget-it-Well, Forget-Me-Not, Hallucinoid, Intoxicant, Nausea, Paranoia, and Vertigo regardless of the delivery type. It will not remove a Poison Shield or Enslavement. It is also a very good in-game cure for an in-game hangover. Purify Blood will not cure any damage previously wrought by a numerical poison effect.</p>
<p>Refit Armor</p>
<p>I summon a force to refit this armor.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell instantly refits armor to its full value This spell only works on actual physical armor.</p>
<p>Reflect Magic</p>
<p>I call fourth mystic power to reflect magic.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell will reflect the next spell cast at the recipient back upon the caster, after which it is used up. The recipient must say "Reflect Magic" to inform the caster that the spell was returned. The original caster is still the caster of the spell. This spell lasts until used up or Dispelled, and cannot be used in conjunction with a Shield Magic. If you have a Reflect Magic active, you may still "accept" spells that are touchcast. You cannot "accept" thrown spells. See"Spell Disruption" on page 46 for more details. Reflect Magic will only work on spells delivered via packet, Glyph (See the Formal Magic section for more details), or Spell Strike.</p>
<p>Regeneration</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to regenerate you.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 1 Minute</p>
<p>This spell restores a living target to his or her full body points. Once the spell is successfully cast, the target will begin to regenerate as per the rules of the special ability Regeneration. Regeneration requires that the character stand or sit in one place for one minute and concentrate If this process is interrupted before its completion, the spell is lost for no effect. The target may not be restored to a total of body higher than is appropriate for his race and level via this spell. This spell may not be used to aid a dead character in any way. This spell only affects targets which are healed by earth magic. This spell does not remove any other negative effects.</p>
<p>Release</p>
<p>With mystic force I release you.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will release a creature caught in a Pin, Bind, Web or Confine effect, as well as negating all active Paste of Stickiness effects upon the creature. It will not free someone who has been Paralyzed or Imprisoned. A Release spell can also be used to free someone bound by any non-magical means (such as handcuffed, tied up, or gripped by a tentacle). It will not unlock a cell door, but will open a stock if the creature is locked in one.</p>
<p>Remove Curse</p>
<p>I rid you of your curse.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will cancel a Curse spell but will not restore any Body Points lost. It will not rid anyone of a Gypsy Curse.</p>
<p>Remove Drain</p>
<p>I rid you of your drain.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>The target of this spell is cured of the drain effect but not of the Drain Life effect which still requires a Life spell to remove.</p>
<p>Remove Fear</p>
<p>I rid you of your fear.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will remove the effect fear from the target. The caster may continue to perform the verse without actually casting the spell on a target each time the verse is stated without disrupting the spell.</p>
<p>Remove Physical Affliction</p>
<p>I rid you of your physical affliction.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will remove all currently active effects with Physical in the verbal from the target. Damage is not cured.</p>
<p>Remove Weakness</p>
<p>I rid you of your weakness.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will remove all active Weakness effects on a creature.</p>
<p>Repel</p>
<p>With mystic force I repel you.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Concentration</p>
<p>This spell requires the caster to hit a target and hold the hand used to throw the packet palm out, facing the recipient. The victim and the target must then stay at least 10 feet apart while the spell is in effect. When the spell is first cast, the recipient must move 10 feet away from the caster. After that, neither the recipient nor the caster may approach within 10 feet of each other; the caster cannot approach the recipient any easier than the recipient may approach the caster. Either could back away. If it is impossible for the recipient to move more than 10 feet away from the caster because of physical obstructions when the spell is cast, the caster must first attempt to move 10 feet away from the recipient. The caster must hold out a hand, palm out, towards the recipient. That hand cannot be used for any other purpose. This spell is not a charm effect and cannot be resisted with the racial ability Resist Charm.</p>
<p>Restore Limbs</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to restore you limbs.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell causes all of the target's Withered limbs to become usable and restored.</p>
<p>Sanctuary</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to grant you sanctuary.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell will remain in effect as long as the subject's hands are clasped overhead and they do not receive any body damage. The recipient is protected against all non-ranged attacks from undead creatures. Ranged attacks (such as spells, missile weapons, and gas globes) can affect the recipient. If you are unsure if an attacker is undead or not, you will be affected by them. You may not call a Hold or otherwise go out of game to ascertain their status. The character with a Sanctuary active may use no game abilities except touchcasting on themselves.  Attempting to pick up an item will disrupt the spell.</p>
<p>Shatter</p>
<p>I summon a force to shatter your <item>.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell may be cast upon any weapon or shield or any item up to a shield in size. It may also be cast at a creature, to affect such an item. This spell will not shatter a shield-like hole in something larger than a shield, nor will it have any effect on armor. The item affected is rendered completely useless. This spell will not work on an unshatterable item or a magically  protected item. Shattering an item that has other items within or fastened to it will destroy all of the items. This spell will shatter not only a shield but also any scrolls attached to the back. Shattering a box or door will set off any traps present as well as the items within. After the item is shattered the prop for the item remains, but is unusable.</p>
<p>Shield</p>
<p>With eldrich force I grant you a shield 5.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell gives the recipient five extra Armor Points. These extra points are the first Armor Points lost due to damage.</p>
<p>Shield Magic</p>
<p>I call fourth mystic power to shield magic.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell will cancel the next spell cast at the recipient, including beneficial spells, after which it is used up. You must say "Shield Magic" immediately when this spell is used. Shield Magic will only work on spells delivered via packet, Glyph (See the Formal Magic section for more details), or Spell Strike. Shield Magic cannot be used in conjunction with a Reflect Magic. If you have a Shield Magic active, you may still "accept" spells that are touch-cast. You cannot "accept" thrown spells. See "Spell Disruption" on page 46 for more details.</p>
<p>Shun</p>
<p>I command you to shun me.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>This spell causes the victim to feel great discomfort around the caster. The victim will not attack the caster, and will immediately move at least 10 feet away from the caster and stay at least that far away while the spell is in effect. If the victim is within the 10 feet when the spell is cast, the victim must move away, but never in a manner that will endanger the victim or cause direct harm to them. In other words, they cannot be made to jump off a cliff or walk towards a magical rift or do any other action which would cause harm (much like a Charm spell cannot force the victim to take self-destructive actions). This spell does not create a 10 foot magical circle around the caster which is effective only upon the vic tim; if the victim has to come closer than ten feet in order to get away (say for example, to pass close to the caster in order to get to an exit), then that is permissible. While within that 10 foot area however, the victim can take no in-game actions against the caster. If the caster attacks the target, the Shun ends immediately. This spell is a type of charm and can be resisted with the racial ability Resist Charm, and it can be cured with an Aw aken spell or Dispel Magic spell. Stronger charms such as Vampire Charm or Enslavement will override its effects. See Table 5-6 on page 64</p>
<p>Shun Animal</p>
<p>I command this animal to shun me.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>This acts as a Shun spell, but will only affect an ordinary animal.</p>
<p>Silence</p>
<p>I command you to silence.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 minutes</p>
<p>The victim of this spell cannot talk and cannot cast any spell. The victim must still call out the damage points his or her weapons do if combat ensues while the spell is in effect, as well as any out-of-game trigger phrases such as Reflect Magic or Parry. The silence can be removed by either Aw aken or Dispel Magic. This is not a charm spell and thus it cannot be resisted by those with the Resist Charm ability.</p>
<p>Silver Aura</p>
<p>I grant you the power of a silver aura.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell will allow the recipient to use the weapon type silver against one opponent in the manner of a critical attack. It will not confer any additional damage. The target may choose to end the effect at any time but cannot reactivate it without using another casting of the spell. The spell may be stacked with two other Blade Effects see Table 5-6 on page 64 , but the spells will only work one at a time.</p>
<p>Sleep</p>
<p>I command you to sleep.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 minutes</p>
<p>Sleep causes the target to instantly fall into a deep sleep. The target will not awaken for 5 minutes unless someone shakes them vigorously while shouting for them to wake. It takes one minute of shaking and shouting to wake a person this way. An Awaken or Dispel Magic spell will wake the victim immediately. This spell will not work on some creatures without a metabolism, such as undead creatures, golems, or some giant insects. It can be resisted by creatures with a Resist Sleep ability.</p>
<p>Stabilize</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to stabilize you.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Continuous</p>
<p>When cast the target of this spell is stabilized as if the First Aid skill had been successfully used upon them. For this to work the target must have been able to be affected by the skill first aid. The caster may continue to perform the verse without actually casting the spell on a target each time the verse is stated without breaking the spell.</p>
<p>Stone Bolt</p>
<p>I call fourth a stone bolt 25.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell deals 25 points of eldritch stone damage to the victim.</p>
<p>Taint Blood</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to taint your blood.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell will introduce impurities into the victims blood. The victim is left extremely weak, and unable to fight or move faster than normal walking speed. The victim becomes unable to use any game skills. This spell might not function against creatures with no metabolism. This spell can be removed by a Purify Blood spell or a Dispel Magic spell.</p>
<p>Tarry</p>
<p>I grant you the gift of tarrying.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>The target of this spell must be dead and within their five minute death count and able to benefit from a Life spell. The target will have their death count extended by five minutes. This spell can be cast on a target multiple times but they must have five minutes or less left on their death count or it will not work and the spell will be lost. Tarry cannot extend a death count past the time of reset and if it has already extended the count past the initial five minutes when reset occurs the effect will end and the character will go to resurrect. This spell can never be used to allow the target to receive a life spell gained in the next reset period if the initial death count expired during the previous reset period. It can never be used to force a character to take multiple castings of the obliterate formal. At any point past the initial five minute death count the target may chose to end their count and r esurrect immediately, a spirit may not be held for longer than their initial five minutes using a tarry against their will even if enslaved or controlled in any other manner.</p>
<p>Trap Undead</p>
<p>I call upon the earth to trap undead.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Line of Sight</p>
<p>This spell will act upon a lesser undead as a Pin spell, but the undead may not rip free. This spell will not affect a living target, although it will remove a living person's Shield Magic or Reflect Magic.</p>
<p>Turn Undead</p>
<p>I Call upon the earth to turn undead.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 Minutes</p>
<p>This spell will affect lesser undead creatures, causing them to leave the area of combat immediately by attempting to break Line of Sight. A Dispel Magic or Free Undead will rid the  creature of this spell, allowing it to return. Greater undead are not affected by this spell in the same manner. This spell will not affect a living target, although it will remove any creature's Shield Magic or Reflect Magic.</p>
<p>Unparalyze</p>
<p>I rid you of your paralysis.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:Yes</p>
<p>Duration: Instant</p>
<p>This spell will free the subject from all paralyzing effects.</p>
<p>Ward</p>
<p>With eldrich force I build a ward.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:No        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: 5 days</p>
<p>This spell magically seals a single room or an entire building. The object affected must be an actual unmovable structure such as a building, a tent, or an unmovable wagon. No effect, person or object may pass through the Ward unless as described below. Anyone within the Ward during the entire casting of the spell will receive an Investiture to the Ward. The names of the people Invested must be written in the room's marshal notes. Investiture in a Ward allows you to enter and leave the warded area at will as well as allow others to enter and leave by saying "The Ward recognizes you", and otherwise follows the rules for Extended Circles of Power described on page 50. The building must be visibly marked to indicate the presence of Ward by placing a large "W" on the door. This spell takes five minutes to cast during which time the caster rests his hand upon the primary portal. Anyone inside a structure that is being warded will be aware of the casting and will be awoken by it if normally sleeping. This spell cannot be thrown. Ward is not be affected by Dispel Magic.</p>
<p>Weakness</p>
<p>I curse you with weakness.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell will curse the victim to do 5 points less damage with every swing (minimum damage being zero, of course). This spell does not actually reduce a creature's strength. It affects all weapon damage in the same way, whether the weapon is used with one hand or two hands. This spell lasts until removed with a Remove Weakness or a Dispel Magic. Multiple Weakness effects do not stack.</p>
<p>Web</p>
<p>With mystic force I web you.</p>
<p>Celestial:Yes    :: Scroll: Yes</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion No</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Line of Sight</p>
<p>This spell snares the arms of its victim, binding them straight to its sides, and immobilizes the victim completely from the neck down. The victim may talk freely, but may not use any game skills requiring use of the arms, including using a weapon or shield, casting a spell, or activating a gas globe. The victim may not walk, run, or be moved in any way. Any item the victim is holding cannot be dropped. However, since the effect allows the victim to be searched, anyone else can choose to physically remove a hand-held item from the victim simply by  searching them. Even a victim with Superhuman Strength cannot prevent himself from being "searched" in this manner. This spell does not prevent the victim from being searched or being given a Killing Blow.</p>
<p>Wither Limb</p>
<p>I call upon chaos to wither your <Limb>.</p>
<p>Celestial:No    :: Scroll: No</p>
<p>Earth:Yes        ::Potion Yes</p>
<p>Manifold:No</p>
<p>Duration: Indefinate</p>
<p>This spell causes the target's limb to become aged and infirm. The limb may be specified by the caster (right or left leg or arm). You can have up to four Wither Limb spells upon you at a time. No weapon may be wielded by that limb nor may the limb be used for locomotion or spell casting. If a leg is withered you must kneel down (unless you can't due to a medical reason), you may not hop on the remaining leg. Only an arm or leg can be thus withered. Tentacles or similar appendages are considered arms for this purpose. The head, tongue, or any other such organ do not count as limbs. A Dispel Magic will remove all active Wither Limb spells. If the caster does not specify, or if the spell is received from a potion or carrier attack, then it is the target's choice as to which currently un-withered limb becomes withered. If all your limbs are withered, call "got it." See "Stacked Effects" on page 47.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Common Formal Magic Spells</p>
<p>Formal Magic Scrolls are magical scrolls of immense power in and of themselves and will always detect as magical. They are treated as Magic Items for purposes of stealing. A Formal Magic scroll can only be read or copied by one who has the skill Formal Magic in the appropriate school. To everyone else, the scroll will be unreadable.</p>
<p>Here is a description of some of the most common types of Formal Magic effects on Magic Items. This is not a complete list, but merely the ones which most players will encounter. Please see the Formal Magic Casting Rules and individual Formal Magic Spell descriptions for more details.</p>
<p>Bane</p>
<p>A magical defense that reflects the attack back upon the attacker. It works at will (even before a spell defense if desired), and protects against only one type of effect. For example, a Bane versus Sleep could be used against a Sleep spell or a Sleep gas poison.</p>
<p>Cloak</p>
<p>A magical defense that works at will (even before a spell defense if desired) and protects against only one type of effect such as Fire or Binding Magic. For example, a Cloak versus Fire could be used against both a Flame Bolt spell or an Elemental flame packet attack.</p>
<p>Obliteration</p>
<p>A very powerful Formal Magic that causes the victim to suffer the same effect as dying and resurrecting three times, although only one trip to the Earth circle is necessary. However, only one pick is made from deaths bag. After the Formal Magic is complete, the victim is still able to receive a Life spell for the next five minutes, and only one such spell is necessary to restore the creature to one body point. If a Life spell is received, the creature is not forced to resurrect at all.</p>
<p>Spirit Link</p>
<p>Spirit Link magically attaches an item to a spirit, thus making it unstealable. The item must always remain in contact with the creature to which it is linked. (It does not have to touch the body directly; a glove or other piece of clothing can come between the item and the person.) When a creature with a Spirit Linked item dies, the Spirit Linked item becomes insubstantial with the spirit and travels to resurrect, reforming with the spirit. If the item is a container, it does not bring the contents with it. If the creature permanently dies, the body and item return to the point where the body dissipated. The item is then linked to the next creature with a spirit that takes picks it up, even through gloves or other articles of clothing or armor.</p>
<p>Spirit Mark</p>
<p>Used to mark a particular persons spirit. The mark is always present on the spirits body, in the location and with a design as decided by the original Formal Magic caster. This mark can be covered by normal means. </p>
<p>Vengeance</p>
<p>Causes a retributive strike of pure magical damage to any being inflicting a killing blow upon the bearer of this formal magic. This damage occurs after the killing blow and is not avoidable in any manner. When a Vengeance is triggered, the call will be <number> Arcane Vengeance</p>
<p>Formal Magic Components</p>
<p>In order to cast a spell from a Formal Magic scroll, one must also have the Formal Magic Components. These components are represented in-game by a tag with a description of the item and its level and type. Some chapters also provide the actual prop itself. If your chapter does not, it can only increase your role-playing fun if you were to provide your own props. </p>
<p>Formal Magic Components may be found as treasure in a module, on an NPC, or randomly in the woods. </p>
<p>Any character can tell if they are looking at a formal component automatically. To identify the level and type of components (i.e. P4 or C1) you must possess one level of the formal magic skill of either school.</p>
<p>Components come in various flavors: Power (P), Creation (C), Elemental (E), Time (T), Void (V), Destruction (D), Spirit (S).</p>
<p>Each component has a value of 1, 2 or 4. Formal Magic costs are listed with the total value of each type of needed component. For example, P5 means any combination of Power components totaling a value of 5. One spell, Gr eater Extension, specifically requires a Power component of value 2 or 4 in addition to other components. Components expire no longer than 2 years after the issue date.If there is no printed expiration date then the expiration date is assumed to be one year.</p>
<p>Extended Circles of Power</p>
<p>In order to use the powers of an Extended Circle, you must be Invested in that Circle. Investiture is a Formal Magic Spell that must be cast upon you in that Circle.</p>
<p>In order to pass into or out of the Circle, you must be recognized by an invested member of the Circle. The invested member must clearly gesture, touch, or name the subject creature and must state the Circle recognizes you. This is an out-of-game statement, so it can be made while Silenced. The effect is understood in-game by all who hear it.</p>
<p>Upon being recognized, a person must immediately enter or exit the Circle. If the recognized person does not immediately act upon the recognition, then the recognition will expire.  </p>
<p>Invested members may walk freely into or out of the Circle, since it is assumed that they recognize themselves. Invested members who are unconscious (or conscious, yet unwilling) will not pass through the Circle unless recognized by someone else. When using combat skills or spells, you must be completely inside or outside of the Circle of Power. For example, you cannot begin a spell incant inside the Circle, and then step out to throw your packet.</p>
<p>If you want to raid a Circle of Power, the same rules as raiding a cabin will apply; you must have a marshal present. See Searching a Cabin on page 95</p>
<p>Identify</p>
<p>An Extended Celestial Circle is capable of performing an Identify on an item or person. The item or person to be Identified and the invested person performing the Identify must be within the circle completely. The invested person touches the target of the identify and says Identify.</p>
<p>If the target is an object directly then the invested person reads the tag describing the items properties and learns them in the time it takes to read the information.</p>
<p>If the target is a person then the target tells the invested person which active spells or Formal Magic spells are active on them as well as what magical items they have in their possession and what the properties of those items are and how to activate them as though the items had been directly identified by the invested person. Sometimes an Identify will reveal additional properties of magical creatures. It takes as long to perform an identification of a person as it does for the target to describe all of the results.</p>
<p>Everyone who hears or observes the Identify call/process is aware of an identification taking place though they should attempt not to overhear the results. If you are Out of Game able to tell who the person performing the identification is, then you know who it is in game as well. If a transform is active and Identified, the school of it and the name of it are revealed, but neither the presence nor any information about a dormant transformation is revealed. You can prevent an Identification unless youre helpless.</p>
<p>The time to Identify is In Game. If youre interrupted then you are interrupted (including if contact is broken by the subject). </p>
<p>While there is no set order to presenting the information and you decide where to start, you must give out all the information you have with the chance of 3rd party interruption</p>
<p>Resurrection</p>
<p>An Extended Earth Circle is capable of providing Resurrections.</p>
<p>The spirit to be Resurrected must be in the Circle. This will take 5 minutes to complete and will bring a body to full body points.</p>
<p>During the 5 minutes, it is apparent to all observers that a resurrection is occurring, although the exact identity is unrecognizable to all except the invested healer performing the resurrection. The</p>
<p>healer may choose to reveal the identity of the person they are resurrecting, if desired. For more on resurrections, see "Matters of Life and Death" on page 22.</p>
<p>Magic Items</p>
<p>Magic items can be found or made through the NERO Formal Magic System. Most give the wearer the ability to utilize a spell and some items grant the wearer effects from the Formal Magic system.</p>
<p>Until you have an item Identified, you will not have the tag for the item and thus will not be able to use it, even if you are already aware of the item's power. You must proceed to the Mages' Guild or monster camp to receive the tag. If you are given the item and are told in-game what the item's powers are and how it is used, you may use the item but must go to the Mages Guild or monster camp immediately thereafter to get the tag. Make sure that any player that gives you a Magic Item phys-rep also gives you the Magic Item Tag.</p>
<p>Activating Magic Items</p>
<p>Spells from a magic item act just like a regular spell. They provide the character, no matter what class or level, the ability to use that spell. The correct process to activate an item is to use the phrase "Activate" followed by the spell incant. For Example: "Activate With Mystic Force I Bind You".</p>
<p>In addition, all the normal rules for casting apply. You must have your hand free, have a packet, be conscious, etc. So you cannot activate an item when in a Web, unconscious, dead, or when tied up. Activating an item IS NOT a Game Ability, so you CAN use an item when you cannot otherwise use a Game Ability or Skill, such as when under the effects of a Taint Blood spell.</p>
<p>Magic Item Slots</p>
<p>Chapters may specify how many magic items a player may have active at any given time. This number is between one and five and is clearly posted at event check-in or on the chapter's website.</p>
<p>If a character has more items on them than the allowed limit they must have a clearly delineated method to separate the active and inactive magic items tags. In order to switch between an active and inactive item at least one minute must be spent while you physically switch your tags between active and inactive. You may only make one switch at a time. If you lose possession of a magic item tag that item becomes inactive for you. During this time you may use no game skills. Characters must be conscious with at least one hand free to switch items between active and inactive states.</p>
<p>The following Formal Magic Spells will not cease to work on a magic item when it goes from active to inactive: Render Indestructible, Extend Form al Magic, Gr eater Extension, Spirit Link, Spirit Lock, and Delimit.</p>
<p>Any item can still be used while inactive, but only with the benefit of the effects listed above.</p>
<p>This limitation on active magic items applies to both Unrestricted and Local Chapter Only Items only as a total (ex: 2 LCO and 3 Unrestricted "active" items in a 5 item slot campaign.)</p>
<p>Spirit as Magic Item</p>
<p>For only the purposes of Magic Item Slots, a character's Spirit counts as a single magic item that can be made active as a whole.</p>
<p>Only the following formal magic spells count for the purposes of this "item:" Enchant, Cloak (Minor), Bane (Minor), Spell Store, Protection Aura, Cloak, Bane, Expanded Enchantment, Spirit Link, Spirit Lock. All other Spirit targeting formal magic spells fall outside of the Magic Item Slot rules. Please note that Spirit Link and Spirit Lock do not cease to work on an item that has been made inactive. </p>
<p>A PC is always aware of all formal magic spells on their spirit, including, school, specific type, and duration as applicable. </p>
</body></Root>