<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Root xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/"><body>
<h2>Physical Rerepresentation</h2>
<p>If you acquire any potions, scrolls, poisons, or alchemical substances during your adventures, then they should have appropriate Tags attached. If you create your own through the Production system, then you must supply a physical representation for the item, and the tag must be attached. This physical representation can be stolen, at which point the thief will take the tag and the item.</p>
<p>A scroll or potion that does not have a tag attached cannot be used. If the tag is lost, stolen or destroyed, the item is not usable. The tag by itself is not the item. If someone hands you an out-of-game tag and says "Here, drink this!" you should reply "Drink what?" since nothing is being shown to your character in-game. This rule exists because after all, these things take up room and add weight. You can't carry around 100 potions as easily as you could 100 tags.</p>
<p>If your character finds or is given a magic weapon, you are sometimes given a physical representation for it (You should return it to the NERO Chapter you found it in when its magic expires). You cannot alter the weapon in any way except to repair it when needed. If the phys-rep wears out, then another must be built that looks just like the original. Magic items cannot ever be modified and must always look the same. This has the advantage of making it easy to spot your stolen sword if you should ever see it again. See "So you want to be a thief?" on page XX.</p>
<h3>Game Items</h3>
<p>All game items (such as jewelry and magic items) should be labeled with a number. This is for the marshals to be able to tell the worth of the item and the magic use (if any).</p>
<p>If you steal an item that does not have a number on it, then you should immediately return it as it is obviously personal property and not part of the game. See "So you want to be a thief?" on page XX.</p>
<h3>Armor</h3>
<h4>Armor points</h4>
<p>There are three ways a player may possess Armor Points: Physical Armor, Dexterity Armor, and Arcane Armor. The three types may be used together and add to your total of Armor Points. You can not use more armor points than your character can wear.</p>
<h4>Wear Points</h4>
<p>Your character's Wear Point total is the limit of armor points you can use or "Wear" at one time. Your base Wear Point total depends on your class, as  shown in figure 7-1.</p>
<h4>Wear Bonuses</h4>
<p>You can add Wear Points to your base by purchasing the skill wear extra armor or by wearing good costuming.</p>
<p>Wear Extra Armor: The skill wear extra armor adds 5 wear points per purchase to your characters wear point total up to a maximum of 40 points.</p>
<p>Costume Bonus: Any player will be awarded five wear points simply for being fully in costume with their entire visible costume fully fitting with the in game atmosphere see "Costumes" on page 121. A marshal must be consulted to see if your costume warrants the bonus. You should do this at every chapter you go to as some chapters have different criteria to make this decision.</p>
<p>The maximum Wear total a player can have is 40 (45 with good costuming), no effect can augment this bonus higher by any means. Armor points granted by the spell "Shield" are considered Armor but do not count toward your Wear Point total. </p>
<p>Example, Mandrake the scholar has 10 base wear points, he purchases Wear extra armor and now has 15 wear points. His costume is reviewed by a marshal and is given the 5 wear points for costuming. So he can now wear up to 20 Armor points.</p>
<h4>Physical Armor</h4>
<p>The Physical Armor Types are Leather, Chain Mail, and Plate. Table 7-6 shows the value of each Armor Type for each Body Location. Each location is worth one point for leather, two points for chain, and three points for plate except the chest and back which are worth three times as much since they cover a larger area. </p>
<p>A suit of armor may be rejected at any point on grounds of safety for such things including, but not limited to; protrusions, sharp edges, and unsafe materials.</p>
<p>Characters may select the armor type to use at each separate body location, making it easier for players to create their own personalized armor. Each location is considered covered in armor if at least three quarters of the entire area is covered. Locations with overlapping armor types count as the higher type. </p>
<p>A Suit of Armor is evaluated by adding the armor point value for each body location covered.</p>
<p>Armor does not have to be real to count for armor points, so long as it looks real.</p>
<p>The tag for armor allows a character to gain protection from a phys-rep rated up to the value on the tag. To claim the entire value of an armor tag the player must wear a phys-rep which has been evaluated by a marshal to be worth at least the value of the tag, you cannot wear 20 points of coverage, have a 30 point tag and claim 30 points of armor in game.</p>
<p>Leather: Leather is any material, natural or synthetic, that looks like leather.</p>
<p>Chain Mail: Chain Mail is made of material of interlocking links whose holes are small enough not to easily catch a finger.</p>
<p>Plate: Is armor made of rigid material that does not easily deform, or of material that accurately recreates the look of plate, either medieval or fantasy. Plate is made up or large pieces of metal or metal looking material.</p>
<h3>Refitting Physical Armor</h3>
<p>When a suit of armor takes damage it can be refitted to its full value. Refitting in this way can only be done by the armor? wearer, and requires that the person spend an uninterrupted minute during which he can use no other game skills, cannot walk around, or be struck in any way. You may choose to interrupt yourself at any time. During the refitting the character will adjust (i.e. tighten straps, reposition plates) his armor so that it offers the best protection possible. If the character is struck by any packet or weapon, the refit is interrupted for no effect and must be begun again.</p>
<p>The smithing special ability Rapid refit and the spell Refit Armor can also refit physical armor.</p>
<h1>Weapons</h1>
<h2>Weapon Combat</h2>
<p>Safety is always the primary concern in weapon construction. Unfortunately, even the safest weapon could cause injury if improperly used. Therefore, in addition to safe weapon construction guidelines, practice in the use of the weapon is needed to ensure that all players enjoy the game as much as possible. Below are additional restrictions on specific weapons</p>
<p>Latex Weapons: may never be used for thrusting, stabbing or poking.</p>
<p>Blunt Weapons: If a blunt weapon does not have a "head" on it, it will inflict one less point of damage than normal. Blunt weapons may not be used for thrusting, and are required to have a padded thrusting tip for safety reasons.</p>
<p>Bows: You can use the bow in combat for blocking, but you may not attack with it. Once it blocks an attack, the bowstring is considered cut or unstrung by combat. The PC cannot fire arrows from it until he restrings the Bow (see below). For safety reasons, no taut bowstrings are allowed though a loose one may be used to sling the bow for carrying.</p>
<p>Restringing involves at least 3 seconds of role-play. No physical representations for extra bow strings are needed.</p>
<p>To Fire, the Bow must be held in front of the archer at arm's length and must be aimed at the target when the packet is thrown. The archer must take the packet out of the quiver, touch the packet to the hand holding the bow, then throw. The packet must be thrown in the normal flight path of an arrow fired from the bow. It cannot be thrown overhead or around corners. It cannot be "flicked." The damage call must be completed before throwing the packet.</p>
<p>The hand throwing the arrow (yellow packet) is the hand that concerns Proficiencies. Master Proficiencies carry over to archery. </p>
<p>All Vorpal Poisons, Enchanted Blade, Silver Aura and Elemental Blade spells work normally. Vorpal tags are to be taped to the bow, not the packet.</p>
<p>Damage Aura or Magic Aura upon a bow confers the ability for the archer to throw packets for the weapon type "Magic." All weapons that fall under the skill Archery will have the weapon type of each missile altered if the weapon itself is targeted by a magical aura of any type. This includes a Damage Aura, Elemental Aura, and/or Magic Aura, and means that each individual missile does not need to be targeted by the formal magic spell in order to create the desired effect.</p>
<p>Bows that are un-shatterable still need to be restrung after blocking.</p>
<p>Real bows and arrows are not permitted.</p>
<p>Spears: One handed spears can only be used to perform thrusting attacks and can never be thrown. A character hit by any part of a spear other than the 8 inch head takes no damage.</p>
<p>Two handed weapons: Two handed weapons must be used with both hands at all times. If you lose the use of one arm (as from a Wither Limb effect), then you cannot wield the weapon at all.</p>
<h2>Weapon Safety Checks</h2>
<p>Before every NERO event, all weapons must be approved at check-in by the weapons marshal. Since the requirements the construction of weapons are fairly strict, it is not unusual for a weapon to be disqualified at check-in. Even a weapon which qualified at a previous event may be disqualified (Weapons do wear out). NERO reserves the right to fail any weapon that is deemed unsafe or hazardous.</p>
<p>Any experimental weapon using unusual materials can fail safety check at any time. Bring a couple of standard weapons with you as a backup in case yours fails inspection. Often the deficiency can be corrected with the addition of a little open cell foam or tape, so it is good to bring these extra supplies with you in case your weapon is not allowed so you can fix it.</p>
<p>If you are having trouble with weapon construction, then bring what you have so far to a NERO event, and you can show it to the marshals who will give you a hand when they can. The old saying "Practice makes perfect" is especially true with both weapon making and use.</p>
<h3>Weapon Tags</h3>
<p>Every weapon must have two tags. The first is the Weapon Safety Tag. This tag proves that your weapon has gone through safety check and is approved to be used for that event this tag will be affixed to the weapon.</p>
<p>The second tag is the Weapon Tag. This is the tag that shows that the weapon is in-game. When you purchase a weapon from a weaponsmith or from logistics, you will be buying this tag to keep on you.</p>
<p>A player may only carry as many tags as he/she has physical representations.</p>
<p>Some weapons can be strengthened to withstand two or more Destroy or Shatter spells. When you have this done to your weapon, you will be given a new tag to reflect the changes. Weapons can also be silvered which can be very useful when fighting certain monsters, as with strengthening, you will receive a new tag. See Smithing on page 42.</p>
<h3>Weapon Construction</h3>
<p>Weapon combat is a large part of the NERO game. Because of NERO's reliance on weapons, proper weapon construction is necessary to insure safe yet semi-realistic combat.</p>
<p>The guidelines in this section cover making a boffer weapon and choosing a latex or other manufactured weapon for play in the NERO game.</p>
<h3>Pre-made weapons</h3>
<p>There are a number of manufactured weapons that fall into the NERO guidelines for safety. If you purchase a pre-made weapon, it is your responsibility to determine the type of construction that was used. You must know what type of core the weapon has and what type of foam was used. Latex weapons are not required to have a thrusting tip, and may never be used for thrusting, stabbing or poking.  Latex and boffer swords are available for sale and many can be used for NERO combat resolution. A current list of approved vendors and styles for latext weapons as well as latex weapon construction guidelines can be found online at www.nerolarp.com </p>
<h4>Make Your own</h4>
<p>You may also choose to make your own boffer or latex foam weapons. Making a weapon can range from very simple to very hard depending on the materials you choose and the design of your weapon. The following sections walk through the construction of a very simple weapon, but also provide information about some advanced materials you can try later on. It is highly recommended that you build a simple weapon for you first attempt.</p>
<p>There are a number of weapons that fit within a medieval fantasy setting that are not mentioned here. NERO allows creativity in developing new weapons but all must be approved before use. Experimental weapon types must conform to the basic standards of safety. You should check with the marshals before and during construction so that you do not end up wasting time and materials on a weapon that will not be allowed in the game, even so it still may not pass in all NERO chapters. </p>
<h4>Weapon Parts</h4>
<p>Below is a list of terms that will be useful to know when constructing a weapon. These terms detail sections of the weapon and what they are used for.</p>
<h3>Thrusting Tip</h3>
<p>A thrusting tip consists of at least two inches of open cell foam padding beyond the end of the pipe insulation. If the foam tip is too small, opponents could get hurt with a stiff thrust. If the tip is too large, it could easily break off or fold over, making it useless. All thrusting tips do count towards the weapon's overall length. The tip must collapse about 50% of its length when pressure is applied. The tip should also be the width of the weapon, and should not easily fit in an eye socket. Weapons with two possible striking ends, such as a staff, should have thrusting tips on both ends. For weapons with heads, the thrusting tip may be incorporated into the head design.</p>
<h3>Blade/Shaft</h3>
<p>This is the section of the weapon that is above the grip of the weapon. Blade/Shaft lengths of weapons can be determined by measuring from the end of the grip to the end of the thrusting tip. The Blade/Shaft area must be continuous 5/8" closed cell foam.</p>
<h5>Head</h5>
<p>Some weapons, such as a polearm, hammer, or spear, have an additional element(s) added to the weapon. The head(s) extend outwards from the shaft, must be a minimum of 6 inches in length along the shaft, must be made of open cell foam, and must be at least 1 inch thick or thicker. Each head can be a maximum of 2 cubic feet. The head must be positioned near the top of the weapon. </p>
<h3>Crossguard</h3>
<p>A crossguard is used in certain types of weapon and is a blocking surface that is perpendicular to the weapon. This blocking surface cannot have any kind of core inside of it, and can only be constructed of foam, and is a maximum length of 18" across.</p>
<h3>Grip</h3>
<p>This section of the weapon is the location where the weapon is held. With the exception of the special cases listed above, this section of the weapon does not need to be padded. The length of</p>
<p>the grip is the length of the weapon from the bottom of the blade/Shaft to the inside of the pommel see figure 7-1.</p>
<h3>Pommel</h3>
<p>The pommel is used to protect the butt end of a weapon; it is located at the end of the grip. The pommel should have closed cell foam that extends an inch past the end of the core and is then capped by a piece of closed cell foam.</p>
<h2>Weapon Specific Specs</h2>
<p>Certain weapons types may have additional requirements, which can be found below.</p>
<h3>Bow</h3>
<p>The NERO Bow (referred to hereafter as Bow) must be curved and formed in the shape of a bow. Overall length in a straight line from tip to tip must be between 34 and 58 inches. Thrusting tips must be on both ends.</p>
<h3>Crossbow</h3>
<p>The NERO Crossbow (referred to hereafter as Bow) must be a T-shape, with a stock length of 12 to 24 inches. The cross piece must be at least half the stock length and may not exceed 24 inches. Thrusting tips must be on all ends.</p>
<h3>Arrows/Bolts</h3>
<p>These are represented by yellow packets. Yellow packets are considered in-game items until they are fired and cannot be held in the same hand as another game item while either item is in use.</p>
<p>Arrows are always stoppable by Shields and weapons.</p>
<p>Quiver: An archer needs a Quiver in which they must carry their shots. There are 30 shots (arrows, bolts, etc.) in each quiver. Each time the character shoots his missile weapon whether he hits or the character shoots his missile weapon whether he hits or misses his target, a single shot is lost from his quiver.</p>
<p>Arrows and other missiles (bolts, etc.) are not recoverable items. Thrown Weapons such as small thrown weapons and javelins are recoverable.</p>
<p>Each quiver physical representation must be able to hold at least 30 yellow packets and, look like a real quiver. Each quiver can hold no more than 30 yellow packets, and a character cannot have  tags for more than 30 yellow packets per quiver rep on his person. The archer may carry as many quivers as he wants, as long as he has a physical representation for each.</p>
<h3>Daggers/One Handed Swords/Two Handed Swords</h3>
<p>Daggers, one handed swords, and two handed swords all follow the same basic construction guidelines. Each sword-type weapon has a blade, crossguard and pommel, and a grip area. There may be no gaps in foam between the top of the grip and the thrusting tip at the end of the blade.</p>
<p>In the case of swords without a perpendicular-style crossguard, such as katana, the blade area may extend from the top of the grip to the thrusting tip.</p>
<h3>Maces/Axes/Hammers (Bludgeon/Hatchet/Sap)</h3>
<p>There are five main parts to all maces, axes and hammers: the pommel, grip, shaft, head and thrusting tip. With the exception of the head that must be crafted of open cell foam, all styles are the same basic design. Weapons that do not have areas of 1" thick open cell foam, which have pointed edges, or areas that "catch" other weapons may be deemed unacceptable by any marshal. Axes may have a crossguard incorporated into the design. A Bludgeon is a small mace, a Hatchet is a small Axe, and a Sap is a small hammer.</p>
<h3>Polearms/Spears</h3>
<p>There are five main parts to all polearms and spears: the pommel,grip, shaft, head and thrusting tip. The thrusting tip is often incorporated into the head of polearms in order to reduce the tendency for it to shear off on a swing, and the thrusting tip for a spear should be incorporated into the head of the spear. Spears may only be used for thrusting. Spears and polearms may both have a crossguard incorporated into the design. </p>
<h3>Staves</h3>
<p>A staff is very simple to make, with whole of the core covered by foam, or you may have two hand holds not covered by foam. A staff must have thrusting tips on both ends. The middle 6" of the staff must be padded with a minimum of 1/2" thick pipe insulation.</p>
<h3>Thrown Weapons</h3>
<p>Thrown rocks, throwing stars, thrown daggers, javelins and other thrown weapons may not contain a core of any sort. Rocks must be made of a 6" x 6" or larger piece of open cell foam, and can be covered with duct tape, kite tape or fabric. Throwing stars, daggers or axes may be made of closed cell foam with no core, and should be cut into the appropriate shape, with tips not less than 2" wide. All thrown weapons must be a minimum of 6" long and may be a maximum of 18": long. </p>
<p>A javelin must be made of 3 feet of closed cell pipe foam with thrusting tips at both ends. A javelin may not include a core of any sort.</p>
<p>Thrown weapons may not be used in melee combat, they must be thrown. Since there is a wide range of shapes and sizes that can be used, approval is based on a case by case basis by the weapons marshal.</p>
<h2>Weapon Safety Guidelines</h2>
<p>Please see the NERO International Website www.nerolarp.com for the most updated information regarding weapon safety rules. There are several basic rules regarding weapon construction in NERO and they are as follows:</p>
<p>All weapons must all within the minimum and maximum length, grip and blade requirements for their weapon type.</p>
<p>All weapons must be approved by a NERO safety marshal before they can be used in play.</p>
<p>All home made weapons must have a thrusting tip.</p>
<p>All weapons must be padded from the tip of the blade to the hand grip. All weapons must be padded with at least 5/8 inch wall thickness closed cell foam regardless of blade size.</p>
<p>A weapon must have at least 0.5 inch but no more than 1.5 inches of closed cell foam extending beyond the end of the core before the thrusting tip is added.</p>
<p>All tips must be rendered safe with tape/cloth and padding. In a melee, it is possible to accidentally hit someone with the pommel or cross guard, so these parts must be protected as well.</p>
<p>All blade areas or areas of the weapon that may come in contact with another player must be protected with at least 5/8 inch weapons such as axes, hammers, maces, etc.</p>
<p>All weapons must be fairly rigid so as not to act as a whip when swung quickly. Under most circumstances, a weapon tip should not bend more than 6 inches from true when moderate force is applied to the tip and the grip is held level. Conversely, all weapons must also have some give to them when contact is made.</p>
<h2>Construction Materials</h2>
<h2>Core</h2>
<p>The core is the interior portion of a weapon that gives it strength and rigidity. There are several materials that can be used for cores including various types of PVC piping, some types of spiral wound fiberglass tubing, and several other types of materials. Please note that you may never use wood or heavy metals as part of your core in weapon construction.</p>
<p>The core of the weapon can be made of different materials based on the size of the weapon to be constructed.</p>
<p>Below is an overview of suggested cores and the types of weapons that can be created with each material.</p>
<h2>Standard</h2>
<p>The standard core for weapons is PVC of which there are 2 types: white PVC used in plumbing and grey PVC or CPVC used for electrical work. The following list uses the inner diameter of the tubing. Please note that schedule 20 CPVC has a thin wall and is more flexible than schedule 40 CPVC. If you use schedule 20, use one size higher based on the weapon you are making.</p>
<p>1/2 inch: This core can be used to make small and short and long weapons. This type of core has more give and should not be used in weapons longer than 46 inches.</p>
<p>3/4 inch: This core can be used to make two handed weapons.</p>
<h2>Ultralight</h2>
<p>Ultralight cores include carbon fiber, kitespar tube, fiberglass tube, and wrapped graphite tube. Aluminum core may only be used for polearms and staves. These material can be used to make most weapons, however the diameter of the kite pole determines which type of weapon it is best suited for. The following list uses the outer dimension of the tubing.</p>
<p>0.414 inch: This core can be used to make small, short and long weapons. This type of core has more give and should not be used in weapons longer than 46 inches. Please note that depending on the style of weapon construction, this core may have too much give at the maximum length for long weapons.</p>
<p>0.505 inch: This core can be used to make short and long weapons and spears. This type of core has more give and should not be used in weapons longer than 54 inches.</p>
<p>0.610 inch: This core can be used to make staves, two handed weapons and spears. This type of core has more give and should not be used in weapons longer than 64 inches.</p>
<p>0.745 inch: This core can be used for all two handed weapons. This type of core should not be used in weapons shorter than 54 inches.</p>
<h2>Closed Cell Foam</h2>
<p>This durable water resistant material is used in the construction of weapons in NERO. There are three types of closed cell foam that can be used for weapon construction: Pipe foam insulation, Pool Noodle, and Camp pad.</p>
<p>Pipe foam Insulation: The most common type of closed cell foam is pipe foam insulation. Closed cell pipe foam insulation is used to pad the blades of weapons, and must be at least 5/8 inch wall thickness. Please note that most foam found in home improvement stores does not posses the correct thickness.</p>
<p>Closed cell foam of the appropriate wall thickness can be difficult to locate. Currently the foam is available from a variety of places;</p>
<p>Merchantswares.com A LARP Gear supply house.</p>
<p>McMaster-Carr (a commercial tool company) and here is a list of part numbers:</p>
<p>Part #4530K161 is usable for .414" kite spar, .505" kite spar and 1/2" PVC.</p>
<p>Part #4530K162 is usable for .610" kite spar and 1/2" PVC.</p>
<p>Part #4530K163 is usable for .745" kite spar, 3/4" PVC.</p>
<p>Pool noodle: Pool noodle is thicker than pipe insulation, and not all pool noodles fit PVC. You should bring measuring tape or a piece of pipe with you when you buy it.</p>
<p>Camp Pad: This material is used to make more advanced, sculpted weapons. The average camp pad found in stores such as Walmart is 1/4" thick. To achieve the correct thickness you must laminate multiple pieces together with contact cement. Weapons made with this material are held up to more scrutiny. Visit www.nerolarp.com for specifications for sculpted weapons. You should not attempt to make your first weapon out of this material.</p>
<p>Open Cell Foam:This material is a less dense foam that is commonly used to stuff couches and pillows and is found in most fabric stores. This foam is used in the construction of thrusting tips, weapon heads and some thrown weapons. The foam should be easily squeezable and not too dense. Alternatively you can also use a car sponge found at hardware stores.</p>
<h2>Tapes</h2>
<p>There are several types of tape that are commonly used in weapon making:</p>
<p>Duct Tape: Duct tape is the standard type of tape used in weapon making. It can be used for blades, thrusting tips, crossguards, and pommels. Duct tape can be found in a variety of colors and various thicknesses. Certain types of duct tape are heavier and less suitable for weapon construction.</p>
<p>Kite Tape: Kite tape or Nylon rip stop repair tape is a type of tape that is used normally for fixing kites. It is an extremely light form of tape that can be used in weapon construction. It is available in a variety of colors and can be purchased from a number of kite supply stores.</p>
<p>Strapping Tape: Strapping tape is a tape that has strands that run vertically along the tape. It is used for securing portions of a weapon together. Strapping tape does not rip, break or tear and makes a great light-weight reinforcement for cross guards, anchor points, thrusting tips and seams. Strapping tape is not used to cover a weapon, but is used under the duct tape to hold things together.</p>
<p>Gaffer Tape: This incredibly durable tape is used in stagecraft. It is a very dense strong tape. This type of tape should not be used on any striking surface of a weapon due to its weight and lack of give. It is useful for making sturdy crossguards.</p>
<p>Weapon Sock: This is sewn piece of fabric (that should be water repellent) that can be used to cover the striking surface of a weapon. This is used sometimes instead of taping the blade of a weapon. Ripstop nylon is a good fabric to use for this.</p>
<h1>How to Make a Weapon</h1>
<p>Constructing a weapon requires time and patience, but it is not that hard once you have practiced a bit. The next section will describe the steps to create various weapons, but focused on a basic one handed edged weapon.</p>
<p>In each of the steps, there will be a description of the materials and techniques.</p>
<h2>Tools and materials:</h2>
<p>Below is a list of tools and a list of materials you'll need to make most weapons.</p>
<h2>Materials</h2>
<p>1. Core</p>
<p>2. Closed cell foam</p>
<p>3. Duct tape</p>
<p>4. 2" x 2" x weapon diameter Open Cell foam tip(s)</p>
<h3>Tools</h3>
<p>1. Marker</p>
<p>2. Measuring tool</p>
<p>3. Stapping/Duct tape</p>
<p>4. Saw</p>
<p>5. Scissors/Xacto/</p>
<p>6. Carving knife</p>
<h4>1. The core of the weapon</h4>
<p>After gathering your materials, the next step in creating a weapon is selecting an appropriate core for the type of weapon that you wish to make. You will need to do several things to prepare the core for weapon construction. First you will need to determine the length of the weapon that you wish make. Then you will have to cut the core approximately 3 inches shorter than the overall length of the weapon, 5 for weapons that require thrusting tips on both ends. This allows for padding both ends and the thrusting tip(s).</p>
<p>Cut the core to the right length with a hacksaw. If you are using a fibrous material, like kitespar, wrap a piece of tape around the area you are cutting to keep the fibers from fraying. Take care not to score areas that will be on your finished weapons. You will then need to clean up the edges of the cut so that there are no burrs or other protrusions. Lastly, you will need to cover both ends of the core with tape so there are no open ends.</p>
<h4>2. Pad the striking area</h4>
<p>The next step in creating a weapon is padding the striking area of the weapon. There are several things that you will need to do in this step. First, you should measure and cut the pipe foam to the desired blade/shaft length. Remember to measure the blade length to account for the the thrusting tip and the 1/2" overhang from the core. Next, you should slide the pipe foam over the core so that a 1/2?of foam hangs over one end. Make sure that the foam is snug to the core; if it rattles then the closed cell foam is too large and you will need to build out the core so that foam does not rattle. Cut off 1?of pipe foam (not from the piece you are using for the blade) and cut it into two equal halves. Compress one of the halves and stuff it into the end of the blade foam. Using a piece of tape, cover the small piece of foam that has been put into the end of the blade.</p>
<h4>3. Add a crossguard (optional)</h4>
<p>The next step is an optional step when creating a weapon though it is strongly encouraged. Certain weapon types have cross guards, including most types of swords and occasionally other hafted weapons. First, you need to cut a section of closed cell pipe foam of the appropriate size. Then cut a hole in the middle of the cross guard foam and slide the crossguard down the core until it meets the blade. Secure the crossguard to the blade using two strips of duct tape, then stuff the ends of the crossguard with open cell foam to strengthen the crossguard. Close off the ends of the crossguard with tape. Secure the cross guard to the grip by taking strips of tape from the crossguard to the grip. This will secure the blade and crossguard to the grip.</p>
<h4>4. Add a pommel</h4>
<p>The next step is to add a pommel at the end of the weapon. Cut a piece of closed cell foam so that is about 3 inches long. Place the foam on the butt end of the weapon so that the foam hangs at least one inch over the weapon? core. As with the blade tip, place a half circle of compressed closed cell foam into the end of the foam and cover it with tape. Secure the pommel to the core with tape in such a way that at least one inch of closed cell foam extends past the core. Make sure that the pommel is secure to the core and is not loose. </p>
<h4>6. Add a thrusting tip</h4>
<p>The tip of the striking surface must have a thrusting tip. This tip is 2" of open cell foam. Longer thrusting tips tend to bend. Cut the foam to cover the tip. Once the tip is in place, use tape to cover it. Take a length of tape and place it so it goes across the end of the tip and down both sides, attaching the tip to the weapon. If the tip is round, use a razor to cut the corners so the tape conforms to the tip. Now add another piece of tape so that it goes across the end and down the exposed sides of the foam tip. Use a razor to cut the corners so the tape overlaps slightly and conforms to the tip. Finally, poke many tiny holes all over the tip so the air can escape and the tip can contract and expand freely.</p>
<h4>7. Cover the blade</h4>
<p>The next step is to cover the exposed foam with tape or with a weapon sock. Any striking surface on a weapon should be covered with either a weapon sock or tape. If you choose to use tape, all of the tape on the striking surface of a weapon should run vertically from the thrusting tip to the pommel and should slightly overlap the piece next to it. Do not use overuse tape on striking surfaces and thrusting tips, one layer with slight overlap is enough. Excessive layering may make your weapon hard and un-passable. Tape should NEVER be spiral wrapped around the weapon.</p>
<h4>8. Add a grip</h4>
<p>The last step of the weapon making process is to cover the exposed grip with tape so that it is easy to wield. Use electrical tape or hockey grip tape spiral wrapped around the grip section of the weapon, so that it can be held easily. If the weapon is not thick enough to comfortably wield, you may use padding beneath the grip tape.</p>
<h2>Maintaining Your NERO Weapon</h2>
<p>Any latex foam or boffer swords must be stored and maintained properly in order to remain safe. There are a few simple things you can do to increase the longevity of your weapon.</p>
<p>Do not store foam weapons in extreme heat or cold for any length of time. Storing it in your car in the sun may cause paints to stick, tape to wrinkle and general degradation of the weapon over time.</p>
<p>Avoid soaking weapons in water and do not use your weapons if they have become waterlogged.</p>
<p>Do not rest weapons on the tips, lean on the foam ends or otherwise mash the foam at the ends. The tip foam will break down leaving less padding on the core, which will lead to failure of weapons safety check.</p>
<p>You may want to consider a fabric bag for individual latex weapons to keep their finish protected while in storage. </p>
<h2>Shields</h2>
<p>Safety is the prime consideration when constructing a shield. You may use almost any strong material such as wood, plastic or aluminum, but all edges must be covered with 5/8?pipe insulation. The face and edges of your shield may not have any sharp edges, bolts or other protuberances that would potentially cut or otherwise injure another person.</p>
<p>The longest dimension of a shield may not exceed 36 inches, including the pipe foam that covers the edges. The maximum area of a shield is 531 square inches (a 26" diameter circle). The area of a shield includes any cavities, recesses, voids or holes in the shield. A shield may be made in any shape, be it circular, oval, "Kite" or "Coffin" shaped, teardrop shaped or make to another design. The parts of a shield consist of the face, padded edging, and handle. Corrugated plastic, round sled blanks or wood are inexpensive and easy to cut to your preferred shape. You can obtain a handle from almost any hardware store, and then use a 1" to 1 1/2" strip of nylon strapping, or part of a belt to make the strap that will hold the shield to your forearm.</p>
<p>Take care to attach the handle and strap in a manner that does not leave sharp bolts or edges on the outside of your shield and trim any edges on the inside that may cut the shield user. While a shield may not be used offensively at NERO, and may not be used for "Shield bashing" it is possible that you could trip or fall on your shield, or someone else could fall into you. Safety is important, and any shield not considered safe by a weapons marshal will be failed at safety check.</p>
<h2>Potions</h2>
<p>The effects of potions and scrolls are the same as for a cast spell. </p>
<p>A scroll or potion physical representation is not valid unless it has an actual scroll or potion tag attached to the phys-rep. Likewise, a scroll or potion tag without a physical representation is also invalid. If you receive tags without physical representations (for example, after using your Production Points to create items), then it is your responsibility to provide the appropriate physical representation and make sure the tag is attached. All potion phys-reps must be large enough to hold, or appear to hold, at least a minimum of a quarter ounce of liquid. The phys-rep does not actually have to contain any liquid to be valid. </p>
<p>When the potion is used, the ?sed?potion tag must be given to the recipient or a Marshal as appropriate. To use a potion, you must role-play the proper drinking motions, and this must take at least three seconds. You do not have to count it out loud.</p>
<p>A potion may be ?orce fed?to an unconscious or sleeping person by someone else, but such a character cannot ?ccidentally?drink one. You cannot attach a potion or elixir to your collar or shield and ?ite?into it to get its effects while bound or in battle. Potions cannot be mixed into food or drink or diluted or mixed together in any way. All potions affect the drinker only, and bypass any protective spells such as Shield Magic or Reflect Magic. Note that potions affect only the drinker and do not give the drinker the ability to cast the spell effect of the particular potion. For example, a person drinking a Dispel Magic potion does not gain the ability to cast a Dispel Magic instead, the potion will dispel all magic on the drinker.</p>
<h2>Scrolls</h2>
<p>To use a scroll, you must pull out the scroll, hold it before you, have enough light to be able to read it, touch a spell packet to the scroll, actually read the scroll, and then throw the packet. If your scroll is attached to a weapon or shield, you may not be swinging it while reading the scroll. </p>
<p>After the scroll is used, the tag is removed but the paper remains. The magical writing is inert although anyone can tell what spell used to be on the scroll. You must have an actual scroll phys-rep for each scroll tag.</p>
<p>All scroll phys-reps must be at least 16 square inches (For example, a scroll that is 2 inches tall by 8 inches long would be fine).</p>
<h2>Alchemy </h2>
<p>Players with the skill of Alchemy can create certain contact substances, elixirs and gases. These substance do not detect as magical by Detect Magic. Alchemical effects are not affected by Dispel Magic.</p>
<p>Anyone can drink an elixir or feed one to someone else or apply Vorpal Coatings. To apply other poisons you need one level of Alchemy. To throw gas globes you must have the same number of alchemy levels as the gas?production level. In essence you must be able to make a gas to throw it.</p>
<h3>Creating Alchemical Substances</h3>
<p>Alchemy is a production skill and is governed by the Production system as described in The skill System chapter page 33. You may make any alchemical substance that you possess the skill to make that has a cost in the Production Levels chart.</p>
<h3>Damage from Alchemy</h3>
<p>Characters can be affected by alchemical substances in many ways. The effects are instantaneous. "Cause" poisons do body damage only, since they bypass armor. This damage can not be reversed by an antidote, but can be healed as normal damage. Berserk, Feeblemind, Hallucinoid, Nausea, Paralyze, Sleep, and Vertigo are all visible to any viewer while they are in effect, so long as they take the time to observe them and ask the affected player "Visible Effects" and the affected player will respond Visibly (effect)ed? Many substances can be reversed by a specific antidote if taken after exposure to the substance. The spell defensive Poison Shield will not stop ingested substances from taking effect, but will stop all other attacks with the word "Poison" in the verbal. The spell Purify Blood will cleanse the body of all active poison effects present except for Enslavement. Al chemical Solvents, Vorpal Coatings, Liquid Lights, Pastes of Stickiness , and Oils of Slipperiness are not affected by Purify Blood and will not set off a Poison Shield or a Resist Poison.</p>
<h3>Mind Effect Restrictions</h3>
<p>A chapter may, at their option, restrict the use of the following effects: Ensl avement, Forget-It-Well , and Forget-Me-Not. The chapter may restrict these effects in one of two ways. They can choose these effects to be void and unusable in their chapter, or they may opt to allow their usage only against NPCs.</p>
<p>Information on whether your local chapter uses the Mind Effect Restrictions rule, and which Game Effects this rule applies to will be available on the chapter? Web site, and will also be announced at the Opening Ceremonies of all of their events. </p>
<h2>Types of Alchemical Substances</h2>
<h3>Elixirs</h3>
<p>Elixirs may be drunk like potions or they may be placed in food or drink. This is signified by either attaching the tag to the underside of the food vessel, placing a token in the food, or having a marshal witness you make pouring motions over the food or drink. Mixing two elixirs does not cancel the elixirs. If a food or drink has more than one elixir present, all elixirs will affect the victim and be used up after the first bite or drink. One use of the racial skill Resist Poison will block all elixirs present.</p>
<h3>Gases</h3>
<p>Gases are delivered by an orange packet. Unlike a spell packet, gas containers are in-game. They work on a single target, indoors or outdoors. Before throwing the packet, the user must announce ?Type> gas poison;?for example ?leep gas poison.?This phrase simulates preparing the gas. The ?erbal?is not in-game so even a silenced or mute character may use one. If the ?erbal?is not said properly then the attack is unsuccessful as the gas was not ?repared?properly (Imagine preparing a hand grenade). The packet must hit the target or the target? possessions and otherwise must follow all spell packet rules. Even though the ?erbal?is not in-game, the effect is recognized by anyone who hears it. (In-game, assume each gas has a different color and texture associated with it to allow for identification.) If the poison does numerical damage, the number is added to the end of the "Verbal" and must Figure 7-4. c Contact: ffl?ixir: (__^ Gas: ( ?| be said before the packet is thrown. Thrown Alchemy is subject to Disruption.</p>
<p>Note that gas globes, since they are in-game, can be fumbled and stolen. To steal a globe, you must steal the actual globe physical representation itself and not the tag. You may then either go out-of-game to the person from whom you stole the globes in order to get the tags, or can get a Marshal to do it.</p>
<p>Gases can also be put into gas traps. See "Gas Traps" on page 97.</p>
<h3>Contact Poisons</h3>
<p>Contact poisons must be represented by a gel-like substance that can be smeared on the object to be trapped. (Petroleum jelly works fine). If the person applying the substance comes in contact with it, he or she will be affected as well (if applicable). poison shield and resist poison will protect the victim from being affected by contact poisons. Multiple contact poisons which would normally affect a victim simultaneously are protected by a single poison Shield or resist poison.</p>
<h3>Vorpal Coatings</h3>
<p>Vorpal Coatings add 5 points to the base damage of the weapon, for a set number of hits per application. They take effect immediately, doing damage to Armor Points and then Body Points after all Armor Points have been removed.</p>
<p>Damage should be called by adding 5 points to the weapon damage (with any other magical or skill bonuses also added, of course).</p>
<p>A hit is used up only if the strike lands or it is negated by a defense, but cannot be saved up to use on later swings once applied; the damage increase is for the first 1, 3, or 5 hits depending on the coating used. </p>
<p>Applying a vorpal coating takes time to apply. It cannot be done with a quick touch in the middle of battle. The tag must be taped onto the weapon. The taping of the tag onto the weapon represents the time it takes, which may never be less than three seconds. If you do not have the tag taped to your weapon then the vorpal coating is not effective. A new tag must be put on the weapon each time a new vorpal coating is applied. Only one vorpal coating can be on a weapon at a time.</p>
</body></Root>